[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
Okay, well, welcome to CS193P,
Stanford CS193P.
This is Developing
Applications for iOS, winter
of 2017. Today we're going to
talk a little bit about what
this class is about, and
the prerequisites you need.
Then I'm, really fast, gonna
go over iOS and what's in it.
And then, I'm gonna dive
into a big, long demo.
And this demo is gonna really
quickly let you see what it's
like to develop an application
for iOS, so you can decide,
is this for me, or not?
So, what are you gonna learn?
Well you're gonna learn to
build cool apps, all right,
that's, that's what we're here
for. Why are these apps in iOS
cool? Well for
a number of reasons, okay?
One is they're in
your back pocket,
you can pull them out and show
your friends on your phone,
a lot of them are networked so
there're kind of social
apps and a lot of that
can be a lot of fun.
Also if you decide to turn
your app into a product it's
really easy to get it out to
customers via the app store.
You don't have to
wrap it in a box and
put it on a shelf somewhere
anymore. You can get it out
there real quick.
And also you're going to see,
today even, it's really easy
to build pretty complex
app pretty quickly. So you get
a lot of instant gratification
from building iOS apps.
For those of you in
computer science there's also
this huge benefit, you're
gonna get to see a real life
object-oriented programming
system. And not just
object-oriented programming,
but we're going to use
databases in this class, and
graphics, and multimedia,
multi-threading, animation,
networking, all these things.
And
you're going to see it in
a real world environment.
So you take a lot of
classes on these subjects
and sometimes you get maybe
a little disconnected from
what's this like in
the real world, well,
you're gonna get to see it all
in action here. Prerequisites,
just boiling it down really
easily. The prerequisite for
the class is object-oriented
programming.
You have to know
object-oriented programming,
I'm not gonna teach that in
the class, I completely and
utterly assume it. And not
only do you have to know it,
you have to have some
experience doing it.
So that's why here at
Stanford CS106 A and
B are a hard prerequisite. You
have to have taken those two,
those are object-oriented
programming classes. And
then I just want to make sure
you have some programming
experience, so either you've
done something outside
of school, or you've taken
CS107 or CS108 or CS110.
CS108 is a particularly
great prerequisite,
that's object-oriented
programming.
So if you have a chance
to take CS108 and
you haven't taken it yet,
yeah, maybe taken it, and
then take this class the next
time it's offered, all right?
So let's dive through what's
in iOS really quickly here.
I've divided it here
into four layers.
These layers are roughly
close to the hardware.
And then up close to the user.
So that bottom layer close to
the hardware, that's actually
a Unix operating system, okay?
Just like macOS, iOS is
a Unix operating system at
the bottom. None of these
APIs are object oriented or
anything, they're basically C,
okay? For
the Unix pretty much written
in C, these API's are in C.
We're gonna do no work at that
level in this class, okay?
This is an object-oriented
programming only class,
so we're not gonna be
doing anything there.
So there's another layer right
on top of that called core
services. Sometimes people
refer to this as foundation,
but there's other things
in this lever, layer,
besides foundation. And this
is an object oriented layer
on top of those things that
were lower down. Okay, so
now you can do networking,
file system, things like that,
using object oriented API. But
this is still non UI layer,
right? It's still kinda closer
to the hardware. So I'll
definitely be teaching you
a lot of stuff at this layer,
'cause you just need it to do
the things you're gonna do.
Now, there's another layer
here, the media layer here I
call it. This is a huge layer,
which has 3D graphics, and
audio playback and recording,
image processing, video,
all that stuff. Unfortunately
I'm not gonna have a lot of
time to spend here, even
though it's a huge part of
what an iOS device does. iOS
devices all pretty much have
iPods in them, video iPods
if you wanna think about it.
And so there's a lot here.
Unfortunately I can't cover it
all. Because I'm gonna spend
most of my time up here,
which is
the Cocoa Touch layer.
This is where buttons and text
fields and things are, but
also much more powerful
objects like maps.
There's an object in Cocoa
Touch which is a map object,
it's pretty much the entire
Maps application on
an iOS device, that you can
drop right into a rectangle
in your app.
With almost no work.
So, very powerful object to
this layer. This is where
we're gonna spend the vast
majority of our time,
building user interface
apps at this layer.
That's a rough overview.
Trying to explain all
of iOS in two minutes is
pretty much impossible, but
that's kind of what we're
doing in this class. We're
gonna use all these components
to get our work done.
Top level there,
Xcode 8, is gonna be...
everything we do is
gonna be in Xcode 8.
The debugger, the editor,
everything, building,
it's all in Xcode 8. There's
a little app, Instruments,
that goes along with it, for
performance and stuff, but
pretty much it's all Xcode 8.
Two, I'm gonna teach you
a new programming language.
So if you're computer science
people, you know that learning
different programming
languages, really
valuable skill.
Not because you're necessarily
gonna use all of them,
some you might or might not
use. But just the process of
seeing how language designers
pick and choose their syntax
and, and the feature set,
is really valuable.
So you'll get that I would
think. It's a great language.
It was just invented in the
last two or three years, so
it kind of incorporates
the best of a lot of different
languages. So I'm gonna kind
of blitzkrieg teach that to
you in the first couple weeks.
Frameworks: That's essentially
things like the Cocoa
Touch UIKit framework.
It's where all the buttons and
stuff are.
Foundation is that, kind of,
mostly that core
services layer.
But there's a lot of other
ones like Core Data framework,
object-oriented database,
we'll be doing that
in assignment five.
Also I talked about that map
thing, that's in a framework
called MapKit. And there's
also things in core motion,
like the accelerometer and
the gyro in the device.
All those things, I'm gonna
be teaching you many,
many of these frameworks
as we go on. And
last, but definitely
not least, and very,
very important,
is the design strategy for
how to build apps, it's called
MVC, model-view-controller.
How many people already
know MVC, have,
have learned in
a different class?
See, so maybe half of you.
I will spend the first part of
Wednesday's lecture telling
you about MVC and what it is.
We 100.0% have to use MVC
when we develop apps for iOS.
There's really no other way to
do it, if you do it any other
way, you're swimming so up
stream against the current of
iOS, it's... You'll end up
with a mess of an application,
okay, so we'll be going over
that as well. This demo
that I'm gonna do, we're
gonna build a calculator.
A calculator's great because
it's got a fairly simple UI,
but it's got a little bit
of guts on the inside,
the actual calculating part.
So
it's just complicated enough
to start showing you MVC and
a lot of language features and
things like that. But not so
complicated that I can't do an
entire calculator, basically,
in two lectures, okay, start
to finish. All these topics up
here, you don't have
to look at them now.
This is the slide to go look
at after my lecture today and
say, hmm did I learn that,
yeah,
I think I got that. So
it's kind of a summary of what
I'm gonna do. Since I'm not
gonna get back to the slides
from the end of my demo,
it's just gonna be
the end of the lecture.
I'll tell you a little
bit what's coming up.
On Wednesday, I'll be
continuing this demo, but
not until after I give
you this talk about MVC,
because what we're gonna do in
the calculator is apply MVC
to it, on Wednesday.
And your first
programming assignment will
go out on Wednesday, which is
pretty much to replicate
what I'm doing today and
on Wednesday, okay? And I'll
give you a video of the demo,
so you'll see it, and you'll
be able to watch it. And
then on Friday,
we have an optional section.
So the Friday sections
in this course,
you don't have to go to
if you don't want to.
But a lot of times,
they're very valuable.
Feature so if you have not
used the debugger in Xcode 8
you really might wanna
go to Friday's lecture.
The location and time of it
will be posted on the class
forums hopefully tomorrow.
I've asked for the room and
haven't quite got it yet
so hopefully tomorrow. And
then don't forget next Monday
is a holiday so we're not
meeting on Monday. Our next
class after this Wednesday
will be next Wednesday.
So let's hop into the demo...
I said we were gonna build
a calculator, let me actually
show you a calculator. This
is the MacOS calculator and
our calculator is gonna look
very similar to this, right?
It has to display along
the top, it has the keypad for
typing numbers in and it's got
these operation buttons. And
then you can just multiply,
times eight, you hit equals,
it does the operation,
that's pretty much what our
calculator is gonna do.
It's not gonna look exactly
like this. It's gonna have
a look that's a little more
appropriate for a iOS device,
but it's generally this. And
I promised that Xcode would be
your one-stop shop for
doing all development, so
we're gonna spend our entire
time here working in Xcode.
Now Xcode is an app that you
just go to the Mac App Store,
and you download it.
It's free.
When you first launch it,
it's gonna put up this splash
screen like you
see right here.
And all of your projects are
going to start accumulating
here over on this right side
where this gray area is. And
you can basically do three
other things here. You can use
a playground, which I'll show
the playgrounds on Wednesday,
it's kind of a little play
area for iOS programming. You
can check a existing project
out of a source control
management system which
we're not gonna be doing.
Although we're probably
have a Friday section
on doing a source code
control. So we're gonna be
doing this option right here,
create a new X code project.
And in fact, when I do
demos in this course,
I almost always
start from scratch.
Cuz I don't want you
to have to like,
come up to speed on some code
that I give you first, and
then, learn from there. So we
try to start from scratch, and
see what we can do that way.
So I'm gonna click on this,
to start a new app.
It's asking, what kind
of app do we want to build,
or what kind of project, and
here you can see, we can do
Watch apps, Apple TV apps,
even Mac OS apps, but
we're doing iOS, and in fact,
we're always going to choose
this single view application
template. It's
the simplest template, and
some of these other templates
have code in there that I
actually want to show you how
to write yourself instead of
having the template just make
that code appear, all right?
So we're gonna do single
view application.
Now it wants some particulars
on our application,
most importantly at
the top its name. Well,
we're building a calculator so
we're gonna call this
Calculator, okay, that's
gonna be the name of our app.
Now this second line here,
team, that's the team of
developers who are gonna work
on this project, that's gonna
be a team of one, which is
you. Okay, when you launch
Xcode, this is probably not
going to be a pull down list.
It's gonna be a button
that says Add Account or
something like that, Add Team.
You click on that, all you'll
need is an Apple ID, any Apple
ID will do, won't cost you any
money. And go through
the dialog there and
it'll add a team for you, and
you use that here. Alright?
This organization name
can be anything you want.
It's just gonna appear on the
copyright symbol at the top of
your source code files,
that's it. But this one,
it's super important that this
be a unique identifier of you.
Okay? So I strongly recommend
doing edu.stanford.cs193p.
You're SUNet ID here, okay?
If you put that in there,
you're almost guaranteed,
if you're a Stanford student,
for that to be unique. If
you're not a Stanford student,
you're watching this on iTunes
U, pick something else that
uniquely identifies you.
Hopefully,
reverse DNS notation will work
in your circumstance as well.
The language we're gonna
use like I said is Swift.
iOS was originally written in
a different language called
Objective-C. Turns out you
can use Objective-C and
Swift in the same application.
They use the exact same
underlying iOS API. So
everything you're gonna learn
in this class in Swift,
if you later went and learned
Objective-C, all that learning
would be valid, okay?
Cuz it's the exact, in fact,
it's the exact same code base,
it's not just same API.
Swift was designed in a way
to be quite compatible with
Objective-C's APIs.
And in the last couple years,
they've even enhanced
Objective-C to catch up with
some of the advanced stuff
that Swift does. Our app that
we're going to build,
our calculator is going to
be universal. That means it's
going to run on iPhone and
on iPad. First couple weeks,
it will be iPhone only but
then, eventually, we'll
add iPad support, as well.
We're not gonna be using
a database in the calculator,
but we will in your assignment
five. And when it comes to
testing, which is super
important, again, I'm hoping
to have a Friday section to
tell you a lot about testing,
especially the UI testing
framework is really awesome,
okay, so hopefully we'll get
a chance to show you that. So
I'm just gonna click next
here to create my app.
It says, where do you wanna
put this project? I recommend
you put it home directory in a
folder called Developer. Okay?
Then all your apps will
just pile up in here.
This is pretty much
a canonical place to put it so
I strongly recommend it. And
then again source control is
more for teams working on it.
You're gonna be working
this by yourself so
you can leave this
switched off.
All right, here's our,
there's your load.
There's your first IOS app,
okay? Now let me explain
a little bit about Xcode and
how it's laid out here.
So if you haven't seen it...
How many people have worked
in Xcode before? See, so
again probably half of you so
quite a few. For those of you
who haven't, it's divided into
these three main sections
here. This main section in the
middle is the primary place
you're going to do all your
source code editing and
things like that. That's where
you do most of your work.
This section over here on
the left, this blue section is
called the navigator. You use
it to navigate your project.
And here you're seeing
it in a file based view,
where I'm looking at all
my files. And we'll look at
those in a second. But
you can navigate by searching,
okay, there's a search panel.
If you, if you're debugging,
you can navigate through all
the break points that you
have, etc. So, you'll learn
all about the different
ways that you can navigate,
as the quarter goes on.
On the right hand side here
you see this little area,
this is called
the utilities window.
And I'm gonna talk all about
this in about five minutes,
okay, we're gonna use this
in great detail. I want to
show you a little bit how you
can manage your space here.
If you look in the upper right
you see these buttons here.
You can click this one
over here to hide and
show. That utilities window.
And same thing over here for
the navigator. So that can
make more space for you.
All right, and there's another
one here, this middle.
That hides something
from the bottom.
This is your debugger
window on the left and
your console, which is
a place where you can log
strings out to while you're
debugging, on the right. And
we'll see that in a moment
as well. All right, so
let's go look at these files,
right?
We're in the file navigator
here on the left. And
there's six files here but
four of them are really
just supporting files, and
we're not not even gonna look
at them in the calculator.
We'll look at a couple of them
as the quarter goes on but,
they're not primary files.
And for example, this one
Assets.xcassets, Xcode assets.
This is images and videos that
might be embedded in your app.
You can see it's the app icon,
I haven't set any of my app
icons, you can see them. But
this xcassets and the Launch
Screen and this Info.plist and
this AppDelegate here. By the
way, I'm pulling down command,
you see in the lower left you
can see any command keys that
I press right down there cuz
I'm gonna use command keys for
various things that we do. So
I use command to
select all these. And
I'm just gonna right click and
go down to here, New Group
From Selection. And it's gonna
put these four files into
their own little folder.
There, it did it, I'm gonna
call it Supporting Files,
okay. And I can move these
around in the navigator.
See there they are, hidden in
there. We're not gonna look at
those. We're gonna focus in
these two files right here,
okay? This file, is your first
look at Swift. Here it is.
It's got some very important
methods right here, which I'm
gonna delete. Okay? They are
important, but the fact that
I deleted them doesn't
make them not important.
It's just that I'm not gonna
teach you about them for
another couple weeks.
So we're not gonna use them in
the calculator. And in fact,
I'm gonna go into detail
about this Swift code more
in a moment.
But before I do that,
I wanna focus on this file
right here, Main.storyboard.
This is your user interface.
This is calculator's user
interface. And one thing you
notice when I click on that,
there's no code here. When
you build your user interface
in iOS app in Xcode,
you do not write code.
We're just gonna to build it
with the mouse. We're gonna
drag some things out. We're
gonna use some inspectors to
set the objects we want. The
way we want them. That's how
we're gonna build our UI.
That code that you saw.
That is only gonna control
the behavior of the UI.
What happens when you touch on
a button? Things like that.
That's what's gonna be
controlled by that code. But
the actual layout of all the
buttons and all that stuff.
Is gonna be done here
in this graphical view.
Now you can see there's this
area here on the left, okay?
This is like, this is
called document outline.
If you're down here you'll
see a little button there.
The document outline.
The document outline has
all the things in the user
interface in an outline form.
And that's gonna
be very useful for
us. Later in the quarter.
So, I'm gonna hide that.
That's this little button
down here is. It hides and
shows it. We're gonna hide
that to make more space.
We're not gonna use that in
the calculator either. So
that leaves this
space here in,
if I zoom in on
a little bit here,
or zoom out rather. You can
see I start to see something
that looks like an iPhone.
Okay, it's kinda iPhone
shaped, I can also by the way
hold down the option key and
use my mouse wheel to zoom in
here. Okay, so this is like
an iPhone, in particular
it looks like an iPhone 7.
You see down here at the
bottom it says view as iPhone
7, all right? And if I
click on view as iPhone 7,
you'll see all the other
iOS devices appear- iPads,
for example. Or old iPhone 4s,
they're really kinda little.
And not only are they there
but you can switch their
orientation, okay?
Now when you build an iOS app,
you want the UI to look good
on all these devices. And
you don't wanna have to
write a lot of special if,
then code all over the place
to make them work. So, this
whole system that, of building
our UI, which by the way,
is call Interface Builder.
This part of Xcode is called
Interface Builder, is oriented
with a lot of functionality
to make you, make it so
you can build your UI once and
it will work on all these
devices. Now, I'm not gonna
actually start doing that
until the end of the lecture
on Wednesday. So, for now,
we're just gonna build our UI,
it's gonna be kinda a mess.
We'll throw buttons anywhere
we want. We're not really,
really working in
landscape mode like this
vs portrait or small
device or large device, ok?
We're not gonna worry about
that right off the bat but you
just wanna preview the fact
that we are eventually gonna
build this universal UI
that works on all of them.
So here's our iPhone 7.
We wanna start building our
UI. What do we need? We need
buttons and we need a kinda
a display across the top.
Let's start with the buttons.
Where do we get these buttons?
Well, as promised. I'm gonna
talk about this utilities area
right here. Now, this
utilities area has a top and
a bottom. You see that?
And in the bottom,
right here, under this region
called the object library, is
a library of IOS objects that
you can build your app out of.
And it has things like
buttons. Text fields,
it has more complicated
things like image views and
text views, which are multi
line and editable text ,and it
even has things like that map
thing I was telling you about.
Or a web view, which is
basically Safari in a little
rectangle. So it's got a lot
of powerful things and
there's a lot of them in here.
And we will try to cover
the vast majority of these in
the course of the quarter.
But it's almost really
too much to cover. So
we're gonna start though
simple with a button. And
if I want a button in my UI,
I just pick it up with
the mouse, okay, and drag it
in. Now when I drag it in, see
these blue lines are trying to
help me put it in a good spot.
You see that? Now, we're not
gonna pay attention to that
right now because I told you
we're doing this thing where
we're building the app that'll
work on all devices. But
when we start thinking about
putting it on an app that
works on all devices we
really wanna use these dashed
blue lines. Okay, because if
you say something like I want
this to be in the center.
Well now it'll be on
the center on every device,
no matter what this size
of the screen, you see? So
these blue lines help you
communicate that to interface
builder, that you wanna it in
the exact center. So again,
we're not gonna worry
about that for now, so
I'm just gonna drop this in
the middle of nowhere. But
again, those blue lines are
gonna be very important down
the road. All right so
we've got this button here.
It's not [LAUGH]
a very good button,
because it's kinda small and
it says button on it.
And we want it to be let's say
one of our number buttons.
Okay, so
how are we gonna do that?
Well, we can double
click on it. And
type one of our numbers, I'll
make this be my 7 button, so
this is gonna be my 7 button
on my calculator. And I can
resize it, you see when I
select it I get these handles.
So I can just pick it up
by a corner and resize it.
And when I do, it even
tells me exactly what size.
So let's pick maybe
a size like mm, 64 by 64?
That's a pretty good
computer science size can be
a little tricky then. Do it
there, there, there we go.
Okay, so we get 64 by 64 now.
Actually the size is not even
gonna matter in the long term,
because on a smaller device
like an iPhone 4 it's gonna be
shrunk down and
on another device it's gonna
be shrunk out. But for now,
will pick some that's kinda
using a reasonable amount of
the screen real state on
an iPhone 7. This is still
kinda a small seven. We want
it larger. So when we wanna do
things like that that's
when we go to the top half.
I'm just gonna get rid of this
bottom half by scrolling it
down here. We're gonna the top
half of this utilities pane.
And this is inspector and
there's different kinds of
inspectors. We're gonna be
using the attribute inspector
here, but there's also, for
example, a size inspector.
And when I click on that, you
see that there's the 64 by 64,
I could have just typed
it in instead of trying
to get it exactly on there.
Okay. The attributes inspector
is kinda an object
oriented inspector.
You can see that it knows
a button is selected, so
it's showing you
button things.
Things that you can set
about a button. But
a button is a class, object
ordinate class that inherits
from control, so you're
seeing control things, and
that inherits from view, so
you're seeing view things.
So this inspector is
object orientated and
shows you all the things that
can be inspected about this
object even using inheritance.
So if I wanna change something
like the font, I just look
down here, title, here it is.
Font. Right here.
I'm gonna click on this and
I'm gonna change this to
30 point let's say. Okay.
That looks pretty good.
Now, maybe I wanna have
a background for this button.
So, if I look in here there's
that background image. I don't
want a background image.
I actually want
a background color. So
there's nothing in
button that does that.
But, If I go down to view. I
can see background right here
that's a color. And if I click
on this, I can pick a color,
one of these pre-defined
colors, or other colors, let
me choose from Color Picker a
little crayon box or whatever.
So I'm just gonna pick
from here the light gray.
That looks like a good
background color. So
now I've got a button, okay?
Here's a nice button.
In fact, we could even run,
see what our app looks like.
Just with one button.
Now when it comes to running,
the way you decide where
you wanna run your program,
because you can run it on your
device or you can actually run
it on a simulator. Okay, and
for the first few weeks in
this class you can
use the simulator.
Towards the end of
the class I'm gonna
ask you to start running
on your device so
you get used to doing that as
well. But the way you do that
is you go up here. You see it
says calculator iPhone 7 plus.
If you click on that
you'll see a whole
bunch of simulators. These are
all simulators of all those
different devices that can run
iOS 10. And then right up at
the top here, you could pick,
if you had an actual device
connected to your Mac, you
could pick a physical device.
And I'll be showing you
that in a couple of weeks,
as well. So, let's run
it on iPhone 7, okay,
so I just picked iPhone 7, now
I'm going to press this little
play button right here to run
it. Okay, now it's going to
launch the simulator. Now that
simulator is a full iPhone
simulator, so it's not just
running our app in a window.
Let's go find it here.
It's over here, and
it's kind of big here, we'll
make it small in a second. So,
this, and in fact, there it
is. You can see it zoomed in,
now the iPhone 7 has
very high resolution, and
I'm running on a small
resolution screen. But
you can actually go down
here to scale, and scale it
down a bit. Maybe that's too
much. Let' scale it to here.
Yeah. So we're seeing 50%
size here of an iPhone 7.
And there's our 7 button
right there. Okay,
now, you can press
the Home button
on this iPhone 7 by going
to Hardware > Home. And
when you do that, look. This
looks just like an iPhone.
You've got settings. You can
go in and set some settings.
Okay? Do home again.
Cmd+Shift+H is home.
And then you can go
back to your app,
which is the calculator
right here. So
if you're writing an app, for
example, that uses GPS and
you need to go to the settings
to enable GPS location.
You can do that here on
your simulator, okay?
All right, so we got the 7
button, let's click it. Okay,
well, It's flashing, so it
looks like it's working, but
of course, it's not doing
anything. We haven't told our
7 button what to do, so it's
doing nothing, all right? So
let's go make it do something.
Now I told
you that the behavior of
the UI is written in code. So
that's what this guy over here
is, this ViewController.swift.
That's the code where we're
gonna do the behavior. And so,
how do we hook up this UI to
this code? Well to do that,
we need to get them both
on screen at the same time,
all right? And the way we do
that is with this button,
right here,
assistant editor button.
So I'm gonna click it, and we
get both. And I can click for
example, on one side
to show my UI. And
it's automatically going to
show the code on the other
side. Okay, cuz it already,
it knows that I probably
wanted to do that. And
it does that because, up here
at the top you see it says,
automatic. It's automatically
picking it. Now you can go to
manual and manually pick the
file you want to appear here,
but most of the times you're
leave this on automatic. And
it's gonna pick automatically
the thing that makes the most
sense to be on the right
hand side. Okay,
we'll make some more space
there. All right? So
let's zoom this in
a little bit so
we can see the whole iPhone 7,
all right, so let's look at
this code first because this
is the first time
you've seen Swift.
Swift is really nice, because
it's kind of succinct and
kind of very obvious in the
keywords it's chosen, etc. So
import is like include in
a lot of languages, it's
just basically saying I want
to use this framework UIKit.
Now, this is our UI
behavior controlling code.
So of course,
it needs to use UIKit,
okay? If we were to write
an object that's more of like
the internals of
the calculator that's
UI independent,
then we would probably
import foundation here.
Foundation to kind of get to
that core services layer,
not UI. You would never want
to import UIKit in one of
those non-UI kind of classes.
And you'll see that when we do
the MVC on Wednesday. There's
of course other things we can
import too, like map kit,
things like that. All right,
so here you're seeing
your first declaration
of a Swift class. Okay?
Keyword class, of course.
Name, this is the name of
the class. ViewController is
name of class,
it's kind of a generic name.
Probably would have given it
a better name if I had had
a chance, but this is what
the template gave me.
You can't unfortunately
just rename this by typing,
because it's linked up to your
UI. I will show you how to
rename this class later. But
for now, we're going to stick
with this generic name. This
colon UI view controller is
the class that view controller
inherits from, okay? This is
object oriented programming,
this is inheritance.
Again, you have to know object
oriented programming to be
sitting in this room.
So you know what that means?
Swift is single inheritance.
So you can only inherit from
one class. And view controller
inherits from this class.
This class' capabilities are,
it knows how to control a UI.
That's why it's called a view
controller. We call this our
view over here, and
it knows how to control it.
So this view controller is
inheriting all the capability
of how to control this.
Which is great,
because that's exactly
what we want it to do. And
then inside the curly braces,
here we're going to put all of
our instance variables and
methods. Okay?
Hopefully everyone knows what
an instance variable and
An instance variable is like
storage of variables inside of
a method is, right?
our class, and a method is
just a function in there.
By the way, we call instance
variables in Swift properties.
So if you hear me
think properties,
I mean like instance
variables. Okay,
we call methods, methods.
So what I really want now
is that when this button is
touched, I want it to invoke
a method in my class, right?
I want it to call a method.
That would be perfect cuz
then I could put whatever
code I want in there. And
that's exactly what
we're gonna do.
Now the way we link that up is
kinda kooky. Here we go, I'm
gonna hold down Ctrl. You see
I'm holding Ctrl down there.
I'm going to drag from
this button into my code,
okay? This is how I'm gonna
connect it. And when I let go,
it says you wanna make a
connection between your UI and
this code, what kinda
connection do you want?
And there's really
two choices.
There's Outlet,
that means make a property or
an instance variable that
points to this thing, so
I can talk to it.
And then there's action,
which means make a method,
and when the buttons touch,
call this method.
Everybody got that?
All right, so here it's asking
for the name of this method.
I'm going to call this
method touchDigit.
Okay, touchDigit. And this
method, it can have arguments,
it could have no arguments,
or one argument which is,
the button sending me
this message. Now I need
that argument because I
want to have one touch
digit method that all my
buttons set. So I'm going to
ask the button who's sending
it to me, who are you?
What title,
are you the 7 button?
Are you the five button,
what are you? So
I want that sender.
This type right here,
it says Any, that's the type
of the argument. Very, okay,
wake-up if you're taking a nap
right now, and when you're
doing your homework,
you cannot lead this to any.
Because we know what kind of
thing is sending you this
message, it's a UI button, so
you're gonna wanna change this
to any to UI button.
If you miss that step and
when you go in there, your
code's all gonna be messed up,
because the argument type of
the sender is gonna be any,
which it just basically
means untyped, almost. So
that's no good. So make sure
you change this to UI button.
Now, when we connect this,
it creates a method. So
you're getting your first look
right here at a Swift method.
Now, this is actually
not part of Swift, okay.
This is something Xcode drops
in there. And it does it so
that it can put this little
circle in the gutter.
You see that circle
right there?
If I mouse over that circle,
look what happens.
I didn't click on it, I just
put my mouse over it. You see,
it tells me what this
method is hooked up to.
In other words, what user
interface element. Sends me
this message, okay? So this
is purely not a Swift thing,
this is purely an Xcode thing.
So this is a Swift method,
okay? So let's look at
the parts of a Swift method,
the syntax of it, so you
understand a little better.
And I'm gonna use a different
method that I'm just going to
make up for this.
Let's say I had some
function called
a drawHorizontalLine and
it draws from some
starting position,
which would be a Double
to some ending position,
which also be a Double.
And maybe it does it using
some color, which would
be a UI color. Okay? So
there's an example of a Swift
method. Notice that it,
this has three parameters. You
see? This one, this one and
this one. This ": Double" is
the type of this parameter.
So it's a double-precision
floating-point number. That's
the type of that parameter.
This one's also Double.
This one is a UIColor. Okay,
which is a different type.
Now what's really interesting
about parameters is that you
have two names for each one.
See, from startX,
to endX, using a color,
each one has two, so what
the heck is going on there
with those two? Well this one,
the first one, is the external
name of this parameter. And
this is the internal name.
So these internal names,
like startX, endX, and
color. You would use those in
your code inside this method.
Like, I might say,
distance = endX- startX, or
something like that.
See I'm using endX and startX
inside this method, right?
Part of it's implementation.
These external names
are used by the callers,
the people who call this
method. So I'm gonna call this
method from touchDigit here,
drawHorizontalLine.
Now, by the way,
Xcode loves to type for you.
So I just type drawH and now
I'm hitting tab. And tab, and
it's not only filling
out drawHorizontalLine,
but it's showing me
all the arguments and
tabbing to the first one so
I can type it. So notice that
when it said that, the from,
the to, and the using
were put in there for me. So
if I say from 5.0 to 8.5 using
the color UIColor.blue
let's say, okay?
These from and to and using
are what the caller uses.
Notice also, that these things
are mandatory. They have to go
in here. You can not call
drawHorizontalLine like this,
drawHorizontalLine 5.0, this
would be, look like most other
languages, you know, blue.
You can't call it like that.
You have to put these
external names in there.
Also notice that the external
names are picked so
this reads like English. Draw
a horizontal line from 5.0
to 8.5 using blue, okay?
Swift endeavors
to be as kind of
conversational in the language
of English as it can be. So
that's kinda crash course.
You're gonna be reading, your
reading assignment's gonna
tell you more about that, but
that's the crash course. But
now let's take a look at thi-,
by the way, if your
function returns something,
you just go like this, okay?
-> String. It's kind of like,
the arrow is saying, out of
this comes a String, okay?
So this would be
the return value, okay?
All right, now, let's look
at touchDigit though,
touchDigit is weird. Look at
its two things here, okay?
The external one is_, okay?
So does that mean I call
it by saying, touchDigit_:
whatever? No, underbar means
there is no external. So
you would call touchDigit
by just saying,
touchDigit (someButton)
cuz that's the argument,
it's a button or whatever.
Okay, there's no, you won't,
you don't put anything in
here, it's not like a foo.
If we had this it
would be foo, okay?
That's not in there. Instead,
it's this underbar, so
you have nothing. Okay?
Now, why do we sometimes have
nothing? Because sometimes,
it's implicit in either
the name of the function or
the type of the argument,
what you're supposed to pass,
so you don't need that little
thing. By the way underbar,
we almost never use that for
the second, third,
or fourth argument.
It's occasionally used for the
first argument, not always,
occasionally. But never for
second, third, fourth, fifth,
okay? Or next to never. Now
in your reading assignment,
I'm also going to have you
read a document that explains
how to do this naming.
What the rules are,
when do you use an underbar,
when don't you. You're gonna
wanna master that document by
the end of the quarter if
you wanna call yourself
a professional iOS developer,
okay?
It's key to understand that.
But this touchDigit, okay, so
this function, okay methods,
I, just to be clear, methods,
we use the keyword func.
Okay, cuz it's
a function on a class. This
is the name. Parameters go
in parentheses like this, they
can be separated by commas if
we have multiple of them. This
is the first parameter here,
first and only. It's type is
a UIButton because of course,
a UIButton is sending this
messa-, method. Right,
it's invoking this method. So
the sender is this UIButton.
And sender is
the internal name.
So that's the name we'll use
inside here to access it.
All right? But before we
start doing that, let's just
have this do something simple
like print out to the console.
So I'm gonna say,
print "touchDigit was called",
okay? We're just gonna print
that out on the console.
Whenever someone
touches a button,
it's gonna evoke this method.
It's gonna print
that on the console.
So let's just do that.
All right? So there's our UI,
iPhone 7. Click and touchDigit
appears in the console down
here at the bottom, okay?
Now the console shares
space with the debugger,
this area on the left is the
debugger. So you can kind of
separate this space back and
forth, you can also completely
hide this space by using these
buttons right here, okay?
So we'll just do console only
right here. Let's go back to
our simulator. And so
every time we press this,
we get touchDigit was
called printed out again.
Does everyone understand
what's happening here,
how we've hooked up this
method to the button? Really,
really straightforward. All
right, now that we have that
working, we know we need more
than just this one button,
we need a whole keypad's worth
of buttons. So I'm gonna,
I want these other buttons
to look exactly the same, so
I'm gonna copy and paste. So
I just copied and pasted that,
paste another one here. I can
even select three at a time,
and copy and paste, okay?
Paste another one.
Now notice here I'm using
the blue lines to line them up
okay, really nicely.
Blue lines are great for
doing that. Okay, and now I
can just rename these buttons
by just double-clicking
on them.
All right, so I've got an,
a beautiful keypad right here.
And what's really great is
that this method is hooked up
to all of them. Okay, that's
because when you copy and
paste a button, it keeps it's
connections to any methods
that it has, okay?
So that's cool. So
now all these buttons are
going to send this touchDigit.
So now if I run, you'll
see that if I press any of
these buttons, not just our
7 button. Right, here's 7,
that worked, but also 5,
0, they're all calling,
this touchDigit was called.
Okay, so that's awesome.
But of course, we want to
know which button was called,
was sending us this message,
right?
And we know that because
that's the argument,
is the sender, okay? So let's
add a local variable here.
So now you're seeing your
local variables in Swift for
the first time. It looks
like this, var digit, okay?
Var means this is a local
variable. Digit is the name.
Now if we wanted to type it,
we could put a type here like
maybe type string. Just like
we put a type of our parameter
here, we can put a type right
here of our local variable.
But, we don't usually do that
in Swift because while Swift
is very strongly typed
language, in other words,
you have to specify
the types of everything.
It wants to know
it will infer what type
you want from the context.
Very often. Ok?
So that's the trade off,
if you have a really strongly
typed language, you have
to type everything. It's
really nice if the compiler
will just figure out for you
what the types of things are.
So, normally, we will leave
the types off wherever we can.
Now, we can't do that in
a method parameter because we
got to know what That method
is expecting. But for local
variables, we definitely can
leave it off almost all
the time, okay? So we got this
digit, and I just wanna
set it equal to something.
What does it wanna
be equal to?
It wants to be equal to
the title of the button
that's sending me the message.
So this guy,
which is a button I want
to ask what its title is.
Now, how do you send a message
to another object in Swift?
Well, you just type
the object you want to
send the message to and you
press dot. Okay, so this is
like Java and a lot of other
languages, just the object and
dot, that's how you send the
message. Now, unfortunately,
XCode is helping me here by
showing me all the methods And
properties that button can do.
Look at this list,
I'm only in the Fs, okay,
I'm still scrolling,
still scrolling. There's a lot
of methods. It's like how am I
ever gonna figure out. I just
want the title of the button,
please. Okay, well, of course
I could get the documentation,
start reading through it,
trying to figure out, and
in fact I want to
do that eventually.
there's kind of
trick here in Xcode.
Which is, just type
the name of thing you want,
Type what you think it might
be and see what happens.
So, I'm going to type Title.
Now there's no method or
property in button
called title.
But you can see that Xcode has
showed me all the methods and
properties that start
with the word title Or
that have the word title in
it. Or even that have "t",
"it", "le" in it, okay?
So it's doing everything it
can to show you every possible
thing that might match what
you typed. Now, let's look
through these and see if we
can find one that will give us
the title of the button, okay?
Title label That doesn't look
very good. How about title for
control state,
that looks good,
returns the title associated
with the specified state.
Mm, that looks pretty good but
let's keep looking because I
don't really know
anything about the state,
that looks pretty good,
but let's keep going.
No edge insets, no, add color,
no, shadow, no. Current title,
the current title that
is displayed on the button,
victory that sounded
exactly what I want. So
I'm just gonna pick that
by double-clicking on it.
So I'm just gonna double-click
on it. There it is,
it filled it out. And so
now we're sending currentTitle
to sender. Now let's find out
more about currentTitle, okay?
We know that one-liner that is
the currentTitle displayed.
I'm gonna hold down Option.
See Option down here
on the left, okay?
I'm gonna hold down Option,
and look.
When I do Option things
that I mouse over turn blue
with a little
dashed underline.
And if I click,
I get a little help, okay? So
I'm getting that current title
display from the button,
but I'm also getting more
detailed description and
I'm getting the declaration
of this thing. And
you could see that
this is not a func.
This is a var. So now you're
seeing for the first time,
the declaration of
a property in Swift, okay?
An instance variable. So
this is an instance variable,
in UIButton, okay? Called var,
makes sense, right?
It's a variable, var.
It's called currentTitle,
of course.
It's type is, string?
Not sure, maybe button's
not sure what the type is.
No, I think button knows but,
we're just gonna assume this
is string, for now. And
we'll see, where that takes
us. Also notice this little
syntax means that, you can
only get the current title,
with this property. You can't
set the current title. Now,
what if I was like, well I'm
interested. How would I set
the current title? So
you would want to, let's say,
go look in the documentation.
How would you get there?
Well, if you look down at
the bottom, it says more.
This property reference right
here. If you click on that,
it brings up
the documentation. Okay?
And here's the documentation
for CurrentTitle. Now what's
cool about this, is from here,
I can click on things.
Like String, I could find
out about String. Or, look,
I can click on the class that
this is defined in, UIButton.
And here's the UIButton,
and look at this section at
the start of UIButton called
Overview. These are awesome,
and I strongly recommend
Every class you go to use
take the five minutes or
ten minutes at the most to
read through these overviews.
Then you'll really understand
how these classes work.
Look at this thing.
It tells us for
example how to configure
the button's appearance.
It tells us all about
this button's stage.
Remember, we had that
title for state.
And we didn't really know
what the state was. Well,
this tells us about that.
Tells you about the content of
a button. And you can put an
image on there, evidently, and
text. Those edge insets,
whatever those are, explained.
Even an interface builder, all
those things in the inspector.
Look, those are all explained,
in detail.
So this is a great thing
to just read through this,
understand this for
all the common classes. And
of course, all of the methods
are listed here as well. For
example, look at this one,
setTitle. Hm, that might be
a way to set the title. And
if I click on that, I get a
full description of this. And
I even see that the state
thing is here, so I can click
on that. And now I can see
the control state, of course,
there's normal, highlighted
button, disabled button,
a selected button. They can
each have their own title,
cool. But you see how I'm
navigating by just clicking
through the various types and
all that you really want to
get faster with doing that
okay it's really important to
be a good IOS developer to be
able to use the documentation
effectively. All right, so
we're back here, we got this
thing currentTitle. It's this
type string question mark. And
I told you that swift would
infer the type. And sure
enough, look, a digit. It's
type is string question mark.
Of course, because I just set
it equal to something that
was string question mark, so
it knows it's string question
mark. So, let's go ahead and
print this digit out. Okay,
it's saying touch digit was
called. Let's try and print it
out. Now in another language,
you might use printf.
And you might say something
like %s was touched.
And then you would
put digit right here,
okay? Now unfortunately, you
can't do this in Swift, okay?
There's no percent s business,
okay? And no printf. Instead,
we still say print, okay? But,
instead of doing percent s.
We can actually use the very
magical\() parentheses.
If you put that
inside a string,
then you can put anything you
want inside there that can
be converted to a string. And
it will include it there.
Including,
a string itself. Can obviously
be converted to a string. So
this way, you can embed
strings in other strings.
Or even embed more complicated
objects that know how to turn
themselves into a string, into
strings. Okay, so this is how
you do the print f business
of printing things out. Okay,
now also I notice, we have a
warning. This yellow thing is
a warning, okay? And they can
be yellow which are warnings
in which case it'll compile
and run. But, you still got to
fix it cuz you cannot submit
any homework in this class
with warnings. You hear me?
Or they can be red.
In red's case, it won't even
build. So this one's yellow.
How do we find out what it is?
Well, we just click on it.
When we click on it, it says
here the variable digit
was never mutated.
Means it was never changed.
Consider changing to let
constant, it says. Okay? And
you can see it even saying do
you want me to fix it? I can
replace var with let and it's
even showing what that would
look like to replace var with
let. How helpful of it. So
actually, I'm gonna have to
do that. I'm gonna click,
change it to let, warning
gone. Now what is all that
about? It said digit was never
mutated, it was never changed,
okay? So digit essentially
was a constant.
We gave it an initial value.
It never got changed.
When you declare a constant
you always want to use let.
Now why do we have a different
word for a constant than for
a var? Well,
because a constant isn't var.
It doesn't vary,
a constant is constant.
And let is a great word
because read this. Let digit
equal sender's current title.
Okay, reads really nice.
Now why do we care about
distinguishing these two?
Two reasons. One if you're
a reader of someone's code and
you see let you know that this
is not going to change, okay.
You know the digit is going
to be, never going to change.
And in fact if someone
did change it or
if you tried to change someone
else's code and change it,
compiler's gonna generate an
error, okay. You can't change
something that's constant.
But even more importantly,
it tells Swift that
it's a constant and
that you intend it to be
a constant. And so later,
if you try to modify it,
even if it's an array or
a dictionary and you're trying
to put something in the array
Okay? Or add something
to the dictionary.
It knows, you intended
that to be a constant. So,
you know, error. So it's a way
to tell Swift what you intend.
Now, the difference
between a mutable array,
an array that you can
add stuff to, and
an immutable one, is huge.
Because if you pa, arrays and
Swift are passed around by
copy. Arrays are passed by
copy. It's very unusual
compared to other languages
where an array would just be
an object in the heap and
you just pass a pointer to it.
You were passing them it
copies them every time you
pass them to a function.
Now that'd be very inefficient
if they were all mutable. Cuz
you have to actually copy them
in case someone changed it.
But Swift knows which ones
are mutable and which aren't.
And when you pass
an immutable one it only- But
doesn't really efficient copy,
okay,
it doesn't actually copy the
element. And in fact, until
you assigned it to a mutable
variable by saying var equals
that, it doesn't even have to
worry about that. And then it
can just do copy on write when
you actually change it. Okay,
so that's the var/let thing,
get used to it,
always do let for constants.
All right, so let's run
this now. See what's going on
here. This should work, right?
We're getting the current
title. We're saying, it,
well, whatever that
title was was touched.
This should be good to go.
Here we go. Seven. What?
Okay, well,
it's kinda working.
I mean it's definitely doing
something different And
it kinda knows which button.
But what's all this
optional quote business?
What's that about?
>> Well, that's because
digit is not a string,
it's a string?, okay.
So what is String? String?
is a totally different type
from String. It's called
an optional. Alright? This
is super important. So again,
wake up if you're napping.
Okay? This is super important.
Very few languages have this
concept. It's a great concept.
It really makes the API really
understandable throughout all
of iOS. But it takes a little
bit of getting used to, okay?
So what is this type optional?
A type optional has only
two values, set and
not set, okay? That's
the only two values it has.
There's no other values.
However, when it's in the set
case, it can have
an associated value. Okay?
A value that it kinda
keeps on the side and
you specify when you
create the optional or
you declare it what type
that associated value is.
So this, the associated
value is a string.
We're talking about the value
of a button of course. So
we would say the type
of this digit is optional
strength. Which means
an optional who's associative
value in the set state is
a string. Okay? Now, in this
case that's all fine and
good but we want
the associated value here.
Give me that associated value,
that title, okay?
How do I get it out of here?
And the answer for
that is exclamation point.
Okay, if you put
the explanation point at
the end of an optional then it
will, if it's in the set state
grab the associated value and
give it to you. So
now look at the type of digit.
It's a string. Okay, Swift
able to infer that since you
unwrapped this optional right
here. You've got a string over
here. Now what if you do
exclamation point and
that optional is in
the not set state? Because
there's no associated value
when it's in not state, that's
only when it's in associated.
What happens to your app?
Anyone want to guess what
happens? Crashes. Okay?
Kaboom. Now, I'm sure
some of you conservative
folk out there are like,
okay well that's it for
me, an exclamation point!
I'm never using that.
I don't want my app to crash,
that's horrible.
But actually having your app
crash during development
can be great, because
you'll find bugs really
fast and you'll be dropped
right into the debugger
where the crash happened so
you can figure whats going on.
How could this have happened?
So in this case were talking
about the title of a button,
that means the title of
the button was never set and
this is touch digit. That
should never have happen. Okay
if that happened in something
I shipped to my customer,
customers would be complaining
left, right and center.
There's a button that
has no title on it,
nothing on it and
I click what,
you know what I'm saying?
So, you want to find
those in development.
So crashing can be
good sometimes.
Now of course you don't always
want to crash when you unwrap
an optional and I'll show you
in a little bit how to unwrap
an optional and get it to
associated value. But test it
first to make sure that it's
in the set state. Okay, but
for now we do this. Let's run
and see what this looks like.
It should work. But now
we've unwrapped this thing,
grabbed its associate value.
And we know the current title
should always be set so
we'll not have to worry
about crashing here. And
sure enough seven was touched,
nine, whatever, three,
five, six, okay? All right,
so we're rocking and
rolling here. We're able to
collect the digits from user.
Now let's put them in
the calculator display.
So we need to add a display
to our calculator.
So we're gonna go back
to our area here.
Go down to the bottom half.
Now be careful not to grab
text field here because
that's editable text and
in a compilator you can't
click on the display and
edit it. You type the numbers
to put your numbers in. So
we're gonna use this one
up here, which is labeled.
By the way, if you click
on one of these and
leave your mouse there for
a second,
it'll give you a detailed
explanation of each of these
objects in the list. So I'm
just gonna pick out a label
and drag it up here to top,
maybe make a little more space
for it. Move out a little bit.
So we've got this label.
Once again just like I did for
the buttons I'm going
to change the size.
Maybe I want to start with
zero in there. Bigger font.
Let's go over here maybe even
really big font, like 40 or
something like that. In
a calculator the text is right
aligned. Right? Text comes
out from the right, so
we want to use this
alignment right here.
Right aligned. Okay?
Maybe with some colors.
Let's put, let's make
the background be blue.
But I don't really
like black on blue, so
we'll go up here and change
the color to be white. Okay?
So that's a pretty
decent looking display
right there, for now anyway.
Now, if we have these
buttons being pressed, we need
to talk to this display, and
tell it what the digits are.
So how are we gonna do that?
Well again,
we need to make a connection
between that display and
our code. But this is not
the same kind of connection.
Because we don't touch
on that label, and
it calls a method, We need to
have an instance variable, or
property, that points to that
thing, so we can talk to it
whenever we want, cuz we
gotta put these digits on it.
Okay? So we're still going
to use the same mechanism to
make a connection, which is
control. And we're going to
drag in here. Okay? And
this time we're going to use
outlet. Outlet means a
property that points to this.
And I'm going to call this
display. It's our display.
It got the type right here.
This weak and strong, don't
worry about that. I'm going
to talk about that next week.
Okay. So don't worry.
So, here is
our first instance variable
in our class. Woo hoo! Okay?
This right here, is again
just some stuff that Xcode
throws in there, so
you get this, right? This,
I told you ignore, okay? So
this is the declaration
of our property and
of course it's a var and
that could be let. If you want
an instance variable that
is set at the beginning and
never changes, you can use
let. It's pretty rare, but
you can do it, okay usually
they're var. Display,
that's the name.
": UILabel" is the type,
okay? So as you might guess,
this has something to do with
optionals, okay?
This is kinda confusing to
start off the bat, but
that exclamation point,
which normally means unwrap an
optional. Obviously we can't
unwrap here, we're
declaring this thing here.
This is pretty much exactly
the same as a question mark.
In fact, I'm gonna change
it to a question mark for
now, and later I'll change it
back to an exclamation point,
and you'll see the difference.
But, the type of this display
is optional UI label. Now, why
is this an optional UI label?
Why isn't this
just a UI label?
Why does it have to be
optional? Because when this UI
first comes up, iOS needs
a few nanoseconds to hook
that up for you. So
when this UI first comes up,
it's not set to an optional
not set case and then UI hooks
it up for you, and now it's
set forever after that. And
that's important that it's set
forever, and we'll see it has
to do with that exclamation
point I just got rid of. But
for now understand that
display is just an optional
we'll have to unwrap it every
time we use it, okay so
as simple as that. All right,
so now instead of printing
the digits on the screen
let's go ahead and
put these digits
into the display,
and really every time a digit
is pressed we wanna append it
onto the end of the display
like if there's 56 in there we
wanna append 2- it's 562 and
8 it's 5268, right? So we're
just gonna keep appending.
So we need to get the text so
it's currently in the display
and add the digit to it.
So I'm gonna add another
little local variable.
It's a constant also called
textcurrentlyInDisplay and
I'm gonna get that by sending
a message to the display,
which I have to unwrap,
and now I can send
your message. And
here's all the messages
that label responds too,
again, hundreds, okay? So I'm
gonna do the same trick, I'm
gonna type text because I want
the text out of there Look at
the very first one, the text
displayed by the label.
It's an optional string.
Excellent, I'll take it, okay.
So, now I've got the text but
it's optional. So,
I need to unwrap it, okay?
So now textCurrentlyInDisplay.
If I option click on it
you'll see it's a string. So,
now I can just say,
set the display, unwrap,
text equal to the text that's
currently in the display
plus the digit. Now, notice
when I set an optional, text
is an optional, right? When I
set it equal to something- by
the way this optional is get
and set unlike currentTitle,
which was get only- so I can
set the your label's text here
and get it. When I set
this optional right here,
I don't have to unwrap
it first, okay?
So you don't have to unwrap
an optional to set it,
you just set it.
And optionals know okay,
this must be the associated
value of an optional string,
so I will set it, okay?
So that's it,
let's see if that works. Okay,
so we got our UI, looks good,
got a display in there, mm-hm.
Let's try 8, well 6,
well, it's kinda working.
It's definitely doing
the appending thing,
but that 0 at the beginning,
that's wrong. That zero is not
part of what I was typing.
That zero just happened
to be there at startup.
So, it shouldn't be put
in in the front there and
the problem here
is really simple.
It's just that we haven't
taught our calculator to know
when the user is entering,
in the middle of
entering a number,
versus when it
just started up.
Or maybe, the result of
an operation just appeared
there. Obviously when we type
we wouldn't want that to
have more, thanks to it.
So, we need to teach our
calculator brain here to know
the difference between whether
the user is in the middle
of typing or not.
And we're gonna do that,
by creating another property
called
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping.
Which is gonna be a Bool. Now,
I typed a long name here. Kind
of for effect. We probably
could have called this typing.
You know, there's trade off
between clarity and brevity.
Okay, brevity is valued,
but clarity is even more
important. So, maybe isTyping
would have been enough.
But I would err slightly on
the side of clarity. So I'm
using this long one. The other
thing, the reason I typed this
long is to show you that I'm
never gonna have to type this
again, because Xcode is always
gonna escape complete this for
me, as you'll see when I start
using it. Now when I added
this beautiful var, this Bool.
Okay, a Bool, by the way,
is just something that
can be true or false,
of course. I got an error.
Look at that error up there.
This little thing here- it's
on a line that had nothing to
do with what I just did.
What? That's not fair.
What is this? It says
Class 'View Controller'
has no initializers. Okay
well, what the heck is that?
That has nothing to do
with the var either?
Well, here's the deal here.
In Swift,
all properties have to be
initialized. Every single one.
No exceptions.
Now there's two ways
to initialize your properties
in a class or struct.
One is with an initializer.
An initializer is a special
method, it's called init,
I-N-I-T. You can have any
number of arguments that your
class requires but, in its
implementation it has to
initialize all uninitialized
properties. Okay? Now,
we're not gonna talk
about initializers today.
I'll talk about it a little
bit next Wednesday,
actually. So, we're not gonna
use an initializer. Because
there's a second way to
initialize, which is to just
give it a value. Okay,
is false, right? The user's
obviously not in the middle of
typing at the beginning, so
is false. And
that got rid of the error.
Okay? In fact, we don't need
this either. Do you see why?
Because false,
can only be a Bool, So
Swift can infer that this
must be a Bool. And again,
we do not want these things in
here, if we can help it. Now,
what about this guy? That's
not initialized. How come he's
not complaining, okay? How
come he's not getting that?
Must be initializers business
going on. Well, because he's
an optional. And optionals
are special when it comes
to initialization. They all
get this automatic treatment.
Equals nil. nil means
not set optional. Okay.
That's the only thing nil
means in Swift. It means
an optional that's not set.
So optional will automatically
get this treatment at all
times when you declare them.
And it makes sense right,
if you have an optional
it's gonna start out not
set until you set it.
Now you could set this equal
to some UILabel of some sort,
and have it be set from the
start, that's possible too.
But if you don't say anything
it gets not set. Alright, so
we've got that. Now we can use
this userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping
thing.
We'll say if the user is
in the middle of
typing then we can do,
this business that we
just did here, okay?
What if it's not in the middle
of typing? Then we're just
gonna set the display's text
equal to the digit, cuz we're
starting a new number then.
In this case of course,
the user is now in
the middle of typing Okay,
everybody got that? So that's
just how we're going to make
sure we do the right thing.
So let's go ahead and run,
see if that whole 0,
leading 0 problem is fixed.
Should be,
because when we start off,
we're not in the middle
of typing. So
when we start typing
a new number, boom,
we get a new number. But if
we're in the middle of typing,
we keep getting the appending
deal. All right,
we are just rocking and
rolling here.
Next, let's put some operation
buttons in this baby.
We can type in numbers,
now let's start operating.
I'm gonna do that by
doing a very bad thing,
which is I'm going to copy and
paste the 7 button.
You're gonna see why that's
bad in a moment. And
I'm gonna do a very simple
operation, pi, okay?
So pi is just an operation
that's gonna put pi in my
display, that's all it's gonna
do. So I'm gonna control drag
to wire it up to a method.
It's an action, not an outlet.
It's an action,
just like touchDigit was.
I'm gonna call it
performOperation,
cuz that's what it does,
it performs an operation.
I'm gonna make sure I switch
this to button like you
guys all are in your
homework assignments. And
then I'm going to connect.
So now I have this new method
right here, and it is hooked
up to pi, so that's good.
And what do I want
to do in here?
Well, I could do the same
thing of asking the button
which operation it is. How
about let mathematicalSymbol,
because that's what these
things are in these operation
buttons, equal the
sender.currentTitle!, okay?
Great, now I've got the pi,
but I wanted to show you,
I promised I'd show you how
to do this unwrapping without
crashing, so let's do it here.
Let's decide that if we do
have a blank button, a button
whose title is not set, let's
say we won't crash. Instead,
we'll just do nothing.
We won't do any operations.
Like you didn't even
click a button, okay?
So, again, optionals are so
important. You can see,
look how minuscule the syntax
is for these things, right?
Question mark. Exclamation
point. You barely have to type
to use an optional. Well, it's
the same thing if you want to
test the optional
before unwrapping.
Instead of putting the
exclamation point at the end,
you put two characters
at the beginning. if. So
read this. If I can let
mathematical symbol equal
the sender's currentTitle,
then. So,
if I can unwrap this optional,
get its associated value,
then I'll do something, and
then you can just put whatever
code you want in here,
and inside here,
mathematicalSymbol will be a
string, the associated value.
The unwrapped optional, right?
Outside of these curly braces,
mathematicalSymbol is not even
defined, so it doesn't matter.
It's not even defined. So
inside this
mathematicalSymbol, I could
say if mathematicalSymbol
equals, pi, then do something.
Else if the mathematical
symbol equals something else,
okay? But, if then else, if
then else, if then else, that
would be really bad code. So
I'm going to use a different
one here.
A different little expression.
I'm going to use switch. So a
lot of languages have switch.
So I'm going to switch on
the mathematical symbol.
Not all languages can switch
on a string. Some can, but
you can in Swift. And I can
just say, in the case that
it is pi, then I'm going
to do something. Now,
unfortunately I'm
getting an error here.
So, what am I gonna do? Let's
just put in what I'm gonna do.
I just want the display.
Woops, the displays, text to
equal pi. Okay. This is pretty
bad to type it in as a string,
we'll get back to
that in a second.
But that's basically what
I wanted to do, right?
Is set the display to be pi.
Now I'm getting an error.
What is the error? It says
switch has to be exhaustive.
And that's true. When you have
a switch, you have to have
every possible case. So unless
we want to spend the next few
lectures I guess going
like this, case a-a-a, and
typing any possible string,
okay, this is no good. So
luckily though,
there is a default case. So
default just means
all other cases.
And here I'm just gonna
break out of the switch.
I'm gonna use this command
break. Now notice that my
indentation's gotten a little
messed up here. This should
really be the same indentation
as this. A really cool feature
is select any text you want,
even the whole file, and
do Ctrl I for indent ,and it
will re-indent everything for
you. And I recommend you do
that on all your source files
when you turn in your
homework. Just select all,
indent. So we got this pi
here. Let's see if this works.
Got the numbers
are still working.
And pi. Okay. That's weird.
I got that pi that I typed
in right here. Okay, but
what, how come I got this
pi symbol added on there?
That seems weird. Let's try
a new number. So, no, okay.
When I type more numbers,
it adds it on to the end. So
even if that pi symbol
wasn't in there,
I'd be able to change
the value of pi,
evidently by adding more
digits to it. That's no good.
And look at this. When I type
more it puts an ellipsis,
and it stops taking numbers.
Okay, this is a mess.
We got three big
problems here. That pi.
The fact that I can add on
things to the end of it,
and the fact that I
get these ellipses.
So how are we going
to fix those?
Let's go fix all three of
those real quick. Okay. So,
first the pi coming on
the end. Well look,
where do I ever set the
display sets? I set it here.
Well, so clearly the pi's
not coming from this.
I set it here. This only
sets it to one digit so
that can't be it,
cuz I've got multiple.
This is the only other
place I set it. Maybe
this is the problem. Do you
see the pi button right there?
It's hooked up to this method.
And to this method. So
it's doing both. It's doing
this and putting this on here,
and then it's calling this,
and doing this. And
the digit is the pi, okay? So,
that's bad. Now, how are we
going to fix that? Question?
>> How did you set
the order range?
>> Yeah,
the question is how did
it decide the order?
And the answer is
the order is undefined.
In my experience,
it's usually alphabetical, but
it's undefined. So you would
never wanna depend on that.
But yeah, perform comes
before touchDigit.
I don't know. But you're
almost never gonna have two
things hooked up like this.
This is obviously an error.
This is causing a problem.
So let's fix it. How do we do
that? There's another way to
know what's connected other
than using the little circles,
which is just to right click
on something in the UI. So I
right clicked on pi, and I got
this big window that shows me
all the connections to pi.
This would be all the instance
variables, all the methods,
etc. And we can see that for
the event Touch Up Inside,
which means a touch of
the finger went up inside
the bounds of the button. It's
sending both these messages,
touchDigit and
perfomOperation, and
we clearly did not
want touchDigit for pi.
Why did I get it? Because I
copied and pasted that 7.
Remember I said that was a bad
idea? Yeah, that's why. So
let's disconnect it by just
clicking this little x, okay,
boom. Now this only is sent
by this, and not by this.
So that fixed that.
What about the fact that
I could type extra numbers on
the end of pie? Well, that's
a pretty simple neither. When
am I allowed to type other
numbers in? When the user's in
the middle of typing a number.
Well as soon as I hit pi,
is the user in the middle of
typing a number? No, they
just typed pi. So they're not
in the middle of typing pi.
And in fact,
they're typing a number.
And in fact any time we
perform any operation,
the user is in the middle of
typing a number is false.
They are clearly not in
the middle of typing anymore.
Whatever's gonna be display is
gonna be the result of that
operation. Okay, so that fixes
that. How bout the little
ellipses, and the numbers
getting cut off. Well here's
a kind of a cute fix to that.
In label, there is a cool
feature called autoshrink,
you see it right there?
So I just selected label,
brought up this inspector.
There's autoshrink, and you
can have it shrink down, for
example to a minimum font
size, let's say 9 font.
And now,
when we get too many numbers,
it'll shrink down instead of
doing ellipses, right there.
Now, this probably isn't
the best solution to this.
A better solution would be,
have our calculator only show
a certain number of digits
after the decimal point.
Probably would be
really better. And
that's extra credit for
you in your homework, okay?
So good luck with that.
Right, so we got this.
We fixed all these problems,
let's take a look.
All right, so got our numbers
here. Pi, alright no pi and
it didn't add them
on to the end and
what if we had a lot
of numbers in here.
Yeah, look at that,
it's autoshrinking.
Okay, we're not
losing any numbers.
Yeah, probably not
the best solution but
I get to show you autoshrink.
Okay, what's next?
We're gonna attack this little
problem right here. Okay?
This is really ugly, really
what I want this to be is this
really cool feature in Swift,
Double.pi, which is the double
precision floating point value
of pi. Of course, I can't say
this because- Cannot assign
value of type 'Double' to
an optional string because
the only way you can assign
anything to an optional string
besides nil would be something
that's a string. So we can set
that associated value. Now,
does anyone know, from
what I've shown you today,
how we could convert this
to a sting? No brave soul?
Back, exactly.
Backslash, open parentheses,
close parenthesis,
that little trick, right?
You can just put
Double.pi in here.
Doubles can be converted
to strings, bingo.
Now, this is kinda ugly, okay?
This really doesn't look good
because this is more meant to
embed things in other strings.
It's not really the way to
make something a string.
The way to really make
a new string is to create
a new string. And so, here
you're seeing what the syntax
is to create a new object,
a new struct or a new class,
okay? The name of the class,
and then parentheses.
Now, inside these parentheses,
can be anything the class
can take to create one of
itself, right? Anything that
class can take. And remember I
mentioned those initializers?
These are the arguments to the
initializer. And initializers,
you've got multiple
initializers.
String has a whole
bunch of initializers.
One of the initializers
that a string has,
takes a double. So
this would be the right way to
convert from a double
to a string and
it looks a lot better in
the code as well, right.
It's more obvious what
we're doing, okay?
All right let's add
another operation here,
I'm gonna make this one be
square root. So underneath
the square root symbol,
from the edit menu, emoji and
symbols, you can actually
search. We could pick a smiley
face but let's go square root.
Square root, here it is, so
we're gonna use this square
root symbol in code there. And
let's go ahead and copy it so
we can use it in the code.
All right, so we have this,
it's nicely hooked up just
to this and not to this.
So that's good. We just need
to say case of square root.
What do we wanna do? We
wanna set the display's text
equal to the square root of
something. Okay, well what do
we want this to be the square
root of? Well we want it to be
the square root of whatever's
in this display already. So,
display!.text, okay, will
that work? No, because this
is a string and we can't take
the square root of a string.
And not only that, the square
root returns a double, okay?
And we can't put a double into
a string, so we at least have
to do this again, put
a string around it. Okay? But
this is still a string. So I'm
gonna get this out of here and
make a little
local variable so
we can work on this, okay?
So, we need this operand,
which is currently a string,
to be a double. So
can we do this, double?
You think we can do that?
In the same way that we went
this way? Can we go this way?
The answer is yes.
Or yes! One of those.
The answer is yes because,
what if that string is hello?
What do you convert hello to?
It can't be converted.
So this initializer for
double that takes a string,
it returns an optional double.
Do you see why? Cuz if you
give it a string that it
can't convert to a double,
it returns not set.
Couldn't do it, basically.
So if we look at operand right
here, it's an optional double,
okay? Whereas when we
did this string up here,
string didn't need to
return optional string,
because it can always convert
a double to a string, always.
But you can't always convert
a string to a double,
it has to look like a double.
Okay?
So, we're gonna do that and
I'm gonna go ahead and
force unwrap it here with the
exclamation point, assuming
that I never have anything
in my display that can't be
converted to a double. Maybe
that's a bad assumption but
I'm gonna assume that for now.
I'm also gonna Ctrl+I again,
to get my indenting right.
Okay, does this make sense?
So now all is well.
Operand is a double.
So I can take the square
root of a double.
I'm gonna convert it to
a string and go to here.
All right, wow,
that's a lot of mess. Okay,
that's really messy code, I'm
gonna have to fix that, but
conceptually you understand
hopefully what's going on
there. So let's do this, let's
try 81 square root. Square
root again. Square root again.
How about pi square root?
78 square root? All right,
this is working perfectly.
But, our code is really
a mess here. Can you imagine,
if we have to do another
case and another case.
And we're always doing this
double this, string that,
back and forth, exclamation
points everywhere. Okay,
there's too many dang
exclamation points in here for
the first thing.
And the second of all,
I'm tired of all
the strings and doubles. So
I'm gonna fix all that. Let's
start with the exclamation
point thing. Look at every
time I use the display.
I use it all over my code.
And every time I have to
put an exclamation point,
every single time. Even
though I know that display,
once it's set up by iOS in the
beginning, it never is not in
the not set state,
it's always set. So
let's go back up here
to this question mark.
This is what exclamation
point in a declaration
of an optional means. It means
yes, this is an optional,
just like a question mark.
But, everywhere you use this,
I'm going to automatically
unwrap it. Now,
it's still unwrapping it, so
even if I go down here and
I take away this
exclamation point,
it works because of this
automatic unwrapping.
But if this were not set,
it would still crash. Okay?
Because essentially,
implicitly unwrapping.
That's why this is called an
implicitly unwrapped optional.
Got that phrase? Implicitly
unwrapped optional. But
it does mean, that we can
go around to all of our
display question marks, and
change them to display.
And that makes our code look
quite a bit nicer. Okay?
Now we're still having to
unwrap text. Sorry about that.
Bottom line is we
have to do that.
That's not an implicitly
unwrapped option on that text.
Okay, what about all this
double and string thing?
The way I'm gonna fix that
is imagine I had a var.
We'll call it displayValue.
And it was a double.
Okay, show me this var.
Imagine if this var, all it
tracked, what's in here, but
as a double? Cuz what's in
there, we can only get it as
a string, we can only
set it as a string. But
wouldn't it be cool if I had a
var that just was always what
was in there but as a double?
Because I need it as a double
all the dang time, and I need
to set it as a double too,
okay? So how can I do that?
Well, turns out Swift
has a really cool feature
called computed properties.
And all I need to do is put
code after the property, and
you can compute the value.
Instead of storing
it, right. The user is in the
middle of typing a value that
storage somewhere. This one
we're gonna compute. And
you can compute both
a get case, right? And,
oops, sorry. And a set case.
So you can have some code that
deals with getting the value
and with setting the value.
So we're not gonna ever
store displayValue anywhere.
We're gonna get it and set it.
And where are we gonna
get it and set it from?
From the text on the label.
Right? So what does the get
look like? Well, we're just
gonna return a double of
the display's text, you don't
have to unwrap display, but
I do have to unwrap text. And
I'm gonna force unwrap that.
Again, I'm assuming there's
always a string that
can be interpreted as
a double in there.
Maybe I wanna change that
assumption down the road, but
for now I'll do that.
How about the set case?
In this set case, I'm gonna
display, set the display's
text equal to a string
that is the value that
people are trying to set
the display value to.
So somewhere in the code,
we write displayValue equals
five. And
here we have to put a five,
a string five into the text
of the display up here.
So what do we put inside this
little string here. Well, for
this set case, okay,
of a computed property,
there's a special variable
called newValue, and newValue
is always of the same type as
what you're setting, and it is
the value on the right hand
side of an equals if someone
says that this var equals
something, okay? Awesome.
Now that we have this
displayValue and
it's always tracking that,
we can use it down here.
Look at this code,
displayValue equals pi.
Done, get rid of all this
mess. displayValue equals
the square root of the
displayValue. All of a sudden,
the code down here has
become essential, right?
This is about the minimum you
could possibly type to say
that you wanted pi into the
display. Right? And so, when I
do this display value equals,
this code gets executed.
When I get the display value
here, this code gets executed.
These are called computed
properties. You're
going to see them
all over the place.
You've already seen one.
It's right here, currentTitle
is a computed property. It's
computed by the button class.
It figures out what the
current title is on there and
returns it. So there's this
is implemented with some
code that says
return whatever.
How do I know that? Because
it's read-only. The only way
to make a read-only var is
using a computed property.
All right, let's make sure we
didn't break anything with our
code clean up there.
All right, 89 looking good,
square root, 81, square root,
square root, square root.
Pi 78 square root. Okay,
it's working. Okay, so that's
a lot of stuff to digest,
I know. Let it all sink in.
On Wednesday at the start,
I'm gonna talk to you about
MVC, this design paradigm, and
then we're gonna
add MVC to this and
we're also gonna make sure
that UI works on all devices.
Okay, see you then.
>> For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.