[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> So
welcome to Stanford CS193P,
this is Developing iOS
Applications, winter of 2017.
So today I'm gonna give
another brief set of slides on
Model View Controller, this
design methodology that we're
gonna use to build all of our
iOS apps. And then I'm gonna
continue the demo that we
started on Monday. We're gonna
actually incorporate MVC into
the calculator. And it's also
gonna be an opportunity for
me to show you a lot of other
cool Swift, language features.
So what is MVC? Model view
controller, what is that?
Basically, it starts out
being a way that we divide up
all of the code in our app
into three different camps.
These three different camps
are the model camp, the model
is the "what" of your app,
so what your app is. So,
in the calculator case, i's
the brains of the calculator,
i's the thing that
calculates, tha's the model,
and tha's a UI independent
part. I's what the app is,
not how it displays or
anything like that.
How it displays is
the controlle's job. So
the controller decides how
to take this UI independent
thing, the model, and
display it on your screen and
interact with the user. That's
what the controller job does.
It's the, how it displays.
Model is the what it is.
Controller is how it displays.
The view is the minions
of the controller, okay?
Things that the controller
uses to do its job,
almost always, these things
in the view are generic,
things like UIButton or
UIScrollView, okay?
Things that come from Apple or
somewhere else,
even things you write, and you
generally try to write them to
be pretty generic reusable UI
things. And the controller is
trying to use those generic
things to build a specific UI.
Now the key to making MVC work
is managing the communication
between these camps
because if we don't manage
that communication,
we might as well just put
them all in the big camp.
And they can all talk to each
other however they want. So
if we're gonna
have three camps,
we gotta think about
how they communicate.
So I've used this road sign
kind of imagery here, okay,
the roads, like the road
lines in the middle of a road
between them to help you
visualize what is allowed
in terms of communication.
So, let's talk about every
boundary here between all of
these camps. Let's start with
the controller talking to
the model, okay.
Can the controller talk to
the model? Absolutely, it can
say anything to the model that
the model publicly allows
to be said to itself. So,
it's a green arrow. It's a
dashed white line on the road.
You can go across
there all you want.
And you can see why this is.
It is the controller job to
get that model onto screen.
It has to be able to talk to
it all at once. So, there's no
restriction of the controller
talking to the model. And
similarly, there's no
restriction of the controller
talking to the view, because
the view are the controller's
minions. Right, so you gotta
be able to tell your minions
what to do without
restriction. Now,
these connections between
the controller and
a view, we call them outlets.
And you've already seen one in
the calculator, we created
an outlet, if you remember,
it was called display, right?
It was an instance variable in
our controller. Remember that
class ViewController
we saw on Monday,
that's the controller of the
MVC that we built on Monday.
And that display var,
was an outlet,
and it's just wired up to
a UILabel in our view. UILabel
is one of the minions for the
controller in the view. Okay,
so you've already seen that
happen. The model and the view
can never speak to each other.
Double orange line there,
no crossing either way across
here. And this makes perfect
sense because the model is
completely UI independent,
and the view is completely UI.
That's all the view is.
So, they have nothing
to talk about,
these two guys, okay? Cuz
they're completely, you know,
different camps that make no
sense to talk to each other.
It's up to the controller to
manage communication between
these two. So, never shall you
just communicate between those
two camps, all right? How
about the view talking back to
its controller? Can the view,
those minions, can they talk
to its controller? Now this is
something you would clearly
want because the minions gotta
work with the controller, but
it's a bit of a problem here.
Because these things in
the view are generic.
They're things like UIButton.
The class UIButton shipped
from Apple last year. It knows
nothing about a calculator,
so how can that UIButton talk
to a calculator? Well, we can
do it. We just have to sort
of do it in a blind, meaning
we don't know the class of
the thing we're talking to.
And structured manner, so that
we can clearly understand what
communication is happening.
So you've already seen a blind
structured communication
between the view and
the controller.
It's target action, okay. So
the controller can
drop a target on itself
by basically creating a method
with that acts on IBAction,
remember that from Monday? And
then you just control drag and
that lets the view
UIButton talk,
basically connect up to
that target. And now every
time that the UIButton wants
to talk to the controller,
it's just sending that
target action. So that is
super simple blind structured
communication from the view
back to the controller. But,
that's a little too simple for
all the communication that
these minions might wanna do.
For example, sometimes,
something in the view wants to
synchronize itself
with the controller.
Or it wants to know what
the controller intends as it's
being used. Let's use
the example of a scroll view.
Okay, a scroll view,
when it's scrolling around,
might wanna ask
the controller,
should I allow the user
to scroll over here? Or
they might just wanna tell
the controller, hey, the user
scrolled down here. These
kind of notifications and
questions about whether it can
do things, they kind of end up
in things that start with
these words I have up here,
"will," "should," and
"did." Like,
should I scroll to here?
I will scroll right here,
if the scroll view was
about to scroll. And
then I did scroll down here
after the scroll view is done.
So those kinds of
communications.
And the way we make that
communication work,
we can't just do this simple
one method control drag,
instead we use what's called
a delegate. And I'm gonna talk
a lot more about a delegate in
future lectures. But basically
the idea of a delegate is,
it's a var in the view, so
like a var on scroll view. And
it's of a special type; that
type is called a protocol.
I know that a lot of you,
even though you have object
oriented experience,
maybe you don't have
experience with protocols. But
essentially, a protocol
is a way of
saying that this type, this
thing that I'm talking about,
it responds to a certain set
of methods. I don't know what
classage it is, I don't know
if it's a view controller,
I don't know what it is, but
I know it's gonna respond
to these methods like will
scroll, did scroll,
should scroll,
those kinds of methods.
That's all I know about it. So
the controller, it signs up
to listen to those methods,
and then it sets itself as
the delegate in the view.
Okay, and we're gonna
see this in action, so
don't worry about too much
now, but that's how we can
have structured communication
where they're agreeing.
The view, this generic
object is agreeing to
send certain messages
to the controller,
not where the controller
can be of any type and
still serve this purpose
of controlling its view.
Now there's a special kind of
communication between the view
and the controller that arises
because a view cannot own
the data it displays. And what
does that mean? That means you
don't want to have inside your
view class, and remember, view
classes are like scroll views,
buttons, things like that.
You don't wanna have
data in there that is
the data you're displaying.
I'll give you an example.
Let's say your entire
iPod music library,
let's say you have hundreds of
thousands of songs in there.
Okay, so I wanna have a list
of them on screen. So
I'm gonna use a generic item
in my view called table view.
Table view just shows a big
long list of something.
It can be a list a million
items long, okay? So
if I really had to take my
entire iPod library and
put it in the value
of a var of
the table view to display it,
that would be ridiculous.
Not just from a performance
standpoint, but
now I have two copies
of my iPad, or
my iPod music library, one
inside this table view, and
one in some database somewhere
in my phone. That's bad, where
they could get out of sync,
managing the synchronicity,
what if I have multiple
apps doing that? Ugh,
it's a mess, so the view never
wants to own that data, okay?
So how the heck is it
gonna get the data then?
I've got 100,000 songs, I need
to show it in this table,
how's it gonna do it? Well,
it's gonna use another one of
these protocol based vars,
okay, called the data source.
And the data source has
different methods in it,
it's not will, should, did,
it's how many items are in
this piece of data? Give me
the data at this location. And
that, again,
is a var that controllers
set in the table view, let's
say, that points back to it.
And so now every time
the table view wants data,
it asks the controller.
And the controller almost
always turns around and asks
the model, give me that data.
Now this also allows something
like table view that's showing
100,000 items. It can only
show 10 on a screen at a time,
so it only asks for 10 and
shows them. And if you scroll
down to somewhere else,
it's gonna ask for that 10.
And it's only keeping
the ones it's displaying. So
it's transferring a lot less
data, only the data you're
actually viewing, 10 out of
100,000 songs. And so it's
a lot more efficient, both
in terms of memory usage and
everything. Now you might
be a little scared,
like, every single
time I'm gonna scroll,
I'm gonna be asking for
this data. But
keep in mind, the model for
the iPod's music library is
probably a SQL database or
something, something that can
serve up data super fast.
That's it's job as a model to
be the source of that data,
okay? So that is usually not
your performance bottleneck.
We're gonna talk about
performance later in this
class, by the way. Usually
the performance bottleneck is
drawing on the screen. Things
like getting data out of
databases, forget it. Drawing
on the screen is much slower
and then going over
the network is even slower.
So those things tend to
dominate the performance of
your app. Okay, so don't worry
about that. So anyway, so
that's a couple of examples
how we have the structured
communication from generic
objects back to our
controller. Now what about
sorry, one statement that's
good to put in your mind that
has all three camps in it,
is that the controller
interprets and formats
the model for its views. Cuz
its views are generic, they
don't really know how to deal
with any particular model.
A controller knows about both,
so that's part of its job.
So a lot of times
I'll be saying,
the controller's job is to
do this, and you'll be like,
yeah, I remember him saying
that. All right, now what
about the model communicating
with the controller?
Now this can never happen as
well because the model is
UI independent. It knows
nothing about any particular
UI, so there's no way it
could talk to a UI guy like
the controller, okay? So what
happens, though, if the model
changes, the data changes?
That controller needs to know,
because it wants to update
the screen in that case.
Well, the way we do that
is with a model that
kind of looks like a radio
station, okay? The model
basically has a radio station,
and it broadcasts on that
radio station, hey, I changed,
or this about me changed. And
then the controller tunes in
to that radio station. And
when it hears a broadcast, it
asks the model what changed,
down that green arrow there,
you see? Okay, so
that's the model we're gonna
use, that's the mechanism
we're gonna use to get stuff
for our model that changes
to notify our controller.
Some people ask, can
a view tune in to a radio
station? And the answer is,
yeah, it probably could. It
wouldn't necessarily violate
MVC,. But the problem is
a generic view wouldn't know
what radio station to tune
into anyway, so it's really
not an issue there. All right,
so an MVC like this, though,
really is not, like your
whole app isn't one big MVC.
Each MVC controls either
one screen on an iPhone or
maybe even a subpart of
a screen on an iPhone or
an iPad. Maybe there's two or
three MVCs controlling what's
going on on the screen, so
how do we build a big app?
An app, you know,
it's building an Instagram
app. I gotta have MVCs for
posting, I gotta have MVCs for
image editing so
I can do my sepia tone.
I gotta have an MVC for
scrolling through the latest
posts that are coming up.
I mean, I need all kinds of
MVCs. How do these things, how
do we combine them together?
Well, looks like this.
MVCs, when other MVCs point
to them, it's always as
part of another MVC's view.
So look at the three
MVCs that are down here in
the lower right corner.
You see these three MVCs? See
this MVC up here, this purple
one? Look how it points to
them as if they were part of
its view. You see that? There
are no other arrows that point
from one controller to
another MVC except for
that goes through this
view side of the MVC.
Let me help you make that
more concrete why that is.
Let's say I had an app and it
was a calendar app, and it was
showing me the year, okay,
a whole year's worth of my
calendar entries. Well, on a
tiny screen it's barely gonna
be able to show me the 12
months, let alone the days and
the things, right? So it's got
this picture of the months.
So that's a year MVC, let's
say, in my calendar app. So
I click on one of the months
cuz I want some more detail.
And now that year MVC
moves out of the way and
puts up an MVC that's showing
all the days of a month, okay?
Well, that month MVC, which
is a totally separate MVC,
do you see how it's part
of the year MVC's view?
Because the year MVC
is showing months.
You wanna look at it,
it's trying to zoom in on it,
it does it with another MVC.
And same thing, in the month,
if I click on a day, the month
MVC's gonna move out of
the way. Put a day MVC that
shows me all my appointments,
for a day and that day MVC
would be part of the view of
the month MVC, okay,
make sense? So that's why,
that's the only relationship
we have between MVCs is across
this view boundary. Now there
can be other communication,
however. Look right here.
This MVC, the purple one
in the top middle there,
it's communicating to a model
that is the same model as some
other MVC. So MVCs can share
the same model. That's
perfectly fine. The models
are completely UI independent.
They don't care how many MVCs
are looking at them, okay?
Cuz they don't even
know about controllers.
Right, they're completely
independent of that.
Also notice these two
models down at the bottom,
they're talking to each other.
That's okay, too, because
a model can be defined any way
it wants. It's UI independent,
it can talk to other models,
whatever.
Now of course, it's still
gonna wanna radio broadcast if
maybe this model changes
something in it. But
it still can talk
directly to the model, so
that's the other communication
that can happen. But
no other communication
can happen.
We do not want our apps
to look like this. Okay,
we've got these MVCs, and
look, see this view over here?
It's talking to a different
controller. This controller is
talking directly to another
one, not out of view, but
just off to this side. You
don't want this mess. If you
do this mess, you really,
you're not even doing an MVC.
Cuz everybody's
in the same camp,
they're all just
talking to each other,
okay? So this is a no-go.
And, of course,
I'll be showing you, not next
week, but the week after,
how we build these connections
between MVCs. For the first
two weeks, we're just gonna
focus on building one MVC,
our calculators, one MVC. But
we're gonna add another MVC to
our calculator in week three.
And you're gonna see, that's
how we wire these things up,
okay? So that's MVCs.
We're gonna dive back into
continuing our calculator
demo here. Again,
this is a slide you're
gonna look at later and
say, did I learn all
these things? I hope so.
And I'm not going
back to these slides.
So let me talk about what's
coming up. On Friday, we have
this debugging Friday session.
I still don't have a room for
it, but it will be
announced on Piazza.
It's gonna be around noon,
maybe 1 o' clock,
maybe 11. I know some of
you have conflicting things
in that time and
might not be able to make it.
It's optional, I hope you're
all able to make it, however.
We'll also in that one,
be going over some like Xcode
shortcuts, how to get around
in Xcode a little more easily.
Cuz I always end up
clicking on everything, so
you can see what I'm doing.
But
there's command keys you can
do to really master Xcode. And
then don't forget
Monday's a holiday, so
don't show up here.
And then next Wednesday,
the reading assignment I
assigned on Monday, plus the
programming assignment that
I just put on Piazza today,
are both due
next Wednesday. And then next
Wednesday, you'll get another
reading assignment and another
programming assignment,
which will be due a week
later, okay? Okay,
here we go, back to our
calculator, here's where,
exactly where we left off
right here. And as I said when
we were there, this is
a great little calculator,
it's nice. But it's kind of
bad that this code right here,
which is the what of this
calculator, what is this?
This is a calculator. Here's
the calculations happening.
That really needs to be
in a different camp.
It can't be in the controller
like this. So that's the main
thing we're gonna do in
this demo right here,
is we're gonna
create a model for
this calculator,
where we're gonna put
all this calculation.
And then we're gonna make this
model really powerful and
extensible as you'll see. So,
we need to create a new data
structure for our model, and
we do that with
File > New File.
Any time we wanna create a new
class or new structure or
any kinda new data structure,
this is what we do.
So we hit this, it's gonna
be a Swift File right here.
We'll look at it, maybe one or
two of these others,
actually we probably
won't even look at those.
It's almost always gonna be
a Swift File that you create
here. Here it is, it wants
to know the name. So this is
the brain of my calculator,
right, the guts of it.
So I'm gonna call this
CalculatorBrain. That's gonna
be the name of the data
structure that I'm gonna use
here. And I'm gonna make sure
I put it in the same group,
down here,
as all the rest of my
classes like ViewController,
see that ViewController.swift?
I'm gonna put it in
the same place there.
All right, so here it is
on the left and right,
actually, let's just make
it fill the whole screen.
If we look in the navigator,
now we have three files,
okay, there's our controller,
there's our view, and
there's our model, MVC, voila,
okay, it's that easy. Now,
we need in this model to think
a little bit about what its
public API is. In other words,
what does this model allow
other people,
like controllers,
to do? Okay, that's one of the
most fundamental things that
you wanna do whenever
you're doing design.
Just think about what the
public API, does everyone know
what API means? Application
programming interface.
It's all the methods and
properties. Snd so
your public API is the methods
and properties you're gonna
allow other classes or other
data structures to access.
So we really, really wanna
think about that. Quickly also
notice that we've imported
Foundation here, not UIKit,
because this is not going to
be a UI class, right? This
is UI independent, this is the
model. Now I could say here,
okay, let's create a class
called CalculatorBrain. Nope,
not Brian, brain. So I could
do that, but I'm actually not
going to do that. I'm gonna
use a different data structure
here than a class, all right?
I'm gonna use a struct. Now,
you're probably used to using
struct in other languages, but
you probably think of it as
just like a little collection
of other variables is
a struct. In Swift,
struct is a first
class citizen,
very much like the class,
okay? And I'm gonna talk about
the difference between that
in a second. And in fact,
most of the commonly used
classes in Swift are structs,
like string, double,
array, dictionary,
these are all structs,
they're not classes. So
what's the difference
between a struct and a class?
I'm gonna talk in detail
about it next week, but
I'm gonna tell you two
important differences,
the two most important
differences.
One thing,
classes have inheritance,
structs do not, okay?
So if you're building
something that you think is
gonna need to be sub classed
to be extensible, you probably
wanna make it a class. I'm
gonna make my CalculatorBrain
extensible in a different way
as you'll see, so
it doesn't need to be a class.
I could possibly change
it back to a class if I
change my idea later, but
my current architecture does
not need to be sub classed,
so that's one difference.
The other difference,
huge difference, and
the one that's gonna take
the most getting used to for
you conceptually, is that
classes live in the heap, and
you have pointers to them.
Structs do not live in
the heap, and they are passed
around by copying them, okay?
We call the copying
style value types.
We call the, in the heap file,
style, reference types.
Because we have a reference
to them in the class case,
we actually copy them
around in the struct case.
Now, you know, that might
seem like a big restriction.
I gotta copy these things
around, what if they're big?
But as I mentioned on Monday,
these things are passed around
copy on right. So when you
pass them around, if you don't
actually change them, then no
copy is actually made. Okay,
but it's all behind the scenes
for you, all right?
So that's a huge difference.
Now why would I want my
CalculatorBrain to be a struct
instead of a class? Well,
I don't imagine I'm gonna have
a whole bunch of different
people referencing it.
The CalculatorBrain is
a brain for an MVC.
So that MVC is gonna access
it, but I, I don't see a lot
of other entities somehow
trying to point to this thing.
So I don't really need
to be reference type,
okay. I can have it be a value
type from that standpoint. So
it's probably fine. Also
it's a great opportunity for
me to show you what it looks
like to make a struct because
making a struct looked almost
just like being a class,
but there's a couple
minor differences,
which you're gonna see
real soon here, okay?
So now back to the public API,
what is the public API of
this? Well, I know that
this CalculatorBrain is gonna
need a func that performs
operation. Okay, for sure
because that's fundamentally
what it does. It performs
an operation. And we'll use
the same mechanism we used
on Monday to define it.
I will have some mathematical
symbol be the thing that
defines what operation we're
performing, okay? And notice
that I made the external name
be blank. It's a close call
here as whether you would
want it to be symbol.
In other words, would I call
performOperation like this,
okay, performOperation(symbol,
whatever. Or
whether I want it to be blank,
and I say performOperation,
and I just put the string,
the symbol in here like pi or
whatever.
It's a close call here,
this is a close judgement
call as to which is better.
I'm gonna go with this because
I think reading this code,
performOperation pi makes
perfect sense to me.
Adding the word symbol
in there doesn't really
make it any clearer to me, so
that's the way I'm gonna
go with this one. Okay,
what else do I need? Well, if
you're performing operations,
you have to have operands
to perform one, right?
If you're doing square root,
you have to do square root
of something, whatever. So
I'm gonna have to have some
func that sets the operand as
well, okay? And again, I'm
gonna have no external name,
and we'll call it the operand.
And I'm gonna have my
entire CalculatorBrain
work in doubles. It's
gonna be a double precision
CalculatorBrain, so I'm gonna
have the operand be a double.
Now, here's a case where I
definitely know that I don't
wanna have an external name,
because saying setOperand
(operand: 5.0), that's
ridiculous, that's completely
redundant, don't need it.
It's very clear, if I do this,
setOperand(5.0).
That's clear what I'm talking
about. So no question in my
mind that that's better.
And then you set the operand,
you perform operations,
guess what? You gotta
get the result. Now, I could
have a func to getResult or
something like that.
That returns a double, right?
That's one thing I do. But
that's really not very Swift.
Really in Swift what you would
do is you say, here's a result
var, that returns result. Now
the only problem with that UI,
or that API rather, is I don't
want anyone to set my result.
I'm the calculator brain,
I calculate the result. So
this needs to be read-only.
Anyone remember how we
can make a var read-only?
No? Someone suggest let.
And that's kinda
not exactly what let does.
Let makes it to constant,
meaning that it's read-only.
But it can only set once.
Whereas result is constantly
changing. So we can't do let,
unfortunately.
But it's a really good guess.
Actually we do it with the
computed property thing. Okay,
remember we computed
that display value and
we had get and set? Well, we
just don't do the set, right?
In this case we're just not
gonna do. Just not put that on
there. Boom,
this is a read-only property.
Everybody got that? It's
like currentTitle on button.
It's get only. All right now,
I'm gonna think a little
bit about the internal
implementation of this before
I go and start using this
thing. I know that a
calculator brain, internally,
it kind of accumulates its
answer as it's going. And
so I'm actually gonna have an
internal var, and watch this,
private var. I'm gonna
call it accumulator, I'm
gonna make it a double, okay?
So this is gonna be internal.
So now, other people
can't access this.
That's what private means.
And for all your homeworks for
this entire quarter, I want
you to put private in front of
things that you think
are internal implementation.
To any class you've create in
this, in this course, okay?
So get used to doing that.
It's very important.
These three are not private.
They're public.
I'm gonna allow other
people to call these. But
this one is internal.
Now, one thing you notice is
I don't have any error up here
that says no initializer.
Remember that when
I created a var in
the view controller,
and it said that there's no
initializers. And I had to
make userInTheMiddleOfTyping
equal false. Why don't
I have to do it here? That's
because this is a struct. And
structs automatically
get an initializer.
That will initialize all of
their uninitialized vars,
okay?
You get a free initializer.
You don't get that with class.
Only with the structs, so
there is one difference
between class and structs.
So we're gonna have a struct,
for CalculatorBrain, or
an initializer for
CalculatorBrain. That will
take a double and it'll
initialize as accumulator.
But actually,
I don't wanna do that.
Because let me think of what
is accumulator's initial value
really wanna be? When someone
creates a CalculatorBrain,
I don't wanna have them to
tell me what the accumulator's
initial value is.
Because I know what the
initial accumulator internally
its initial value is when
I start up. It's not set.
So I'm gonna make
this be an optional.
Do you see why I'm
making that an optional?
Because the accumulator when
I create my brain. I haven't
accumulated any result.
So I'm in this not set state.
So, it's a perfect opportunity
to make this a double or
an optional so I can express
that in my code. All right? So
if I have this internal
accumulator right here,
how can I use that
to implement these?
Well, two of them are easy.
Okay, setOperand
just sets the accumulator
equal to that operand. Okay,
cuz when you set a new
operand to operate on,
that replaces anything you
have on your accumulator.
It's what you're now
accumulating. So that, that
could be any, any easier than
that. And then we get results,
you're just gonna return
the accumulator. Now,
we've got a couple of
errors here that we
have to deal with.
What's this one right here?
This looks perfectly fine.
How could this be bad?
Accumulator is an optional
double, I'm setting it to
a double. It's gotta work,
what's the problem?
Says I cannot assign to this
property, because self is
immutable. Self meaning the
calculator brain is immutable.
And it's saying, do you wanna
fix this by making this method
be mutating? You see he's
trying to add this here.
Another difference
between structs and
classes, if you have a method,
okay? Or a property
that you're setting, that
well, if you have a method and
it changes the value
of this thing,
you have to mark it mutating.
You have to tell Swift, this
method can change the value
of this struct. Why is that?
It's because of that copy
on write thing. Remember,
I told you that structs are
passed around by copying them.
And when you write to them,
then it copies it. So
it has to know you're writing
it by calling setOperand.
So, you have to make
setOperand be mutating func.
So that's the difference
between class and a struct.
With that, what's this error
down here? A different error.
Anyone know what this
error is? Louder? Okay,
the problem here is we're
trying to return a double,
an accumulator is an optional.
Okay, so it's saying here,
hey unwrap this. Now, I do
not wanna do this here. Okay,
because it's perfectly valid
for the accumulator to be not
set. In fact, this starts
out not set. And in fact,
I can think already of another
case where the accumulator is
gonna be not set. What if I
say, five times three equals,
in my calculator?
After I say five times,
my accumulator is
not set right now.
Cuz I need the three equals
until I can get the result. So
my accumulator's often gonna
be going back to not set.
When we're in that weird five
times three equals five times,
the accumulator's not set
right now. Three, okay,
the accumulator's set again,
equals, okay,
here's the result. Okay,
so I can't have this
be exclamation point.
Or this thing is gonna crash
every time someone asks for
the result after they say five
times. So we can't have that.
So instead, I'm going to turn
result into an optional. And
that makes sense too.
Because if someone using this
object in the middle of five
times says, what's the
results? It'll tell you it's
not set, because I'm in the
middle of five times, right?
And in your homework, you're
even gonna make it clearer to
users of this why this
might not be set, okay? So
you'll see that. All right, so
that's a good start to the
implementation of this thing.
But before we go into deeper
in this implementation,
let's go back to our
controller and use this public
API that I just designed.
Okay, I wanna use this.
So I'm gonna go back
to my controller. Now,
I wanna have my controller and
my model on screen on the same
time. Just so I can see
them side by side. And
the best way to do that is
to bring out this assistant
editor thing again, right?
And you can go up to the top.
And you can actually
manually pick. Or
I'm gonna teach you
one little Alt thing.
If you hold down Alt and click
on some other file over here,
you'll get that to
appear on the right.
So Alt-clicking means
bring it up on the right.
Okay, so here I have
my model on the left.
And here I have my
controller on the right.
So what I need to do now is
fix this broken code that is
doing model stuff inside the
controller by using the public
API of my model.
Now, notice that
touchDigit does nothing when
it comes to calculating.
All it does is get the digits
from the keyboard and
put them in the display. It's
not doing any calculating, so
we don't have to touch that.
Same thing here with this
display value computed var.
All it's doing is converting
the display from
a double to a string and
back. That's all it does.
It has nothing to do
with being a calculator.
That's just the UI for
this particular calculator. So
the only thing we actually
have to change is this method,
performOperation. Now,
we know that this part in here
does not belong in here. And
in fact, I'll throw it over
here in my model. Even though
it's not gonna work there.
But we'll throw it over there
for now just to get it out of
the way, okay? So now we
need to somehow use this
API over here in this
implementation. So,
let's look at all three
parts of what has to do,
what we have to do in perform
operation. First of all,
if we're in the middle
of typing a number,
we need to set that number
as an operand, okay?
Because obviously, the user
typing in a number and
they perform an operation
that number they were typing
needs to be an operand.
So, right off the bat here.
I'm gonna say, if the user
is in the middle of typing,
then I'm going to set
the operand. Now, how do I
communicate to my brain here?
Where is my brain? [LAUGH] I
don't have a var for my brain.
So let's create a var, and
it will be private. Because
the model is almost always
private to the controller. Cuz
you don't want someone else
reaching in and messing with
this controller's model. So
I'm gonna make it
a private var.
I'm gonna call it brain. Its
type is CalculatorBrain, okay?
That's good. Now, as soon as
I put this line of code in,
look what I get. The old, you
don't have any initializers.
That's because this
is not initialized.
So I'm gonna initialize it by
creating a CalculatorBrain.
And you create
a CalculatorBrain in exactly
the same way that you
create as a class.
With the name of the type and
then the parentheses.
Now we have no arguments
in here. Because we have no
uninitialized var. Since we
made this be an optional,
it's initialized to nil
automatically for us for free,
remember? So we have no
uninitialized vars, so
we just do open parentheses,
closed parentheses. And
of course, we don't
need this type, right?
Because it gets inferred. So
if we ask what type is this?
It says, that's a calculator
brain. Has to be cuz that's
what you set it to. All right,
so now that we have a model,
our controller. This is the
green arrow, talking from our
controller to the model.
We can say, brain set your
operand to be whatever
the display value is. And
of course now we are not in
the middle of typing, so I'll
put that in here. So that's
all we need to do to set
the brain's operand. We only
need to do if these are in
the middle of typing
something new,
and they hit
an operation button.
We need to give them
that operand, okay?
Now, what about the stuff
that was in here, okay?
We get this mathematical
symbol of the operation to do.
Now I'm just gonna
let the brain do it.
So I'm just gonna say
brain perform operation,
the mathematical symbol.
That's it.
I'm just handing that off to
the model. Because that's,
this is not my job as a
controller to do calculation.
Okay I'm a UI guy.
Now of course after the
operation is done I need to
set my display value equal
to the brain's result.
But of course I can't do
this because displayValue
is a double.
And the result, might be
not set cuz it's an optional.
So I'm gonna say here,
if I can let the result
equal the brain to results.
In other words, if the brain's
result is determined. Then I
will let the displayValue
equal the result. That's it.
Okay, so that little piece of
code to input has completely
taken all calculation
out of the controller.
And put you into this
other camp the model.
And now we can spend the rest
of this lecture making this
really powerful model.
And nothing is gonna
change over here.
I'm literally never gonna edit
this code ever again. In fact,
I'm just gonna get it
off the screen. And
we're gonna spend all of our
time over here in the model.
So, let's start by making
kind of a really dirt simple
implementation of
performOperation here. Which
is try to get this code that
was already there to work.
And mostly, that's just a
matter of changing the names.
Because this
argument is symbol,
not mathematical symbol.
So, we'll do that.
And instead of setting a
display value cuz we're not in
a UI any more.
Now we're just setting the
accumulator to that double pi.
Right, and the same thing here
we're setting the accumulator
to be the square root of
the accumulator. Okay,
now this is a problem
right here.
This line, why?
Accumulator is an optional.
You can't take the square root
of an optional. So I could say
for example, if let operand
equal the accumulator.
So if my accumulator is set,
then I can tap the accumulator
be the square root of
the operand, okay? Now,
we have another warning right
here on both of these lines.
Why do you think, does anyone
know why this is? We seen it
before, five minutes ago. This
modifies this CalculatorBrain.
So this method,
perfomOperation, also needs
mutating in front of it,
okay? So I'll fix that,
add mutating.
Adding this mutating takes
a little bit getting used to.
But it's great because its
compiler notices it. And it's
gonna always be reminding you
to do that. So believe it or
not we now have an MVC version
of this calculator and if we
run it should just work.
All right,
here we go. Let's see.
7, 8, that's still working.
Okay, that was in
the controller. Pi, woah,
that's working.
It's going off to the model.
And this is actually
executing. And it's causing
the accumulator to get set
to that double pi. And
then flicking at the result
and putting it in display. How
about 81 square root, square
root? All right, excellent,
okay. So now we're starting in
a place where exactly where we
were before. But we split off
all of our calculating code
into this little class
right here. So this is
a great opportunity now to
enhance this to the max.
So we are gonna use all kinds
of cool, Swift stuff that you
probably did not see
in other languages.
To make this a much more
extensible calculator.
Cuz right now, man, if I
wanna add more operations.
I just get this huge switch
statement case, this case,
that case. I'm gonna have
to do if let operand equals
accumulator every single time.
For the things that are unary
operations like square root.
Imagine when I have the binary
case like five times three
equals. I'm gonna have to do
the figuring out how to deal
with the times and the equals
for every single case.
Forget it. I can't do that. I
need to build an engine here.
That can deal with constants.
That can deal with these unary
operations like square root.
That can deal with binary
operations like multiply and
plus and things like that.
Okay? So that's exactly what
we're going to do. We're going
to enhance this model. Now,
as we do all this enhancement,
we're not going to change it
externally at all. And so the
controller will not change.
That's what's really cool
about this. We can do our
model development
independent of our UI.
Once we have the UI, that kind
of does the basics, all right.
So what are we going to do
here? Let's focus first.
Let's get rid of this code,
cuz we know that's a mess.
We're not going to do that.
Let's focus on constants.
Wouldn't it be kind of cool if
I could like, build a table.
Okay, I'll do square brackets
to hold my table. And
in this table, I had, like pi
and double dot pi. And then,
maybe I had e's does everyone
know what the constant e is.
Mathematic 2.71 one something.
We have a nice symbol for
that and not quite as nice as
Double.pi. But it's called
M under bar E. So, and I put
all my constants in a table.
And then here in
performOperation,
I'll just look up the symbol
in that table and
get the value. Wouldn't that
be a lot more extensible for
constants? Right, I could add
all the constants I want.
I just, one line of code each.
That would be a lot better
than putting extra case this
blah blah blah. Okay, so
how can we do that?
We need to create a table.
So how do we create
a table in Swift?
We use the struct called
dictionary, okay? So
dictionary is how you create
a hash table of things. And so
I'm gonna create
a private var.
I'm gonna call it,
I could call it Constants, but
I'm gonna call it Operations
cuz I'm basically, eventually
going to enhance it to work
for all of our operations.
And it's gonna be of type
Dictionary. Now Dictionary,
you're gonna see a new feature
in Swift right here. It, this,
you have this feature in Java,
as well. It is a generic type.
So a dictionary, it can be
a dictionary that goes from
almost any kind of key to
almost any kind of value.
Okay, the key has to
implement a certain protocol.
It basically has to
be hashable. Okay,
so as long as it's hashable,
then it can be a key and
then the value can be any
type. So you specify that,
same as in Java, the key type.
So I'm gonna have my key
be a string like pi or e.
And then the value is
going to be a double,
like Double.pi here, or _E,
okay? And believe it or
not, I can actually say
equals this syntax and
it will create one for me with
that step in there, okay? So
open square bracket, key colon
value comma key colon value,
that's how you can
put a dictionary.
Now of course, you can add
things to a dictionary and
remove things, and
get things out of dictionary.
I'll show you that
in a second. But
this is a nice way to do this.
So
let's do that. Okay, so
we have this nice dictionary.
So now we could use this
dictionary of operations and
performOperation.
I'm gonna say,
if I can let the constant that
I want equal the operation
that matches that symbol then,
now why am I doing if let here
for operations sub-symbol?
This operation sub-symbol,
that's how you look up a
symbol in a dictionary, right?
Operation to the dictionary,
click on it, right?
To dictionary, strings and
doubles. So you look it up.
When you look it up,
it returns an optional of
the value. Why, anyone
think why it would do that?
>> It might not be there.
>> Exactly, it might not be in
the table. Okay, what if
I say operations sub X,
that's gonna return not set,
because there's no
X in this table. Only pi and e
are in there, okay? So that's
why I have to do if let there,
and if the constant is there,
now I can set my accumulator
equal to that constant,
okay? Because this constant
is gonna be a Double, because
this is a Dictionary that has
Doubles as its values, okay?
That's cool. Let's go ahead.
Let's run it.
That's all we need to do. So
now we've built, for constants
only, a much more extensible
internal architecture here,
to our calculator brain.
So of course, square root's
not gonna work, okay,
but pi works, and if I add an
e button, it would do e. Okay,
everybody cool with
what I did there? But
of course, that's kind of
useless just for constants.
We wanna be something like
this, watch this. Quote,
do my Emoji & Symbols here.
There's our square root,
square root colon,
what do we wanna put over
here? How about square root?
Okay, and maybe a cosine.
Put cosine there.
And wouldn't that be cool
if we could do that, okay?
Because now we'd really
have an extensible table,
it can do constant and also
can do these unary functions.
But we got a problem here,
because square root is most
definitely not a Double,
right? Square root
is like a function, so that's
no good. So we're gonna,
if we wanna have a dictionary
that has mixed things in it,
we need to create a type
here that represents those
mixed things. So that's what
we're gonna do, we're gonna
create a new type, okay? This
is gonna have a data type that
you're gonna be somewhat used
to, to other languages, but
you're gonna see it much
more powerful in Swift.
I'm gonna make it a private
type that's embedded inside my
CalculatorBrain, so you can
have types within types and
it's just a scoping issue,
that's just a naming issue,
okay? The name of this is
gonna be CalculatorBrain,
the dot, what I call it here.
And it's not gonna be a struct
or a class, it's gonna be
an enum. Does everyone
know what an enum is in other
classes? It's basically a data
structure that has
discrete values. Right,
it can only be one, like case
this, case that, whatever.
It can only be one of
a discrete value and
the same thing here in Swift.
I'm gonna call it Operation,
and it's gonna have
case constant and
case unaryOperation. So those
are the two kinds of things.
And then I'm gonna make this
Dictionary return an Operation
instead of a Double. Okay, so
that means I have change all
of these, to say
Operation.constant, because
this is a constant. We'll just
comment that out for a second.
And then this is also
an Operation.constant.
This one will be
an Operation.unaryOperation.
I can just call that
Operation.unary.
We'll say unary operation.
Operation.unaryOperation,
okay?
Cool! Okay, we can't do this
anymore, of course, cuz now
it's not a constant that
we're pulling out of there.
It's actually an operation,
okay? And obviously,
we can't do that because
this constant here,
is now an operation not
a double. So we can't say that
equals that, okay? So this is
good. This is getting better.
We've got our table to be
able to have both things. But
in doing this, I've lost
the fundamental meaning
of all of these things.
I commented it out. So
now this table is kind
of useless, right?
It knows that pi
is a constant.
It knows that square root
is a unary operation.
But it's so what? Because we
can't do any of them. And
this is where, something
you've heard of before,
associated values comes in.
Remember optional has
this thing where when it's
in the set stage it has this
associated value that's
associated with the set state,
but is not associated with the
not set state? Okay, optional
is an enum. It's an enum with
two cases. The not set case,
which is called none and the
set case, which is called sum.
And in the sum case, it has
a little associated value with
it. And we can do the exact
same thing, okay? In our enum,
when the case is a constant,
we can have an associated
Double. And that's,
we just put it right there and
we can actually could have
multiple associated values.
We only need one for
constants. But we can have
this associated value.
Okay, so associated values
are something not specific
to optionals. It's for
all enums in Swift. So this
is super powerful because now
when I add a constant into
this table, for example,
I can just associate
Double.pi with it.
Same thing with this constant,
I'll just associate the value
of e with it. Okay, now we'll
get to these ones in a second.
A little more complicated
there. All right, so
now I've got a table with
got constants in there and
I actually know the values.
So down here, when I get the
operation out of here, right,
this is a type Operation,
it's one of these enums. How
do I look at each of these,
and like get this associated
value? Well, how would you
look at the values of
an enum in another language?
You would probably
switch on them. So
I'm gonna switch on
this operation and
I'm gonna do a case for
when it's a constant. And
I'm gonna do a case,
we'll do colon and break.
And I'm gonna do a case for
when it's a unaryOperation,
and break on that case, okay?
And I don't even have to
say default here, because
these are the only two values
that an operation can be,
cuz it's an enum,
it only has one of these two
values. Now here, you can see,
it already put this in
parentheses right here.
Okay, it wants to help you get
that associated value out.
Okay, awesome,
how do we do that?
We say let
associatedConstantValue or
whatever we wanna call
this variable. And
that means inside here,
associatedConstantValue
is gonna be that associated
value. Now we would never call
it associatedConstantValue.
We'll rename it in a second.
But now what are we
gonna do with it? Well,
in the constant case we're
just gonna set our accumulator
to that associated value.
Now, why we wouldn't call this
associatedConstantValue? Well,
first of all, anyone reading
this code knows that this
is the associated value,
so you don't need to say
associated. And we know i's
a constant because we're
in the constant case, so
i's really a waste
to say that.
So, we would just say value
here. Cuz that's what it is,
i's the constant value that's
associated with it, okay?
We don't need break.
Everybody got that?
By the way, switches are
slightly different in Swift in
that they don't fall into each
other. When you have constant,
it does this, and it's done.
It doesn't go down, fall down
to the next case, okay? So you
don't need break at the end
of every single one, which
is really nice. All right?
So this is great. So
should this work? I think so.
Let's try it. All right.
So. Pi, okay, square root we
haven't done anything with,
but pi should work.
Let's try. Bingo, okay.
So you see how pi
is working here?
We're saying to look up pi
in this table. It finds that
it's a constant operation with
this as the associated value.
We switch on that operation.
Find out that it's a constant.
We let value equal
the associated value,
and then we just set
that to the accumulator.
And now that's our result, the
next time they ask for result
that's what we got. Okay,
now let's do unary operation.
Okay, this one's
a little tougher, okay?
Cuz really what I wanna
do is this. Right?
The associated value wants
to be those functions.
Can I do that in Swift?
Of course!
We wouldn't be here if
we couldn't do that.
How do we make an associated
value be a function?
Well the cool thing about
Swift is that functions
are normal types. Just
like a double, any struct,
a class, no difference
between that and a double.
So how do I go back up
to my enum, and it have
an associated type here be
a double? How do I say,
the type which is a function
that takes a double and
returns a double? Cuz
that's what I want in here.
This is a unary operation, so
I need this to be a function
that takes a double and
returns a double. We just
type it, function that takes
a double, returns a double.
Just type it right in there.
This is a type.
Just a type, just like string,
but it happens to be
a function. Now I'm
going to take a time-out right
here just to show you a little
bit more about this
function types,
to make sure you're getting
this. And what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna create a new
thing called a playground.
So a playground is just a
place we can play around with
iOS code. Okay? So
you just say new playground,
this is gonna be an iOS
playground. I'm gonna call it
my CalculatorPlayground,
I can call it anything I want.
Just gonna save it on disk so
that what I
type in here when I'm playing
gets saved for the next time.
You can put it
anywhere you want.
I recommend the same place,
home directory, Developer.
Okay, don't put it inside
another project or whatever.
And you can see the playground
looks like this. On the left,
you can type any iOS code
you want. And on the right,
it's going to evaluate what's
on the left and show you not
only, well, it's basically
gonna show you the result or
the value of any
var that it finds.
So here it found this var
string, str, and it's
showing you the value of str
over here. Okay? So I can say,
for example, let i = 27 and
it's gonna say that 27 is what
it sees there. But
I'm gonna create a new var.
I'm gonna call it f. Its type
is gonna be a function that
takes a double and returns a
double. Okay, that's its type.
I could have said f,
var f string, but
I said it's a function
that takes a double and
returns a double. And
I'm gonna set the value of f.
I'm gonna set it equal
to square root. Okay,
I mean it's a function
that takes a double and
returns a double. So I can say
f = square root. Now how do I
actually call this function?
Well I'm gonna let x equal f
of 81, for example.
Okay, so I call this variable,
right here, which is a double
that takes a double,
just like it was a function.
And if I were to go back and
change this to cosine,
look what happens. Okay,
so now f is cosine so now I'm
getting the cosine of 81.
I can even write
my own function,
how bout func changeSign,
let's say it takes
a double and
returns a double, okay.
So it's a regular function,
returns the changeSigned
operand, right,
operand changed sign. So
now I could go down here and
change this to be changeSign,
function I wrote. And
now I'm getting minus 81.
Okay? So everyone's seeing how
this type functions as a type?
They're just normal type.
Absolutely, you can use
a function as a type anywhere
you can use any other type.
Argument to a method,
associated value in an enum,
local variable, anything.
No restriction on it, okay?
I'm even gonna take the,
note also, by the way, the
change sign has an external
name, operand. When you tall,
call change sign,
looks like this. See? We've
got this operand. It's okay,
when I call it down here, I
don't have to say f(operand).
In fact, I can't say that.
And that's because f
is just a function that takes
a double, returns a double.
It can be any function
that takes a double and
returns a double, so you can't
have those external names in
there, cuz it can
be any function.
As you change it you can't be
changing this, so, anyway,
just a minor note there.
So I'm gonna take changeSign,
actually, and copy and paste
it back into my code up here,
so I just made a new function,
it's even a nice global
to this file, function
called changeSign. And
I can go back here and say,
changeSign, let's do something
for changeSign. I think I
can remember how to do this,
there, Ctrl + C, Cmd + Ctrl +
Space, something like that,
let's go here. Edit, Okay,
we need something for
changeSign, I think I have
one here, this one, okay?
It's not really change
sign [LAUGH] but,
it's all right we'll use
it for that. And, so
this is an operation, an
Operation.unaryOperation(chan-
geSign). Okay? Perfectly
legal. Okay, everybody got
that? So now, down here in
our switch, in the same
way that we grabbed the
constant value with let value,
let's grab that associated
function with let function.
And again we can call, this
doesn't have to be a function.
This could be f. It could be
func. Can't be func, because
that's a keyword, but function
it could be. Okay? So we got
this unary operation. What are
we gonna do? Well we just want
to call this thing with
the accumulator. Okay?
But of course we'd better, I'm
sorry, we want our accumulator
to equal, calling that
function with the accumulator.
We'd better check though to
make sure this is not nil. So
I'm actually gonna do
something a little different.
Instead of if let, I'm gonna
say if the accumulator does
not equal nil. Then we'll
do this. This is another
way to protect against this
crashing your app. Okay,
somewhat similar to if let
operand equal accumulator,
but I'm just actually checking
to see if accumulator is in
the not set state,
accumulator isn't optional,
so it can be equal to nil or
it's equal to something else,
and it has an associated value
like these things. All right?
That's all we need to do.
Let's take a look. Whoops,
we, we have errors there?
No, we don't. Okay. All right.
So, pi, still good.
81, square root.
Working like a charm. Okay,
and again if we add cosine and
those which we are going to
add those in a second, but for
time I'm not adding them in.
But we'll add cosine and
all, actually I'm,
forget it, let's do it.
Let's go back to our UI right
here and let's add those other
buttons. Let's put
cosine in here. Cosine,
and let's even put our little
change sign that we did there.
Ctrl+Cmd+Space, there we go.
Change sign.
Put the change sign in there.
So we'll put those in there
and that's all we
need to do in my UI.
It can just run again,
because my brain,
my model already knows how
to do those operations.
So I can put any operation
my brain knows how to do
into my calculator's UI and
it'll just work.
So here we got, you know,
how about pi cosine, -1.0,
all right? Change sign,
positive 1.0. All right, so
this is really looking nice,
because our calculator brain,
still hardly any code in here,
and yet
now it's fully extensible for
both constants and
unary operations. What's next?
Binary operations.
5 times 3 equals, okay,
much more difficult, right?
Because there's actually two
operations there when we do 5
times 3 equals. There's the
times, which puts you in this
weird pending state, and
then there's the equals which
actually finishes the 5 times
3 equals, right? So I'm
gonna need some data structure
to remember the 5 times
until the equals comes along.
Okay, so let's do that,
let's add a data structure for
that. Actually, before we even
do that, let's back up here
and talk about all this mess.
What's this gonna be like for
binary operations? So we need
a binary operation here.
And what's its type gonna be?
What's its associated value
gonna be? What do you think?
How about a function
that takes two double and
returns a double? All right,
and we're also gonna need
an equals operation as well.
And so
we can just go down here and
do, for example, times,
let's do times.
Oops, space, there we go.
I've got a nice mathematical
times symbol here. Okay,
we have to enter in
Operation.binaryOperation. And
we need multiply basically
here. So I'm gonna make my own
multiply function.
We'll just put multiply there.
Also of course, I need equals
which is Operation.equals.
Okay, put those on my table.
So this multiply,
where's that? There's no
function called multiply.
Well, just like I did
changeSign up here,
I'm gonna create my
own little func,
multiply. It's gonna take op1,
which is a Double,
and op2,
which is a Double. And
it's gonna return a Double,
of course. Oops, and
it's just gonna return
op1 times op2, okay?
So I got this nice function
up here. Fits in here nice,
no error, everything's
fine there, got that. So
now we have the hard part of
what do we do with the case
here that is binary operation?
We still have a function,
but now it's a function that
takes two doubles and returns
a double. All right, so what
are we gonna do here? Get,
like I said, we're gonna need
some kind of data structure
to remember five times and
wait till we get another
case which is equals, okay?
And we're gonna have to
do something in here. So
let's take a time out here and
create another data structure
to remember five times
while we're waiting for
three equals to happen.
So I'm gonna make it a struct.
It's also gonna be an embedded
private struct, just like this
was embedded private enum.
So the name of this enum,
its full name is
CalculatorBrain.Operation, but
as long as I'm using
it inside this struct,
we can just call it operation,
like we did right here.
Okay, so same thing here.
I'm gonna call this one
PendingBinaryOperation.
Okay, it's gonna be
a PendingBinaryOperation.
And it's gonna have two vars.
One is the function which is
gonna be, it takes two
Doubles, returns a Double. And
it's going to have the first
operand, which is a Double.
So it's just gonna be a struct
that holds those two things.
Now never forget that structs
in Swift can have methods and
things like that. In fact,
I'm gonna put a method on here
just to remind us of that.
I'm gonna have a func
called perform which will
perform this binary operation.
Now what does
it need to perform it?
It needs a second operand.
Okay? And it's gonna
return a double. Okay,
now, notice the naming here.
Why did I use this naming,
with as my external and here
secondOperand as my internal?
Well, secondOperand
is the internal,
because that's what
this argument is.
And in my code here,
I want the firstOperand and
secondOperand to have
the right names. But
I'm using with because when
someone calls this, they're
gonna say perform(with: 5.0).
And of course,
if they're performing
a pending binary operation, so
this makes perfect sense.
If you say binary operation,
perform(with: 5.0). It makes
sense, right? And these
internal names, even though
they're only used internally,
you can think of them as
part of the documentation.
Cuz anyone who sees the
documentation of this method,
he's gonna see both with and
secondOperand, see? So they're
kind of getting a little bit
of documentation that that
with is with the secondOperand
to this binary operation.
Okay, and how would we perform
this? Well, we would just
return the firstOperand times
the secondOperand, okay? But
we're not doing times here,
we're doing this function.
So I'm gonna call it that
function with the firstOperand
and the secondOperand. Okay,
this is a really simple little
method, but I just
wanted to make it clear.
Notice this method doesn't
have mutating on it. Because
it doesn't actually change
the PendingBinaryOperation,
right? It just returns to the
evaluation of the function,
but it doesn't change any
internal values. Also notice,
these are lets. That's
because I'm gonna create this
PendingBinaryOperation in
a moment with these two things
set and
I'm never gonna change them.
So they are constants in this
struct. Now, also notice,
no error that says you don't
have an initializer and you
have these two uninitialized
vars. Again, this is a struct.
Structs automatically
get a free initializer
which will initialize
all of these things. And
in fact,
let's use that right now.
I'm gonna create a private
var, which I'm gonna call pbo,
PendingBinaryOperation, but
only temporarily, because
this is a bad name. I'm mostly
doing it so things won't
wrap, cuz I'm using a big font
so you can see here. I'm gonna
go actually change this back
to a better name in a second.
But this pbo is
a PendingBinaryOperation,
and optional.
Why is this an optional
PendingBinaryOperation?
Cuz we're not always in the
middle of a binaryOperation.
Only when the person
taps five times. Okay,
if we'd said five square root,
we're not in the middle of
a PendingBinaryOperation, so
this has to be not set. Are
you starting to get a feel for
how we use optionals
all over the place,
to be semantically exactly
what we mean? And here,
if we're not in the middle
of PendingBinaryOperation,
this is not set. So it's
an optional. All right, so
when you've pressed the times,
5 times, all I'm gonna do
here is remember, or create,
a PendingBinaryOperation.
So I'm gonna say pbo =
PendingBinaryOperation.
Now when I tab here, and I do
the open parentheses. Look,
it's showing me that there's
already an initializer,
one that, tab, takes
function and firstOperand.
Woo-hoo! So this is that
free initializer I get,
because I'm a struct down
here, not a class. So what is
the function? Well, that's
just this function right here,
that we got as our
associated value.
That's the function in
the binaryOperation.
And what's the firstOperand?
Well, it's our current
accumulator, right,
five times are equal if
it's a five, okay? Now,
here I'm unwrapping it, so
I better do if accumulator
does not equal nil. Cuz I
don't want to crash here and
I'm, so that means I'm gonna
ignore times. If you've
pressed times and you
haven't given me an operand,
we're just gonna ignore that.
It's like if you start up your
calculator and say, times 3
equals, I'm gonna ignore it,
because I don't have any
operands who times it by.
Okay, so that's good, that's
what I want. Also, when I
have this times, I'm gonna set
my accumulator here to nil.
Because I'm in this weird
half state five times,
my accumulator is waiting for
the three equals to
be set to anything.
So I'm setting it to nil not
set for the moment. All right,
so that's it, that's all I
need to do when times is hit.
But now when equals is hit,
I have the the three, and
I need to calculate
five times three.
So I need to actually call
this perform down here. So
I'm gonna put this in its own
little method. I'm gonna call
it performBinaryOperation,
actually, we'll even say
performPendingBinary, oops,
BinaryOperation, okay.
I'm putting it in
another method,
you'll see why in a moment.
Okay, so I'm gonna do private
func which is that, now what
am I gonna do in here? Well,
here I'm going to perform that
pendingBinaryOperation. So
I'm gonna do pbo.perform, and
what am I gonna perform with?
I'm gonna perform with
the current accumulator, okay?
Now notice this put a question
mark right there, okay?
The reason I need a question
mark there, really,
what I wanted was exclamation
point. Because pbo, here,
is an optional, and
I need to unwrap it.
But what's really cool is if
instead of exclamation point,
you put question mark,
then it will unwrap it, but
it's not set,
it will just ignore this line.
Ignore the rest of the line,
okay? So
that's kind of a cool feature.
But I'm not gonna do that,
cuz I didn't really talked
enough about it, so
I'm gonna unwrap it. So here I
need to make sure pbo is not
nil. And I need to make sure
that the accumulator is also
not nil, okay? So if those
two things aren't true,
I don't really want to be
doing this line of
code right here,
right? So I'm performing it,
I get the results and
I'm going to put that in
my accumulator, okay?
So my accumulator is no longer
nil, why is this happening?
It's the third time, mutating,
all right, excellent,
I love it when people catch
on real quick. So, yeah, that
needs to be mutating, cuz this
is changing the accumulator.
So it's modifying the internal
state of the calculator brain.
Now, the other thing is no
longer am I in the middle
of a pendingBinaryOperation,
so I have to set that to nil.
Okay, cuz I wanna be
consistent in all my
code that when that's nil, I'm
not in the middle of a pending
operation. I just had
the three equals, okay,
everybody set? Now, I told you
I didn't like pbo as a name.
It's a bad name, okay? Someone
looking at it would have to go
look at the declaration
to figure out it.
A better name here would be
pendingBinaryOperation, so
I'm gonna change it to that.
And here's how you can change
the name of something all
throughout the context
that it's in.
You just mouse over it,
I haven't clicked on it,
I moused over it.
You see that little arrow that
appears? If you click on that
you get a menu and you can
say, Edit All in Scope. And
now when you change this, it's
changing it everywhere. Okay,
so I changed it from pbo
to PendingBinaryOperation.
You can see why I did that,
because I didn't want
the wrapping to happen when
we were first doing it, okay?
So that's it,
that's all we need to do for
our little
Pending BinaryOperation, so
let's go ahead and add some
pending, some binary, so let'a
add some binary operations to
our UI. In fact, I'm going
to add a few that we don't
even have in our table yet.
So let's do times,
come up in the space.
Yeah, so here's times, but
I'm also going to do the other
ones here divide and plus and
it's just so we don't have to
come back here again to do
that. So there's divide, and
that there, I'll do
another one, do plus and
minus here. So I'm doing
command control space,
I guess,
to get this little emojis and
symbols thing and
a plus, okay?
And we need one other thing,
equals, gotta have an equals
button. So we'll put that down
there, okay? So now we only
have times, so times is the
only one that should work but
let's see. Actually I'm gonna
bring back that code so
you can see it at the same
time. It's hard to see it all
at once, but.
All right here we go, okay?
4 square root, that's still
working, pi, still working.
How about 8 times 6 equals,
wahoo, square root?
Nice, okay, so times is
working there beautifully.
Now the only thing is,
we have to do divide and
all that, so
I guess what I have to do is,
I go create this four times.
And I'm gonna have to go
here again and Ctrl+Space
again, we'll do divide. And
we'll go here and Ctrl+Space
and we'll do plus. And
then we're gonna go here and
we'll do command, space, and
we'll do minus, okay?
Now, am I gonna have to write,
write a method divide and
go up here and
copy and paste this and
do one with divide? You know,
if I have to do that, all of
a sudden, I'm feeling like,
this whole table business
really didn't buy me that
much, right? Cuz I'm still
having to create a method for
every single binary operation
I want to do? I mean, for
unary operations it was nice
because I had all these built
in ones, I did have to make
this one method. Yeah, I can
even see with unary operations
I wanna create a bunch more
and I'm having to create
these other functions.
It's not really
working out for me.
Okay, so how are we gonna fix
this? Well, we're gonna use
a feature in Swift,
which is really powerful.
And you're gonna have
to get used to it,
cuz it's not in a lot
of other languages.
It is in some other languages,
I don't wanna make it sound
like it's not around,
it's definitely around. But
may not be something you've
used in any languages you've
used and it's called closures.
Okay, how many people
know what a closure is,
have heard that before?
See, almost none of you,
so a closure is a function
embedded right in line of
your code, okay? And so,
we can actually take multiply
right here, select its code.
I'm gonna cut it, go down
here to where I used it and
paste it in there.
Now if didn't quite work,
there's two things we need to
do. One, this open curly brace
needs to be at the beginning.
So, we're going to
replace this open curly brace
with the keyword in, and
put the curly brace
at the beginning. So
that's how you take a function
and put it right in line.
Just literally copy and
paste to write in there.
Change the curly brace to in
and move it to the beginning,
okay, got that? So now we
don't even need multiply,
all gone. Now this
doesn't look much better.
It's still a lot of
typing stuff in, but
let's use Swift's inference of
type to make this a lot nicer.
Swift knows that this,
right here is this,
the associated value of that
type. So it knows that this
down here is a function
that takes two doubles and
returns a double. So we don't
need these types right here,
get rid of those. Okay,
now it's starting to
look better. In fact,
maybe if I go here and put
some things on the same line.
Yeah, now I'm liking it, okay.
But we can do even better than
this. Swift also knows that
this returns something.
So we don't overturn, okay.
Swift also will let you have
any number of arguments you
want. Called $0, $1, $2 $3,
for however how many.
So I don't need that or that.
I can say $0 times $1.
Okay, now I'm winning. Now,
the essentials of what is
going on here is right there.
And there's no
extraneous types and
all that business.
And of course, that means for
these other cases like divide,
I can say divide.
And for add, here I can see
plus, and for subtract,
I can do minus, even for our
friend change sign right here.
Okay, we can take
this copy it paste,
get rid of all this junk
because this is just -$0,
okay? So, this closures allow
you to do this thing where
you get the essentials of what
you're doing, right in there
in line. So, you're not having
to go look at some other
method somewhere like
changeSign up here.
The other thing closures allow
you to do, is to pass off to
methods some piece of code to
execute if something fails,
or when something completes.
Or do this and
animate it, while you're doing
it, for example. You're gonna
see API like that. So, being
able to pass these methods
around, you're gonna see.
Really makes for great, great
API. So, you're just seeing
the simplest possible use of
it here. We just using as the
associated value, but imagine
it as function, parameters and
things like that. It's,
it's pretty incredible. Okay,
so let's go see if that works.
All right, 4 x 5 = 20,
square root, cosine,
change sign, pi, cosine,
this all working beautifully.
And now, we can add as many
new operations as we want,
with one line each, okay. So,
you see how I built a struct
here that's extensible without
having to do sub-classing, and
all that stuff. I can just add
thing, and I could even go
further and make this public.
If I make this operations
table public. I also have
to make operation public,
then other people can get
my calculator brain int and
add operations to it,
okay? So very,
very sensible, not requiring
any subclassing whatsoever.
So, structs can often
be just as good,
if not a little bit
better design point for
classes. All right, the last
thing that I wanna do here.
Let's go back to our
simulator. Is talk about
the layout of the UI. You see
I have this layout right here.
Let's look what happens if I
rotate this into landscape
mode. So, I'm gonna go up
here in the simulator, and
go to Hardware, Rotate Left.
Okay, my calculator is
now completely unusable. Okay,
cuz there's no equals, so
I can't even do five times
three equals, right? So
it's completely useless,
I guess I can still do pi,
mm, but it's clear that's
not what you want, right?
When you rotate, you wanna use
that space in that way, okay?
And I promised you we were
gonna build a UI that would
work in all those things,
and, in fact,
we're gonna do that right now.
Let's go back to our UI,
and doing this is not gonna
require any change to
our controller or
our model. Okay,
this is purely something we're
gonna do in the view, and
we're gonna do it with this
business up down here. Okay,
this multiple phones that
we'll be able to click here,
and see how things look
in all these different
orientations right here.
And out basic strategy
is we're gonna stack all these
buttons into rows, and then
we're gonna stack all those
rows on top of each other.
And then we're gonna stack
that with the display, to make
this kind of block that has
our UI. Then we're gonna tie
the edges of that block, to
the edges of the device. So,
that as the device changes,
that block of stuff, gets
stretched out, or whatever.
And the stuff inside,
is gonna automatically now
how to resize the buttons and
stuff to lay out. Okay, so
that's all that we need to do
to make that happen. To have
nice rows and columns here,
I'm gonna add one more
button which you need for
your homework anyway. Which
is a dot button. One of your
homework assignment items, is
to make floating point input
possible. This is already
a floating point calculator.
I can say 4, 45. Well,
I can't type here, sorry.
But I can type 45 and
hit square root. And
it would give me a floating
point number, right?
But you can't enter any
floating point numbers,
'cuz there's no dot,
right? So,
that's part of
your assignment.
So, I'll put that in there for
you. Okay, so now,
I'm gonna take this row. And
I'm gonna put it into a stack.
It's gonna be a horizontal
stack on its side. And you do
that up here with editor.
Embed in Stack View, okay?
So, when I do that, see, it
stacks them up horizontally.
And I can inspect that stack,
it's selected right here.
And you can see Stack View
right there, it's horizontal.
I'm gonna put some spacing in
there, 10 points of spacing.
I'm also gonna make sure,
that they're equally spaced.
So, I want each of the squares
in there to be the same width.
All right, so same thing here.
Let's go this one.
Now, there's actually another
way besides going up here,
editor, embed in. There's
a button right here for it. So
common, there's a button
right there, Embed in Stack,
so boom, I'll do that. Again,
I'll put a space in here.
Notice that the cosine button
is wider than the 1, 2, 3.
So, I'm gonna say
fill equally and
make them all
the same width again,
Oops, sorry, again,
so we'll do 10 and
fill equally. Same thing here,
stack. Fill equally, 10 and
we'll stack this one.
Oops, dammit. Okay, now I'm
gonna take these horizontal
stacks. These five horizontal
and stack them vertically. So,
I'm gonna embed.
Notice that it's pretty smart.
It noticed they were
above each other so
it would automatically put
it in a vertical stack. But,
it pushed them all over to
the left in the stack, and I
want them to spread out across
the stack. So, I'm gonna have
the alignment here, instead
of leading, be fill, and
that's gonna fill the whole
width. And of course I want
spacing here as well, so we'll
do that. So look at this,
I got this beautiful keyboard,
keypad right here for
my calculator. Now, I'm gonna
hook that up to this display.
I'm just gonna select
them both, and
say stack them. Okay, puts
them into a stack. The left
line aligned it again,
leading aligned it there so
I'm gonna say fill, I don't
want fill equally here though.
Cuz if I do fill equally here,
it's gonna make this display
the same height as
the whole keypad, so
I don't want that.
So I just want fill,
I want to fill this space, but
I do want the spacing here so
we'll do 10 points again. So,
now that my whole UI in a nice
whole rectangle here. And
I'm just gonna tie the edges,
of this UI to the edges of
the device basically, okay.
Now, I'm gonna start here,
whoops, I'm gonna start, yeah
be careful a little about that
too. If you click on something
and drag it, see you might try
to drag the inner one away.
A trick for not doing that,
there's two tricks.
One, is you can do command
shift I believe it is, yeah.
Command shift will let you
pick which one you want,
under the mouse.
Actually it's control shift.
Control shift under the mouse
let's you pick it. But,
another easy way is
to use drag select,
to select the one you want,
and then pick it up.
Okay, so I'm gonna use the
blue lines, actually, to put
this at the proper space
on the left edge and top.
And now I'm gonna do the magic
to hook it to an edge. And
I do that with the Ctrl key,
just like we did dragging into
the code. But here, I'm gonna
drag from this selected thing.
Make sure the whole
thing is selected. And
Ctrl+Drag up to the top.
So we can tie it to the top.
And when you let go,
it's gonna say,
what relationship do you want
between this big box and
the top? And, and really it's
talking about the outer edge.
And you can try and
make them the same width, or
the same height, which really
doesn't make sense here.
Or you can pin this
vertical spacing to the top
layout guide.
So I basically pinned it to
the top. And same thing here,
I can go to the left and
pin the leading space. And
I can go to the right and pin,
pin the trailing space. And
I can go to the bottom and
sorry, yes, the bottom, and
pin the bottom space, the
vertical space in the bottom.
Now we're just seeing pinning
it to edges, but you can use
this mechanism to Ctrl+Drag
between any two elements and
say, make these two the same
width, line up the left edges,
line up the tops.
You see what I'm saying? And
once you have that ability to
have all your items have rules
of their relation to each
other, now you can imagine how
you can rotate the whole thing
and have it all look good,
because it's following
rules about what to do.
Now one thing about these two
pins, okay, those I pinned to
where I wanted them. But these
two pins are not what I want.
It's pinning it this
far from the edge. So
how do I fix that? You can
actually double-click on that.
If you double-click
on this I-beam,
it says, yes, I'm pinning this
113 points from the edge. And
you can go up here and
try to pick Standard Value.
But that's grayed out,
so we're gonna use 0.
So you almost want either
Standard Value, if available,
or 0. So in this case,
0 means 0 points from this
layout guide edge, okay? And
same thing with this one down
here, I'm gonna double-click.
By the way, we can also
see these things, okay?
If we select this, we can go
over to the size inspector.
You can see all these things
down at the bottom here,
okay, all these connections
to the edges, right?
See this one's 301. So
I'm gonna double-click on this
I-beam, and here, standard
value is available. So I'm
gonna pick the standard value,
okay? And it puts it there.
Now so they tied it to the
bottom and stretched this out.
Now it didn't quite stretch
out the way we wanted here,
right? So some of these,
rows in the inside,
we didn't get the right
attributes on.
So let's go back and check
them all. We got fill equally,
horizontally, and all of them,
yeah? We do, right?
And how about this? Here I'm
gonna use the Ctrl+Click.
We'll pick this stack view.
See this one, okay,
this is this inner one, wants
to also be filled equally,
right? We want all these rows,
not including this top guy,
but all these inner interior
rows to be the same.
So I'm gonna go fill
equally here to fix that,
okay? So now I have this
thing that can stretch out,
because it's got these
stacks that have rules about
how to fill. And then I've
hooked them to the edges, so
that now when I switch
orientations, it adjusts,
even if I go to a smaller
device, okay? Or
a large device.
Now one thing that's
interesting about the very
smallest device, an iPhone 4,
is that in this orientation,
it can't fit everything. You
see that? The display is just,
it can't fit it. So this is
why it's great to be able to
see this in Interface Builder,
cuz we can go back here and
pick a smaller font, for
example. We can even,
you know, have our font be
variable, but there's no way
to have the font automatically
squinched down, unfortunately.
There's no autoshrink for
buttons like there is for
labels. So sorry about that.
But we would pick a smaller
font that would work upon all
of our platforms maybe, okay?
All right, so we have this.
And, of course, now if we run
it in the simulator, we can
rotate it in the simulator as
well and see it working there.
And if we had a device, we
could run it on our device and
do it there. So here we go.
Here's our iPhone 7.
7 times 9 equals.
It's still working.
Square root, that's good.
And when we rotate,
by the way, I'm gonna
rotate using Command key.
Okay, Command left and right
arrows, you'll see it down in
the lower left corner here,
but Command Rotate.
See that? Okay, so you can
see we had to do very little
to make this thing adapt. And
this is a fairly simple UI,
a lot of rectangles.
More complicated UI,
we'd do a little bit more. And
in about week five, four or
five, I'll go into detail
about how we build these, even
for complicated UIs how we
build these rotatable things,
etc. Okay, so that's it.
Your homework
is basically to reproduce
what I did in these first two
lectures and
then add a couple of things.
Add a little label up there,
add some buttons, change some
colors, that kind of business,
pretty straightforward.
Make it work with
floating point inputs and
that's due next Wednesday. I'm
here if you have questions,
and I'll see you then.
>> For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.