[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
this is Developing
Applications for iOS,
winter of 2017. This is the
only lecture in this quarter
where I'm not going to do
a demo, so this is all slides,
and that's because I'm
pretty much going to try and
get you fully up to speed on
Swift. Everything that I'm
going to talk about today is
covered either in your reading
assignment one, which was due
today, so hopefully you're
done with that, or it's in
reading assignment two,
which is going out today and
is due next Wednesday. So,
why am I even covering this?
Because I know that reading
through that reading
assignment can be a big slog
through a lot of information,
and I want you to understand
the things in there that
are really important. As I go
through the slides today,
if you see something and
I explain it and you're like,
my gosh I didn't get that,
just make a note about
whatever the topic is that I'm
talking about and
then you can go back and
read about it again in your
reading assignment to try and
understand it. If you
still don't understand it,
you can of course ask
on the class forums.
You can think of this as kind
of the highlights of the fist
two reading assignments. Some
of these are also highlights
of the first two lectures
I did in the demos,
so there's a little bit
of that in there to.
But, this is really kind of
the important stuff in Swift,
that I can teach
you at this point.
There's more important stuff
in Swift to come, okay,
but I'll teaching it kinda as
we go in the next two weeks.
Okay, so lot of Swift topics,
let's start with the first
one, probably everybody's
favorite topic when
they first learn Swift,
which is optional. Optional
is interesting in Swift,
because not a lot of other
languages have optional, so
I'm sure, in fact I've heard,
that some of you are like,
"Hmm, I'm not sure I really
understand that optional
thing". And that's probably
okay, but by the end of next
week you should feel very
confident with Optionals,
because you're gonna see that
they are absolutely everywhere
in iOS. Now, I mentioned
this in the lecture but
I wanted to show it
to you from a code,
kind of a code point of view,
which is that optional
is nothing more than an enum,
it is fact just an enum,
this is the enum that is an
optional. It's a generic type,
kind of like array, how with
array when you say the type,
you say the type of the thing
you're putting in the array.
You should all be familiar to
that, with that from Java for
example, same thing in Swift.
So, with optional
it is the same way,
you put this type and the type
that's associated there, or
not that's associated, but
the type of the generic type
that we're talking about,
that "T" in an optional,
is just the type that's going
to be the associated value.
When you look at
this enum Optional,
it only has two cases: "none"
which is "not set," and
"some" which is "set". When
it's in the some case, look:
"(T)", you know what that is
from the calculator demo,
that's an associated value,
just like when we had
operation in calculator it had
associated values, like unary
operation had an associative
value of a function, and
constant had an associated
value of the constant's value.
Same thing here, with
optional, in the "some" case,
the "set" case, it just has
an associated value, and
it's whatever type
the option was, so
if this is an optional string,
then it would be a string.
Now what makes optional like,
" I don't really get optional,
what is it?", it's because of
all those question marks and
exclamation points. But,
exclamation points,
are just sugar,
syntactic sugar, to make your
code look a little simpler and
straight forward, because it's
so common to use them. So,
I'm going to map this
enum to that sugar.
Let's take a look, here's
the first one: If I say let x:
String?=nil, that's
exactly the same as
saying let x =
Optional.none,
just like by saying array,
I'd say
Array that would mean
I want an array of String,
here when I say Optional
, that means I want
an Optional String. And
I'm picking the none case, and
in just the same way, if I
say let x = Optional=
hello, I'm just saying x
= Optional.some
with associated value hello.
Everyone got that? That's all
that's happening there with
the question mark thing.
And then here is the unwrap.
When we do that exclamation
point all we're doing is doing
the switch to get things out
of an optional, so we're
switching on the optional,
and it's in the "Some" case,
then we're going to grab that
associated value just like we
did in the calculator, and
we say "let function" or "let
value" to grab the associated
value, we're saying
"let value" here and
it's grabbing that value
that's associated with it.
If it's in case none,
where it's not set,
then it raises an exception
and crashes your program,
we haven't talked about how to
do that, it's quite easy, but
that's what happens here,
that's all exclamation point
is, it's basically a switch.
And then finally,
If we do the "if let",
"if let" is also
just a switch, but
in the none case of an if let,
we don't raise an exception,
we just break, break out of
the switch, do nothing. Okay,
does that help you a little
bit understand what optional
is? Optional is a type, it's
an enum, it's just like any
other type, it just has this
interesting behavior, and
it's got all
the question marks and
exclamation points to make
all the code look a little
simpler. Now, there's even
other stuff about optionals
that are interesting.
Optionals can be chained.
Now what does this mean? Well,
this is best shown by example.
So, let's say I have
a Optional UILabel like my
display in the calculator and
it's got the text, that's also
an optional, Optional String,
we all know that. And
let's say we want to get the
hashValue which is just a var
on string, which hashes the
string, gives you some integer
for it, I want to get that
hashValue of what's in
the display. So then I would
probably do some code that
looks like this, this is
probably similar code to what
we have in our calculator
where I've got my display,
that's my IBOutlet probably
that display UILabel?, and
I'm going go do "if let" here,
because I don't want to crash
so I don't want to do
exclamation points,
I'm going to do "if let",
so I'm going to say "if let
some temporary value equals
to the display" (now temp1 is
the UILabel), and then I say,
"if let temp2 = temp1.text",
I'm sending text
to the UILabel and
now I'm getting back a String,
not an Optional String, but
a String, because I did "if
let", then I can finally say,
then "let x = temp2",
which is the String,
the hashValue. Okay, this is a
lot of code to have to type to
just get that dang hashValue,
out of that UILabel's text.
With optional chaining, this
same code looks like this,
the first line of
those two lines.
"If let x =
display?.text?.hashValue,
then do something with x".
In that case of course, x will
be a non-optional, because
I'm doing if let on it.
If I take the "if" off, and
just do "let x =" all that,
then x will be an optional
Int. Now, how is this working?
What's happening is that every
time that you have one of
those question marks after
an Optional, it's saying,
if this is in the set case,
then grab it and keep on
going, send the next thing.
If it's in the nil case, then
just return nil for this whole
expression, this entire line,
boom, it's just gonna return
nil. If I'm if letting it,
then obviously the code
won't get executed.
You can do as many of these
as you want in a row, and
we do this all the time, this
optional chaining is going to
be all over your code, and
it makes perfect sense because
again, we're using this
question mark and exclamation
point. Here we happen to use
the question mark when we're
accessing it versus when we're
declaring it. That's what it
means to use a question mark
when you're accessing it,
it means go get it,
and if it's not set,
then just return nil from
this whole expression,
it will just bail out
of the whole thing,
It will never even execute
hash value because we'll never
get down to that end of it, if
any of these things are nil.
Another cool optional things
we can do is optional
defaulting. So what if we had
wanted to put a string in our
UI label like in our display,
but we know that if that
string is nil, we don't want
to put nil in there because
what'll happen to our label
if we put nil in as the text?
It'll collapse down, right,
probably most of you saw that.
You have to put
something in there,
at least a space. So let's
say that I want to do that,
I want to put space in there
if it's nil. This is the code
that it would look like here:
I'd have my string, I would
say if the string is not nil,
then put it in the display,
otherwise, if it is nil,
put space in there. This looks
a lot cleaner with optional
defaulting, which looks like
this, display.text = s That
means if s is nil, use
this other thing. It's like
the default in case s is nil.
We will use this all the time
as well. Everybody got that?
Just optional defaulting.
Alright, so I bring those out
of the optional world
just to highlight them,
because there's a lot in
the reading that you're doing
about optional, but these
are kind of the highlights.
There are a couple more things
actually I'll show you later,
but basically that's it for
optionals. Alright, tuples.
So I had you skip tuples in
reading assignment one, but
you'll be reading about them
in reading assignment two.
What is a tuple?
A tuple is super simple, it's
just a grouping of values,
and you can use it anywhere
you're using a type. What does
a tuple look like? It looks
like this. This var here,
this constant, actually x, I'm
setting its type to be a tuple
with a string and int and
a w, that's its type. A tuple
can have any number of things
in there, but realistically,
we probably only have three or
four, sometime only two, but
it can have any number. I can
set x equal to parentheses,
those three, any value of
those three types. So here,
I've set it to hello,
5, and 0.85.
Now I can get the values out
into individual variables by
saying let parentheses three
different variable names equal
x. And now it will pull out
the three different values
into the three separate
variables, word, number, and
value. So it's kind of
mirror image there,
you can kinda go either,
either direction,
putting things in or out. We
actually, believe it or not,
don't do it that way
most of the time,
because it is also possible to
name the elements of a tuple.
So here, I define x, same
thing, string int double, but
look, I've named each of them,
I called the string part w,
I called the int part i, and
I called the double part v for
some reason. Now, I still set
it equal in exactly the same
way, no difference there. But
now I don't need to pull it
out into separate variables.
I can just say x.w and get the
w, the first component of it.
You see that? This is how
we do tuples, with names.
I strongly recommend
you almost always use
names with tuples. It's just
a little easier to read,
clearer to say what your
intent is as a programmer.
Because those names
of the parts of the tuple can
have good variable names.
You're gonna see in your
programming assignment number
2, I'm gonna have you write a
function that returns a tuple,
and it's going to specify the
names of the parts. Now even
if you name them, like we
have x with the named ones,
you can still do that thing
where you just say, let (word,
num, val) equal x, and
it'll still pull it out into
individual ones, so naming
them doesn't stop you from
pulling them out by individual
variable, if you want.
Also, in tuples, you can
always put underbar for
any of the names, like here I
could say let word_ val or
let word,_, val equal x, and
then I would get word and
val into individual variables,
and I would just ignore that
middle one. Underbar in Swift
always kinda means ignore
that, I'm not interested
in that particular thing.
We've already seen this with
function parameters when we
want to ignore the external
name of a function parameter.
Alright, so using tuples
that return values,
like I said, you're gonna
see this in the homework.
Nothing special here. It's
a type like any other type, so
it can be the return type of a
function. So, this is how you
can have a function that
returns multiple values.
In some languages, it's
very difficult to do this.
You have to create a structure
or something to return.
However, it's very, very,
very easy in Swift.
You literally just do this.
And
when you get the value that
comes back from that function,
you just access the elements
by name. Notice that when I
returned it in my code there
in getSize, I didn't have to
give the names; I
could if I wanted to,
I could have said return
weight:150, height:, but
I decided, eh, I'm just gonna
return the values. Okay,
another thing: range,
range is an important little
struct in Swift: all that it
represents is two end points.
So a range is useful for, for
example, a selection of text,
where the selection starts and
where the selection ends.
It's also good for a sub-slice
of an array. If you've got
array of 100 elements,
you might want the 15th to
the 40th one, so you could
specify that range, 15 to 40.
So range is this really simple
little struct, which kind of
looks like this. I say kind
of, because it's a little more
complicated than this, but
it basically looks like this.
It's a generic type like array
because of course, you can
have a range of ints. You
could have a range of floats.
You could have a range of
strings even. Okay, so
that T right there could
be float, float, int,
string. T is restricted
a little bit, and I haven't
really talked about how you
restrict a generic type.
But that T is restricted,
and it has to be what's called
comparable. That's because
range needs to make sure that
the start index is less than
the end index. That's part of
what a range is defined to be.
So that T has to be something
that can be compared
to see if the start index
is less than the end index,
minor thing there. So, for
example, a range of int
would be great for specifying
a range in an array,
cuz an array is indexed by
integers, right, starting at 0
and going up to the number
of things in the array.
Now there are other more
powerful, more capable ranges,
like CountableRange.
A CountableRange is
just like a range, except for
that you can count through
intermediate values between
the start and the end.
Okay, it's like a range of
ints. A CountableRange means
the begin point and
end point and one point each.
Now as you stride through that
range, it depends on what
the type is. Striding through
a range of ints is different
then striding through a range
of floats, or striding through
a range of strings. There's
a little difference there, and
we'll talk about
that in a minute.
There's a special syntax for
doing range, which is "dot dot
less-than" or "dot dot dot".
Dot Dot Less-than means that
you put the start index and
the end index on either side
of the dot dot less than.
And that means go from the
start index to the end index,
but don't include the end
index, not inclusive of it,
and the dot dot dot
includes both ends. So for
example, in an array, let's
have an array of four strings,
a, b, c, d, and let's say
that I want to get the c and
the d out of there,
I can say array sub, ( just
like how I can say array sub 5
or array sub 3 is the fourth
index of the array),
I can also specify a range and
get a sub array, a slice of
the array, it's called. So
I can say 2...3, which
means index 2 in the array,
which is c because a is index
0, b is index 1, c is index 2,
dot dot dot index 3, which is
the d inclusive, cuz it's dot
dot dot. And then the less
than 1 would be exclusive,
so that's why the d wouldn't
be included in that one. So
see how I'm using a range to
get a sub slice of an array,
that's kind of cool.
By the way,
if you say give me
the array from 6...8,
that's going to crash at run
time with an array index out
of bounds because this array
only has four elements. So
just because I'm accessing
this subscripting with a range
instead of with a number,
it still has to be in bounds.
And then if I say
array[4...1],
that also will crash at run
time, because the range
is going to look at that and
say I can't create a range
where the start value is
greater than the end value,
can't be a backwards range,
that's why that type like
int has to be comparable, of
course you can compare ints.
One thing very important
to understand: a string,
a subrange of a string
is not a range of ints.
You might think it is,
right, I've got this string,
100 characters, you might
think strings sub 15 to 40
would be the 15th
character to the 40th. And
it's not: a string subrange
is a range of string.index,
which is a different
little data type, and
I'm going to talk all about
that in a few slides.
But I just want to
make it really clear,
that it is possible to say
string subrange start..<end,
but start and end are not
ints, they're string.indexes,
and we'll see how that works.
If the type
of the range that you create
with dot dot less than or
dot dot dot, if that type
is an int, (actually,
if it's strideable by int,
they can be strided by int so
it's not gonna be float, but
I'm not really prepared to
talk to you about strideable),
but if the range has
ints on either end, so
it's a range from 2 to 7, for
example, then it automatically
creates that countable range,
that more capable range.
That range then becomes
what's called a sequence, And
sequences can be iterated
through or enumerated, and
the way you do that is with
"for in", so Swift's for
statement, this is the only
one there is. It's called
"for in" and all it ever means
is, I want to go and enumerate
all the values of a sequence.
I'm going to talk about what
things that can be sequenced.
Countable range is 1,
because if an int
goes from 0 to 7, and
it's a countable range, then
it can go 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7. Arrays are sequences,
sequences of their elements.
So you can "for in" through an
array. Dictionaries are also,
and we'll see that a little
later. So here's how you do
a normal C-like for loop,
for (i = 0; i < 20; i++).
You cannot do that in Swift,
that syntax simply doesn't
exist. Instead you would say
for i in the range 0..<20,
because notice I said it's
less than 20, not less than or
equal to 20, so 0..<20 means
go through that. And so
that little block of code is
going to be executed once for
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, all the way
up to number 19, so
that's same thing as
what you see there.
Now what about floats?
Floats are a little weird.
What if I wanted to do for{i
= 0.5; i <= 15.25; i += 0.}.
Whoa, how am I gonna do that?
I can't, for
example, say for
i in 0.5...15.25.
How does it know to go by 0.3?
And the answer is, it doesn't.
In fact, a range like that,
0.5...15.25 is not a countable
range, it's just range. It
only knows the start and end,
it knows nothing about
what's in between, so
it cannot be a sequence,
it can't be for in over. But
luckily, there's this great
global function called stride.
Stride takes a from and
a to, or a through,
(depending whether you wanna
go through to the end,
or just to to and
not including it), and
a by, which is,
what it's going to step by.
So here, I say stride
from 0.5 through 15.25,
because I want less than or
equal to, by 0.3, and
that's gonna create a new
object, it's a CountableRange.
Now it's a special
CountableRange, it knows
how to count from 0.25 to
15.25 by that 0.3 step. You
don't need to worry about how
it implements it, Stride just
creates you a CountableRange.
Actually this will be called
a ClosedCountableRange because
it counts through to the end,
so it's a dot dot dot kind
of range of a dot dot
less than kind of range. So
I have a CountableRange, and
it's a sequence, so I can for
in it, so I say for i in.
Stride, I'd probably say for
f in, or even better than f or
i. A lot of times, by the way,
on my slides, I'm gonna use
variables like i or x or d
because I want it to fit on my
slide, I don't want it to be
wrapping. It's hard for you to
read the slide if the code's
always wrapping around, so
just because you see me using
i and d and f doesn't mean
that's license to have those
kind of terrible names for
your variables. You need to
have meaningful names. So
that's how for in works here,
because stride is gonna
return a CountableRange,
ClosedCountableRange in
this case. So
that's how you do your
standard for loops from C.
Alright, let's talk about
the data structures in Swift.
You've already learned about
three of the four of them,
which are classes, structures,
and enums. In our lecture,
we already did all
three of those things.
We had a class, which is our
view controller subclass.
We had a struct,
which is our calculator brain.
And we had enum,
which was our operation.
The fourth one is protocols,
and
I'm not gonna talk about
that until next week or
even the week after. Protocols
are super, duper important,
I don't want to make it sound
like they're not important,
But they're new to a lot of
you, and so I'm gonna try and
ease you in with these ones
that are more familiar,
although different in Swift
probably than what you're used
to, they're still
more familiar to you.
Let's just review quickly
these three structs and what's
the same and different about
them. So what's the same?
They're declared very,
very similar: they have
different key word, but
they're almost
exactly the same.
The only difference really is
a class can specify a super
class, otherwise they're
declared exactly the same.
They can all have properties
and functions, So,
they're all very similar in
that way. The only thing here
is that there cannot be any
stored properties in an enum.
Enum keeps any data it has in
associated values, so it can't
have any stored properties,
but it can have computed
properties and they certainly
all can have functions.
Another thing that's very
similar is they can all
have initializers except
enums. Enums don't need
an initializer cuz you just
say the case you want, but
structs and classes have
initializers. Okay, so
that's the same.
Now what are the differences?
Well of course, inheritance is
a big difference for classes.
Classes have inheritance.
Structs and enums do not. But
the most important difference,
which I mentioned last time,
is that structs and
enums are value types, and
classes are reference types.
So let's go into that and talk
about it just a little more.
It's so important, I'm gonna
talk about it again. A value
type, what does that mean?
It means that it's copied when
you pass it as an argument
It's copied, even if you just
assign it to another variable,
to a function.
it gets copied. If you assign
it to a let, it's immutable,
that's very important to
understand. If you assigned
a value type to a let,
using let x equal that thing,
you just made it immutable, No
matter how complicated it is.
If it's an array or
dictionary,
you can't add any elements.
If it's a calculatorBrain,
it means you can't call any
of its mutable functions, So
you can't do perform operation
on it. Now in assignment two,
I'm gonna have you add a
method to the calculator brain
that is gonna let you use
the calculator brain when it's
immutable, which is kinda
cool. You still wouldn't be
able to perform operation but
you can be able to something
very important, immutably. Now
because of this, this kind of
copyright-on-write behavior
of value types, you must,
of course, mark all the
functions that are going to
modify it as mutating. And
that's how the Swift knows,
"Oops, I've gotta make a copy
of this, an actual real copy,
if someone writes to it". Now
a reference class is pretty
different in that it gets
stored in the heap somewhere
with a pointer to it, and
when you pass it around to
a function or to assign it to
another variable or something
like that, you're just passing
a pointer around to it.
Now, by the way, when you say,
let x equal a reference type,
you can still send it
messages that will mutate it.
All you're saying is
the pointer can't change, but
what it points to can
always be changed.
Now reference types
are what you're used to.
Most languages that have
object-oriented reference
types. Reference types
are a little bit Wild West- I
don't have time to teach you
this, I hope you'll get to see
this sometime in your
career at Stanford, but
there is a different way of
thinking about programming
than you're used to: it's
called functional programming.
How many people have
heard the phrase,
functional programming?
So about half of you. The idea
of functional programming is:
you don't want this Wild West
where you've got these objects
with multiple people pointing
at them, any of whom could
modify it at any time.
That leaves you open to a lot
of difficulty in verifying
the correctness
of your program.
Whereas if you have a lot of
objects that are immutable,
you know they can't change,
and their APIs are basically
like mathematical functions
where data goes in and
predictable data comes out,
because there's
not all this side-effecting,
data-effecting other objects
that someone else is
pointing to in all this.
It's this really
well-contained little thing.
Now iOS was not developed with
functional programming in mind
at all. But
the people who invented Swift,
they were thinking about
functional programming, So
you can kind of mix
a lot of the elements of
functional programming
into your application,
if you're building an iOS
application. Now that's a new
frontier in iOS, because for
however long, 20 years,
really, or 30 years, really,
if you consider all the way
back to the invention of the
technology that led to iOS,
people have been
programming with basically
reference types only, for
their object-orienting.
But when you do this
programming with structs and
enums, and especially when you
throw in protocols, (which I
told you I was gonna tell you
that are very important, but
I cannot explain to you yet,
and generics),
when you start throwing those
things all in there, you can
really do a good job of doing
real functional programming.
All of the Swift foundation
is really designed with a lot
of functional programming in
mind. If you ever really wanna
kind of see a good example of
how to apply this immutability
and generics, and protocols
and all that stuff to build
an architecture,
chase down all the things that
are going on in the foundation
library: string and range and
all these things. Remember,
that I said things like
the range is a sequence, or
this thing is comparable,
remember how I said things
like that? Okay, well,
how do you express that?
You use protocols,
with these immutable types,
that can be immutable and
use generics.
So I can't explain all that,
I've already spent too much
time on it than I have to even
talk about it in the lecture
today, but just so
you know, there is a huge
advantage of programming in
a different way; it requires
a real mindset change.
So hopefully, you'll take
a class where maybe the whole
class is functional
programming,
and really you'll
get a feel for it.
Swift does a good job
of supporting for
the fundamentals you need
to do that. That's kind
of the long-winded answer to
which do you choose. If you're
doing more of a functional
approach, even if you're doing
a reference-based approach
like what you're used to, try
to lean towards immutability,
try to ask yourself,
can this thing work and
be immutable? Is there some
functionality in my program
that I could share by creating
a generic, for example.
At least those leanings
might help you build the apps
that are more testable,
because it's a lot easier
to write a test for
something that's like
a mathematical function where
you know the data out is
supposed to be the same for
the data in, than it is for
something where there's
a lot of data that you have to
set everything up. Set this,
set this and this and this,
and now call the method,
that's a lot more difficult
to write test cases for, etc.
So that's value and reference.
Let's talk a little bit about
the syntax of methods.
I'm gonna go fast on this.
Hopefully, you all
understand this.
All parameter names have
external names and internal
names. The internal name is
used inside the definition, or
the inside the implementation
of the function.
So here I have these two
functions, foo and bar. Bar
calls foo. So you can see that
inside foo's implementation,
it is using the first and
the second, whereas bar,
when bar calls foo,
it uses external first and
external second, as the names
of the items. And you know
that you can put an under
bar to make it so there's no
external name. We only do
that 99.99% of the time with
the first item. Why do we do
it? Because sometimes the name
of the method, and/or the type
of that first argument, is
enough to make it clear what
that thing is supposed to be,
so we don't need to
put an external name.
It's kinda clear.
All the other parameters,
we don't have the advantage of
having the name of the method
there. So that's why we
almost never put underbar for
the later ones. By the way,
if you only put one
parameter name, then that's
both the external name and
the internal name, and
that's not that uncommon,
you'll do that occasionally.
All right, so you know all
that. When it comes to doing
overriding, subclassing, in
reference types and classes,
when you override, you have to
explicitly let Swift know that
you know you're doing that.
And you do that by putting
the override keyword.
So if you override a method
from your superclass you have
to say override func whatever.
You can mark a method or
even a whole class final, and
that means that it cannot be
overridden, subclasses will
not be allowed to override it.
Most languages have that.
Now on the topic of methods.
You've seen, actually you've
seen both, but mostly seen and
understood instance methods.
These are methods,
or vars, that are being sent
to an instance of the class
struct or enum.
In other words, one of them.
Like I create one of them:
I create a double of 15.5,
I have one, and
I can send it messages.
But types, like the type
double, the type strength,
the type calculator brain,
they can also have methods and
vars. Computed vars,
no storage, but computed vars.
All you do to add a method or
a var to a type is
you put static in front
of the declaration.
So "static func whatever"
means this is a function on
the type, not on instances of
the type, on the type itself.
For example,
let's think about double here.
Double actually has quite a
few static or type methods and
vars. You access them by
sending the message to
Double to the actual word,
capital D-O-U-B-L-E. You
don't send it to an instance,
you send it to that word. And
you've already seen at least
one of these, which was pi.
Remember we said Double.pi and
we got the value of pi?
Pi is a var, a computed var,
on the class or
struct actually, double, but
it also has other methods,
like abs.
Abs takes a double value and
returns the absolute value
of it. That is on the type.
You say Double.abs, Double.pi.
As opposed to, for example,
if I have a double
like x is equal 23.85.
So x is now a double.
I can't say x Double.pi cause
x is an instance of a double.
You see the difference?
We see saying x.pi,
trying to send pi
to an instance versus
sending pi to a type double.
So what do we use these
type methods for?
Well, we can't access any
instance variables because
we're not sending
them to an instance.
We mostly use them for utility
methods, things like that.
Constants like pi is a good
example. Things that
kind of are functions that are
associated with this type but
don't belong to
a particular instance or
wouldn't really operate on
an instance. Now for example,
you might have
an instance method or
even an instance var called
abs, A-B-S, with no arguments,
That you would send to
an instance, and it would take
the absolute value of
the thing you sent it to. But
of course the type one has
to have an argument because
you're sending it
to the type double,
so there's no double involved.
There's no instance of a
double involved. Everybody got
that? Alright: properties.
You know all about properties.
We saw computed properties
like display value in
our calculator. There's
actually some really cool
features on properties. One of
the most interesting ones is
property observers.
What is a property observer?
A property observer is
a little piece of code that
will get executed when
your property changes.
Anytime your property changes
just a little piece of code
can get executed.
Now you can actually find out
just before your
property changes. Or
you can find out just after
your property changes.
Or both. And the way you
do this, and this works for
your stored properties, like
userIs InTheMiddleOfTyping:
we could put a property
observer on there, and
execute some code every time
we change that. It also works
for inherited properties,
so if you inherit something
from your superclass, you can
put these properties in and
notice that it changed. By the
way, if you have a property
which is a value type,
(a struct or
something, like an array or
an dictionary), this property
observer stuff will happen
if that thing gets changed,
if it gets mutated. So if you
add something to the array,
boom, the Property Observer
will kick in and say,
"that changed". How do
these Property Observers
work? They look a lot like
a computed property. Remember
that the computed property
displayValue had get and
then we had some code,
And then we had set and
we had some code?
This is similar except for
get and set it's will set,
or did set.
By the way, you probably would
never (I don't even know if
you can) use this in
a computed property because
you've got the set
clause there so
you can just put
it right in set.
You don't need to find out
when it's set because you set
it. But for stored properties
and inherited properties,
that make sense, so
you have willSet.
Now, willSet, first of all,
you put it all in a curly
brace after the property
just like if you were doing
a computed property but, this
is not a computed property,
just adding a curly brace
doesn't make it a computed
property, you have to put
get or set in there, but,
if I put willSet, then,
inside that code,
there's a special variable
just like there in the set
case of computer property,
called newValue, and
that is the value that that
thing is going to be set to.
It's not set yet.
Some property,
see some stored property
up there? It has not yet
been set to newValue but it's
going to be. And then didSet,
that code occurs after some
property has been set and
the special variable
in there is oldValue.
That's the value it used to
have before it got set. So
you can compare if
they've changed, for
example. So
where do we use these things?
Probably the number one place
that we use them is in our
Controller in view.
Let's say I'm a button and
my background color changes.
I inherit my background color
from my super class, UI view.
Up the chain of super classes.
Every time the background
color changes,
the button wants to
redraw itself so
it will have var background
color is a UI color,
open curly brace,
didSet open curly brace
draw myself closed curly
brace. Question? Okay,
so the question is, if someone
changes some stored property
there, am I responsible for
doing something about that
in willSet or didSet? Do I
have to actually set it? And
the answer is no. Okay, that's
being set somewhere else.
You're just getting a chance
to run some other code that
you wanna run just before and
just after it happens.
But you're not responsible for
setting the actual value.
That's done for you.
That's why you get to
see the old value and the new
value in the two of them.
So we'll see this next week
when we start drawing on
screen, where we're gonna be
watching properties change so
we can cause ourselves to
redraw. Next, lazy properties.
Lazy initialization is
a really powerful tool.
It's gonna get you out of
a lot of binds in this class.
What does it mean?
A lazy var, a var
that you say lazy in front of,
whatever it's set equal to,
that equals doesn't actually
happen until someone accesses
that var. Until someone asks
for the value of that var,
it doesn't actually do
the initialization there.
It doesn't do that
equal something.
So it's lazy. It's waiting.
Now why do you wanna be lazy?
Well, one obvious reason
is like here, lazy var
brain equals calculator
brain, what if calculator
brain was really expensive to
create. What if it opened
a network connection because
we're going to share the
calculation with the internet
or something,
you know what I mean,
do something that
is expensive.
Well, you wouldn't
want to do it,
unless someone actually
tried to access the brain,
called set up operand on it or
something. Then you would
want to actually do
the work to create it.
Okay so one reason to be lazy,
it's not that important of
a reason it turns out, but
one is to delay
expensive operations. But
what's another reason to
do it? Well, in Swift,
all vars have to be
initialized. Remember that?
Remember we added
userIsInTheMiddleOfTyping.
And we didn't say, equals
false. And we got an error.
It said we had no init,
because we hadn't initialized
that. Not only did they all
have to be initialized, but
they all had to be initialized
before you could even send
a message to that class,
even internally. So
you can't invoke any of your
own methods until you fully
initialize yourself. What if
one of the things you want to
initialize needs to call
a method on yourself? It's
impossible. Because if you
need to initialize something
to be allowed to send messages
to yourself and you need
to send a message to yourself
to initialize something,
it's a deadlock. You can't do
it. Okay, well lazy let's you
do it. Because you can say for
example, the last one there;
lazy my property equals some
method on myself. This is not
going to be executed until
someone says my property and
no one's allowed to access
my property until I'm fully
initialized. So
by definition there's no way
that that is gonna try to get
initialized until I'm already
fully initialized. And yet
this lazy thing counts as this
thing having been initialized.
So this is the big loophole.
Lazy var myProperty counts
as having been initialized
even though it really hasn't
yet. Because it's waiting for
something to actually access
myProperty. But it counts for
the purposes of that rule, so
now someone comes along later
and accesses it, now we
can call this method. So
do you see how deferring
the calling of this method in
order to initialize this gets
us around that requirement
that everything
be initialized?
It's really tricky.
And then the middle one there,
someProperty, that's super
tricky. Because you can
actually have a closure,
(remember what a closure is,
right from calculator brain,
it's just a function,
in line function), you can
actually have a closure
to initialize your thing
lazily. All you do is you
put the closure, open curly
brace, close curly brace.
It obviously has to return
something of the type
of that bar. And then just put
the little open parenthesis,
close parenthesis at the end.
When we open parenthesis and
close parenthesis at
the end of the closure,
that means execute this
closure right now. But
it's not gonna execute right
now, it's gonna act lazy so
it's gonna happen later. And
that means that that closure
inside could reference self.
Because self will be fully
initialized by the time
this closure gets executed,
since it's lazily executed. So
lazy will get you out of some
of these tricky wickets,
because when you see me
talk about initialization,
you're gonna be like, "I
don't want to do that, ever".
You're going to try and
avoid it, and
this is a good way to
avoid it. So yeah,
it still satisfies all those
things. Alright, on to Array.
Everybody knows what an array
is. Everyone knows what
a generic array is. You just,
when you declare the array,
you have to say what
type of things are gonna
be in the array. There's
a different syntax though,
which I didn't introduce when
I did dictionary in the demo.
But you can declare an array,
those two yellow things
up there are exactly
the same thing. So,
open square bracket,
string close square bracket
is exactly the same as saying
array angle bracket string.
It's just kind of a special
way to declare an array and
it actually seems to be
the preferred way. I actually
prefer the other way because
it's a little clearer to you
that are learning that this is
an array, because it says
the word array and string.
But open square bracket,
close square bracket,
we know that's going to
be index into an array so
it looks kind of array-ish but
just get used to it. [String]
means an array of string.
It's the declaration of
the S and the name of that
type array of string. So if I
had a string right here like
this giraffe, cow, doggie, and
bird. Four animals in here,
four strings and I said
animals dot append ostrich,
well append appends something
onto the array, now the thing
you are appending has to
be the same type obviously
as the type of everything in
the array, however the type
was declared. Notice that
animals is in inferred.
By Swift, to be an array of
string. Because Swift sees
that you sent it to
an array of things and
it looked at all the things
and they were all strings.
So it said, the animals must
be an array of string. Now,
this line of code
animals.append("Ostrich").
That's very bad.
Can anyone tell me why
that's not gonna work?
Yeah?
>> That's exactly right.
We define this animal's
variable with let, so
it's immutable. So when we
say append an ostrich onto
an immutable thing, it's
going to crash my program.
But actually, it won't
even crash my program.
It won't even compile.
Like, Swift compiler's
just gonna say, no way,
you can't do append of
something or other.
So that's a good one
over there, you got that.
How about this one? I'll
give you a second chance for
everyone.
Why is this one no good? Okay,
I'm trying to get animal[4]
over there, why? Nobody?
This one's easier. Array
index, yes! Array index is
out of bounds because arrays
are indexed starting at zero.
Okay, so giraffe, cow, doggie,
bird that's zero, one, two and
three. So if I say, give
me array number four, bam,
crashed my program array
index out of bounds.
Let's talk about the fact
that array is a sequence.
Array is actually a collection
and collections are sequences.
And a sequence means I can do
for in on it. So if I say for
animal in animals, my little
for loop will get executed
four times, once with animal
being giraffe, next one with
animal being cow, next one
with animal being doggie,
next one animal being bird.
Okay, so that's a really cool
feature. Remember this is the
only four there is in swift.
For in, that's the only for
there is, nothing else.
So array in a lot of
classes instructs
in iOS have some
interesting methods
that have arguments that are
closures. So I teach closures
to you right at the beginning
of the of the quarter.
And why do I do that? Because
closures are an important
thing to understand if you
want to really use iOS API
well. So let's take at this
(just so we can learn a little
bit about how closures
can make our API great,
especially again if you're
doing functional programming,
closures can be really good),
but why are closures so great?
So let's look at this so,
this first function right here
called filter is
an array method.
Nothing special about it,
it's just funk and array.
It has one argument, which
is called includeElement.
And that argument is a
function. It's a function that
takes one argument which is of
the same type of the things in
the arrays, cuz it's a t. So I
have an array angle bracket t.
It's a generic type so this
function is declared in that
generic type so the t means
the same t, the same type. So
if I have an array of strings
this filter expects this
to be a function that takes a
string. As its only argument.
And it returns a Bool,
so that's the argument.
The argument is a function
that takes a string and
returns a Bool or takes a T,
whatever that is, and
returns a Bool.
And then what's the return
value of this filter thing?
It's an array of T, so another
array with the same kind of
elements. So what does filter
do? Filter takes every single
element In the array that
you're sending it to and it
runs that little function. And
if that function returns true,
it includes it in the array it
returns. If it returns
false it doesn't.
It throws it out. So
it's a filter: it's filtering
your array and creating a new
array with all the things you
don't want as defined by this
function that you're
providing as an argument.
With all the things you don't
want thrown out. So for
example here, I have this
var that I'm creating,
bigNumbers, and I'm creating
an array on the fly 2,
47,118,5,9, (see?
I created an array), and look,
I'm sending it a message right
away. Yeah, I didn't have to
put it into another var,
by the way, I could have but,
I just want all be on one line
here. I created this array and
I'm sending it
the message filter and
look what I'm providing for
the argument there.
That include element it has an
underbar, so, you don't have
to actually put the include
element column in there. So,
what am I putting in there?
That's a closure. So
that means, it's a function.
Now, Swift knows that this is
a function that
returns a bool. So
I don't have to put the word
return in there. I can use
dollar zero to be the one and
only argument to the function.
And I'm just going
to check and
see if dollar zero is greater
than 20, in other words,
is this a big number. So I get
back an array which has only
47 and 118 in it, because I've
filtered out all the things
where the value's not greater
than 20. Imagine writing
this line of code without
filter. You're gonna have
to a four loop. You're gonna
have to create another array.
You're gonna have to run
this little function,
call this function,
create a new array and
add, append thing to do it.
It's at least four or
five lines of code. And
here you get it in one line of
code, okay? So you see how
closure there has helped us.
This is also much more
readable cuz you can read this
like this: Let the big
numbers equal this array, but
filter for things there
are greater than 20.
That reads nicely,
so I'm just clear.
It's very easy to understand
what's going on here.
So here's another one. It's
called map. What does map do?
It takes a closure,
or a function. And
it executes that function
in order to transform each
of the elements in the array
you're sending map to,
to a new array.
Now that transformation could
be anything that a function
can do. And you can convert
it to any new type you want.
Although it's one function,
so it
coverts everything to the same
type. So you could use it for
type conversions like I
have here. I've taken 1,
2, 3 and mapped it to the
string versions of 1, 2, 3, so
now I have the new array with
strings in it. String of 1,
string of 2, string of 3.
That's a trivial mapping.
But you can imagine much more
powerful mappings where you
take each element
of the array, and
call some complicated function
on it, and get the result into
a new array. So by creating a
really powerful argument there
instead of String($0),
something more powerful, you
can really have one line of
code that's really expressive.
It can do a lot of things. One
thing about this one: notice
that after the word map,
there's no parentheses,
no open parentheses.
Did you notice that?
You see the difference
between filter and map, okay?
When I called filter,
I said open parentheses,
open curly brace, the
function, curly brace, close
parentheses. Here I just say,
, no parentheses.
And this is what's called the
trailing closure syntax. You
are allowed to have closures
that are the last argument to
a function. The outside of the
parentheses of that function,
if they're trailing, see
they're trailing the call. And
in fact, if there's
only one argument and
it's closure, you don't need
the parentheses at all.
And that's what happened
there with map.
I'm just saying map,
parentheses get rid of them.
Just put the closure there,
trailing. And
that also results in
some pretty cool looking
code right here, you see that?
So you can use that anywhere
that a closure is the last
argument of function.
You can take it outside of the
curly braces. Cuz you already
got the curly braces, and
that's why they do it.
You don't really need the
parentheses around it as well.
So put that at the end.
And put all the rest of the
arguments, if you had them,
inside the parentheses right
before. This last one, I won't
go into the details, but
it's a similar kind of thing.
Reduce: what reduce does is
it takes an entire array and
reduces it to a single value.
So here I'm reducing it by
adding all the numbers in the
array up. So my closure is $0
+ $1, because the argument it
takes is a function that takes
two elements. One of them is
an element from the array and
the other is the answer so
far, and
then it returns the new answer
so far. So it just executes
that function over and
over and over on the arrays.
By the way, notice that I
can say this as sum = [1,
2, 3].reduce(0, +) which is
my starting so far value.
Which I haven't added a name
on, so it starts at 0 and
then I can say plus. The
reason I can say plus right
there at the bottom line,
is because plus
in Swift is not some kinda
weird built-in thing,
it's just a function. It's
a function that happens to be
declared in a way that says,
this is a function, but
it's two arguments it's
going either side of it.
It's called an infix
operator on a function. So
since plus is just a function,
and
I'm taking a function
as an argument,
as long as it's a function
that takes two arguments and
returns one, which is exactly
what plus does, it works
there. We could have done that
in our calculator brain, too.
Remember all that closures
we were doing ($0* $1),
that could've just been *),
($0+$1), that could've just
been +. Cuz + is a function
that takes two doubles and
returns a double. Plus also
know how to plus other types,
ints. And it even knows how
to plus and into a float,
for example, etc.
You can plus strings together.
So that was just a little
aside just to give you
an introduction there. You're
gonna start seeing a lot of
methods that take
functions as arguments.
So I want you to start to
get comfortable with that.
Okay, dictionary. So we
learned a lot about dictionary
in our first lecture.
Dictionary also has this
special declaration syntax,
which is open square bracket
key type colon value type
closed square bracket. So
those two things in
yellow are equivalent.
And the one on the bottom
seems to be the preferred
one these days. So you know
you can create a dictionary.
By the way, I show you
creating dictionaries from
kind of constant values here.
But you can create
a dictionary just by saying,
let d equal dictionary.
Open parenthesis,
close parenthesis.
And if you say var d
equals dictionary, then now
you can start appending items
onto it because you get an
empty dictionary to start. But
here I'm starting my
dictionary with stuff in it.
That probably should say
var pac12teamRankings
because two lines later I say
pac12teamRankings sub Cal
equals 12. Note also that
when I try to get the ranking
of Ohio State, it returns nil.
And we know that when we
use square brackets to get
something out of
the dictionary, it returns
an optional of our value type.
Our value type here is ints,
so it's gonna return
an optional int.
Alright, enumeration.
A dictionary is also
a collection and thus can be
sequenced. So you can do for
in on it. Of course,
a dictionary has keys and
values. So we need a tuple
to do our enumeration for
the tuple key common value
in the dictionary. And
then it'll go through and
key in value will be set.
It's a perfectly
straightforward way
to enumerate or iterate
over a dictionary. Okay,
String. So string, you would
think, is the simplest class
in all of any language.
It's just a string, right?
Well, that turns out not to
be so true. When you think of
a string that represents every
language in the entire world,
all of a sudden it got real
complicated real fast.
Because some languages are
ideographic. Some languages go
right to left instead of left
to right. Some languages have
a lot of diacritic marks and
accents in them. Some don't.
Most languages don't use
the same alphabet as we use.
So string is super
complicated,
this is a very complicated
class. Now string tries
its best and does a pretty
good job of simplifying it for
your use. But the complexity
is still there. Now the most
important complexity about
a string is that representing
a string is not always
one character equals one
internal representation unit.
Now the units, the kind of
thing that's used to represent
strings on the inside,
are Unicodes. I had you skip
that reading in assignment
one, I'm putting it in for
assignment two.
It's really not that critical
that you understand it.
I think it's very interesting,
though, so
you probably want to read it.
But the thing about Unicodes
is it's not one Unicode
equals one character.
In fact, if you have like a
little emoji of a dog barking,
that might be three Unicode
characters. It's only one with
regards to what you perceive
to be a character. Or
even more simply, the example
I have here, the word cafe.
It's got e accent aigu on
the end, right, it's a French
word, e accent aigu.
That could be four Unicodes,
because there is a Unicode for
e accent aigu.
Or it could be five. It could
be the e with another Unicode
character that says put
an accent on that previous
character. So, when you have
this kind of unknown how many
characters it represents,
you need a new abstraction
to represent what we perceive
as humans to be a character.
Even that is difficult to
truly define, when you think
of all the languages in the
world. It's easy in English,
though. So that's really how
we're gonna interact with
strings: to try to think of
them in terms of characters.
But a string itself
is not actually
a collection of characters.
A string is a more powerful
internal structure,
it's got all the Unicodes in
there and all that stuff,
it's not quite that. And
that makes for a little bit of
complication as you're gonna
see. Now, you can't string, is
indexable which means you can
use the open square brackets
just like you can in array to
get one of the characters.
The only rub is what I said
on the other slide that index
is not an int.
So if you have the word hello,
it's not like you can say,
hello[1] equals e.
You can't do it that
way because it might,
if it was cafe
then cafe sub 3.
It's not clear that you want
a character at that point, and
so you've got to make sure you
get the right index in there
because that index behind
the scenes can be quite
complicated. There's this
other struct for it, which is
called a string.index.
So let's say I had a string,
which I'm gonna call s and I'm
gonna put hello into there.
Now, what if I wanted s[0]
now, I can't do s[0],
because we don't index
strings by integers but
let's say I want that.
How do I get it? Well,
I start by calling this var,
again using this var and
string called startIndex,
okay? It gives us
a string.index. It's very
important, we need to get
a hold of a string.index
because the way we're gonna
move around in string is
by taking index we know and
moving forward or backward
by character, by human
understandable character.
Not by Unicodes, because we
don't know how many Unicodes
there are per character but
by character, we're gonna
be moving back and forth.
So we start with
this first one.
And so now I can create a
variable firstChar which is of
this type Character,
that human
understandable character.
That's gonna be equal
s[firstIndex]. So see look,
I've used square brackets
to index into a string, but
I had to use a String.Index
not an Int. This first index
I got by asking the string
"what's your first index"?
Well this is kinda useless
because I have to ask
the string, what's the index
of your first character and
then turn around say okay give
me S of your first character.
So that's not
the interesting thing,
what if I want the next
character. If I
want the next character, I ask
the string what's the index of
the character after your
first character. And
it'll give me a new index,
of its second character and
now I can get that one. Even
that is a little bit like,
my God, you're kidding me,
this is really how I have to
do this? What if I wanted
to go jump ahead though, and
get the fourth, the fifth
character, let's say? Well I
can jump ahead by saying s,
give me the index of,
starting at your first index,
that's four ahead so
jump four ahead,
four characters ahead.
This is all a little
tedious and of course this is
not the actual way that we're
interacting with strings.
We're usually looking for
substrings, okay, or
subranges of characters or
we're trying to find
a character in a string.
By the way, you can use
ranges, so I could say
give me the substring which is
firstIndex...secondIndex and
it would give me he.
A new string which is he, so
you can use ranges there but
they have to be string.index
not ints. So we want
basically something that
is a collection of characters.
A string is not a collection
of characters so you can't do
for in, for example, on it.
You can't even say index(of:).
Index(of:) is this great
thing where you can,
if you have a collection
of things, you can say give
me this index of this thing in
there. You can't even do that
with a string because it's
not a collection. Luckily,
string has a var which will
give you a collection of its
characters. And
not only is it gonna give
you a collection of its
characters that you can for
in over and do index(of:), but
the string indexes you get
from that collection will
match what's in the string. So
you can use this collection of
characters to find things in
there, get the index of
a character, things like
that. And then use the indexes
you find there to go back to
your string and say, okay
now give me a substring. So
characters is the name of this
var on string. So for example,
if I want to iterate over all
the characters one by one,
do a for loop over
them I can say, for c:,
which will be of
type character,
by the way, in s.characters.
I can't say for c: in s, for
c: in s.characters. And
that's just gonna call my for
loop once with each character.
Question? Yeah,
great question.
So if I do this over cafe,
what am I gonna get? I'm gonna
get four characters, okay,
because that E-accent-agu that
they use is considered in our
human perception
one character.
I'll get four characters.
So there is a character.
Characters are struct,
right and in the character
there is a character that
represents e-accent-agu.
No matter how it's
represented in the string,
in the string it might be two
characters, it might be one,
it doesn't matter. You're
gonna get the one character
for it, so that's a really
good question. How would I
know how many characters
there are in a string? Again,
from the user perspective.
s.characters.count,
not s.length or something,
the count of the characters in
the collection of characters
for this string. Also, what if
I want to find the first space
in a string? Got a string with
a bunch of words, I wanna find
the first space. I would say
s.characters.index(of: " ").
And that's giving me
a string.index(of: " ') that
collection of characters.
I can then use that string in
that index though to go back
to my string and do something.
Maybe insert
something there or
delete the word that's right
after the space or insert
another space. I'll have
the index into the string now.
String is a value type, so
when you do let versus var,
if you do let you cannot
do things like append on to
the string cuz it's immutable.
Most strings in Swift
are immutable, that makes
it super high performance.
But if you have a var you can
do reading plus equals there
and so I can have hello there.
It doesn't have any effect on
hello, the let one because
that's immutable, right? Okay,
so I can't do that. And
I can use the characters to
manipulate strings in really
powerful ways. I can, I don't
have time to talk about all of
it, this is where you really
do need to read your reading
assignment carefully. But for
example if I want to insert
the word you into hello there,
so it says hello you there,
okay, I would just get the,
find the first base by doing
characters.index(of: " "),
which I showed you on the
previous slide. Then there's
a method in string called,
insert the constant,
the content of this
collection of characters
at this location, this
string.index. So, when I want
a collection of characters
that represents " you", I say,
" you".characters, because
it's the .characters, and
it gives me a collection of
characters for that string. So
it seems a little weird but It
actually turns out to work out
pretty well. And there's
a billion other functions,
in Swift, many, many, many,
I can't talk about them all.
Notice I say if let
firstSpace, because that might
return nil if it couldn't find
it. So I wouldn't do it there,
I wouldn't insert it there.
Yeah a bunch of other things
checking where strings
have prefixes or not.
You can replace subrange,
of course you have to find
the range which usually you're
gonna have to look at that
collection of characters to
find the ranges you wanna
replace things etc. Even
cool methods like components
separated by string will take
a string that has like calm or
separated values and
grab all of the values and
put them in an array which
is kinda fun. Okay so
a lot: string has dozens and
dozens of methods, you really
need to familiarize yourself.
If you don't take the time to
familiarize yourself with
those thing in strings.
Then I guarantee you're going
to be writing a program and
you're going to want to
do some string parsing or
something and you're going
to write a whole bunch of
code to do it and then find
out there was one method that
did exactly what you
want in the string.
There are things in
there take closures and
do all kinds of fun stuff so
make sure you pay attention
to both to string and
to the character view which is
a collection of characters.
All right, other classes. This
is kind of quick summary here
of other important classes.
One is NSObject, NSObject is
a class. It is the root of all
Objective-C classes. An iOS
app written before a couple
years ago when Swift came out,
all the classes in there
would inherit eventually from
NSObject. So NSObject has a
base functionality. You do not
need to subclass from NSObject
to make a swift class.
However there are some really
obscure features still left in
IOS where to expecting a class
that inherit from NSObject.
If we even get to them,
I'll show them to you. They're
pretty rare. But that's just
so you know what NSObject is.
Doesn't really have
meaning to you,
cuz you guys are gonna
be Swift programmers.
NSNumber is another class,
it's a generic number
holder. This is also inherited
from Objective-C, you can tell
by the NS there. Until we
can hold any kind of number,
floating point, decimal,
you can even hold a bool,
since it considers that a
number where zero is false and
one is true. Any nonzero
is true. And you can also
do type conversions. Again,
in swift, we're gonna be using
the actual concrete number
classes like double an int and
we'll use their constructors.
To do type conversion.
But just so that you know that
NSNumber is around. Okay,
date. Super important class.
Anytime you are representing
a date or time, you're gonna
wanna use this date struct.
And it has a lot of ancillary
classes that go with it,
like calendar, date formatter,
date components like date
components will tell you
the month of a date. And
of course, what the month
of is of a date depends on
the calendar it's in, cuz not
everyone uses a calendar like
we do. All right,
there's a lot of calendars
all over the Earth that
are different than ours.
So anytime you're even
contemplating putting a date
anywhere in your UI you need
to be using this class.
Because if you wanna have
your app work in anything but
English, you're gonna have
to format your date, using
the DateFormatter, in whatever
locale your app is running in.
So date is super important.
You would think date is really
easy, but no. Date actually
has a lot of complexity to it,
because of all the different
ways we represent dates in
the world. Same, similar
to strings complexity. And
then there's data, D-A-T-A,
that represents a bag o' bits.
Just a bits, bunch of bits in
there. Usually this might be
something like an image,
the bits of an image, or
something like that. Something
you get over the the network.
So data is how we
represent those.
Notice that there is a struct,
it's a value type.
It gets passed around
copy on right. And
you'll start seeing data
in UI maybe week five or
six of this class.
All right, initialization.
So initialization is
very complicated. You're
gonna have to read the reading
assignment on it eventually.
I'm gonna give you the really
fast highlights of it. init
method, again, we can have
them on classes or structs.
They are used to initialize
any of the properties that we
didn't initialize with equals
or using lazy or they were
optionals. All those are taken
care of and if there's one
left, or more than one left,
then we need an initializer.
To initialize it. And they're
kind of a pain in the neck.
Because, especially for
classes. For structs,
they're not a pain in the
neck. They are perfectly fine.
Struct, you just have an init
with whatever argue you want,
arguments you want.
And initialize your variables.
It's all very simple. But for
classes, it's a little more
complicated. Now, whether
you're a struct or a class,
you can have multiple init.
And they can have different
arguments. As long as you give
them enough arguments to be
able to initialize all their
variables, you're good to go.
So you can have as
many inits as you want.
And a lot of classes have
multiple inits. Meaning on
kinda how they are being used,
how they are being created.
Think of something
like string.
String has an init
that takes a double.
It has a string that takes
another sting if you want to
make a copy of the string it
turns out. It takes an init.
It has all these things that
you can compare to string.
Or not all the things
you compare string but
a lot of things you can
compare to a string.
It has an initialized that it
will take that as an argument
for example. Callers execute
your init by creating
one of the thing. They just
put the name of the type and
parentheses and the arguments
you want for that init. So
they pick which of your
init that they want and
they call that one
with those arguments.
We've seen many examples of
this in our lecture, so far.
You get some inits for free.
If you're a base class, okay,
you don't inherit
from anything else.
You get a free init with no
arguments. Congratulations.
So that means, at least,
people can create you.
But, again, if you have any
vars that aren't initialized,
you're gonna have to create
your inits that initialize
them. Structs are even better.
They get an init that has all
of their vars. Now if a struct
implements even one of its own
initializers, it stops getting
this one, this free one.
You only get the free one if
you don't do any other ones.
So it's like the default one.
And we saw this in
the lecture also.
We got the free one in the
init function, first operand.
We never wrote that init
function, we got it for free.
It just appeared and
we were able to call it. , so
structure nice you get
the basic free init for
all your vars. What can you
do inside of a nit? I'm
gonna start going fast here,
okay. So here we go. One,
you can set any properties
value even if that property
already had its value set,
you can reset something else.
You can set lets. So
you're gonna have a let that's
got less x equal 5. You can
still reset it in your init.
Your init is allowed to set
lets. You can call other init
methods okay in your own class
or your own struct. And you do
that by saying self.init with
whatever the arguments to that
init method are so init
methods can call each other.
In a class,
you can call super.init.
An initializer from
your super class.
Of course you need to get
your super class initialized.
Now, when we start talking
about class though,
and we start talking about
calling inits in our super,
and we start thinking
about inheritance,
it gets really complicated. So
let's start thinking about
class and break this down.
Let's start with what are you
required to do in an init for
a class? in a struct it's
easy you're just required to
initialize all your vars
that aren't initialized. But
in a class what are you
required to do? By the time
it's done you have to have
initialized all your vars.
We know that. There are two
types of initializers.
A convenience initializer.
This is only for classes.
A convenience initializer and
what's called
a designated initializer.
Designated is the default.
There's no keyword it's just
if it's not marked convenience
then it's a designated.
Now here's where
the rules come in.
A designated initializer
non convenience must and
can only, call the designated
initializer that it is in,
that is in it's
immediate superclass,
it's very important. It has
to call a superclass init
and it has to get designated
initializer. It cannot call
it's convenience initializer
in a superclass. Nor
can it call two classes up the
inherent chain unless the one
right above inherited the init
from the one up above, and
we'll talk about that in a
second. You have to initialize
all of your properties before
you call that super init.
You must have completely
done all the ones that you
introduced in your class.
Get them initialized before
you call super init. And,
you have to call the super one
before you can reinitialize or
change the value of any of
it's Properties, obviously,
you gotta let your super class
have a chance to initialize
itself before you start
mucking with its properties.
Otherwise, when units call
super, it's probably gonna
blast whatever you did
to its properties.
A convenience init can only,
must and can only,
call an initializer in
its own class, no super.
Only in your own class,
convenience initializer only
in your own class. You can
call it another convenience or
you can call it designator,
but it has to be
in your own class,
not in your super class. And
a convenience init has to call
whatever init it's gonna call
in itself before it can
set any of the property
values. It's kind of different
from an init that calls into
super because that one has
to do its initialization,
the designated one,
before it calls super.
This, in this case,
you have to do convenience,
you have to call your
other one first.
And the calling of all other
inits, whatever you do, any
inits that you have to call
has to be done in all cases,
before you start calling
methods on yourself or
accessing properties.
Not setting the properties,
but accessing them.
In other words, you have to be
fully initialized before your
init can start using
your class. All right,
whew is right: a lot of rules
there, and a lot of them
are conflicting and all that
stuff. Let's make it even more
complicated when we talk
about inheriting inits. So,
you wanna get some inits
from your super class,
whoa, not so fast.
If you don't implement
any designated inits, you only
implement convenience inits,
then you'll inherit all of
your super classes designated,
but only if you don't
implement any of them.
And if you implement
even one designated init,
now you're not gonna inherit
all your super classes. If you
override all of your super
classes designated inits,
then you'll inherit all of
its con, convenience inits.
Now why is that? That's
because your superclass,
when it implements these
convenience inits,
it depends on the designated
inits being implemented,
so you have to
implement them all.
Of course, you could inherit
them all by implementing
none of them as well. So, any
init that you inherit by these
rules can be used to
satisfy any of these other,
other requirements that we're
talking about on the previous
stage. You can make an init
required. You just say
required init. Required is
a key word, and that will
make it so the subclass has
to implement that init, okay,
it's required. Failable inits,
we talked about these with
double. If you put a question
mark after your init,
init question mark, that means
that this init can fail.
And that means that this init,
or when you create this thing,
will return optional
version of this class. So
we thought it was double.
If we said double parentheses
string, it would return
an optional double.
It was a failable init, and
that's because you could have
said double of hello, and
you would be like " I can't
turn it into double: fail".
And the way you fail out of
a failable init is you just
return nil. Otherwise,
you don't return anything out
of init, it just initializes,
but the one time you
return anything is out
a failed init, you can return
nil. So, an example here is
UIImage. UIImaged named
looks up that image in
the xe assets. Remember that
xe assets thing that I moved
off to supporting files at the
beginning of the first demo?
This looks it up in there, of
course, it might not find it.
So we do if let image =
UIImage(named: "foo"),
then we do something,
otherwise we fail,
that UI image initializer
failed. Alright, Any and
AnyObject. There is no more
init, we're done with init.
Any and AnyObject: these
are types, special types.
These types really are almost
exclusively used for backwards
compatibility with Objective C
because Objective C had a type
in it called id,
which was kind of like Any,
AnyObject actually. So Swift
needed some compatibility, but
Swift doesn't really
use Any very much, so
we wouldn't, Swift is strongly
typed. So you wouldn't wanna
have a type which is like, it
can be anything. Okay, because
that's what Any and AnyObject
are, it's like anything,
any type. It's this weird kind
of typeless type kinda thing.
The only difference
between Any and
AnyObject is AnyObject
can only be a class,
it has be a reference type.
Any can be anything,
reference or a value type,
that's the only difference.
So why do we have these
AnyObject things?
Where are they gonna show up?
Well,
there are some methods in iOS
where one of the arguments
truly could be anything. One
example here is when you have
multiple MVCs, which we're
gonna learn about next week.
The way you go from one to the
next, next is called segueing,
you segue from one
MVC to the next.
And the thing that causes
a segue to happen, okay,
is the argument in this
method called prepare for
segue called sender, okay,
just like we had sender
in the IB action. So
the sender is the one who's
causing this segue to happen,
well, a button could be
causing a segue to happen,
a line in a table view could
be causing it. Some custom
piece of code of yours could
be causing this MVC to segue.
So when you're preparing for
it, you've gotta be
able to say which one it was,
and that's just Any. So
if this were a Swift API,
they wouldn't have done Any.
They'd have had a protocol
where you could be a segue
sender. And you'd have to
implement probably some
functionality that would make
sense here. But in this case,
it's Any. It knows optional
Any too because you can have
nil, the center could be nil.
Where else will you see it?
You could have an array of
AnyObject or an array of Any.
That could be an array that
has doubles and strings and
things mixed in there. Now you
might be tempted to use this
in your assignment number two
when you see the assignment.
But you're not allowed to
because one of the required
tasks says you can't use Any
or AnyObject. Also you
wouldn't be very Swifty.
In Swift, if we wanted
to put doubles and
strings in the same array,
we use an enum.
That's what we did with our
operations array, and that's
what we would do in Swift, so
we wouldn't use AnyObject.
Another thing you could
possibly use Any for is for
a cookie, right, some piece
of data that you're giving
out that you don't want people
to know what class it is.
And they're just gonna give
it back to you at some point,
and you'll do
something with it and
only you know what it is.
So you know, an opaque type,
you could use it for
that. How do we use something
of type Any, because we can't
send any messages to it cuz
it's not of AnyType, so
we don't know any methods that
it does or whatever. Instead,
we have convert it, and
we convert type Any or, or
AnyObject into some class
that we know about using as.
As is a key word, and we do as
question mark because we don't
know for sure that we
can convert something,
so it's an optional.
And we use it with if let.
So if I had some
variable unknown,
which is of type Any, so I
don't really know what it is.
But I think it might be
MyType, I'm not sure.
But I think that might be
MyType in there. So I say,
if let foo =
unknown as MyType,
if let. Then inside there, foo
is now going to be unknown,
but as MyType.
So I will be able to
send foo message whatever my
tape, I'll be able to send foo
whatever MyType understands,
methods and vars.
So that's how we use it.
We use this "as?", it's called
casting. This casting, by the
way, not just for AnyObject,
we can cast other things. For
example, if I had a variable
which is, vc which is
a type UIViewController,
I could assign it to UI,
to CalculatorViewController.
Because
CalculatorViewController is
a subclass of
UIViewController. So
it is a UIViewController, so
I could assign it to vc. But
if I assign it like this,
with this typing,
I cannot say vc.displayValue
cuz vc.displayValue,
displayValue is a var in
CalculatorViewController,
and vc is of type
UIViewController.
Even though it points to
a CalculatorViewController,
from Swift's perspective,
it's typed as vc, and
Swift is strongly typed. So if
I wanted to send displayValue,
I would have to say,
if I can let calcVC = vc
as a CalculatorViewController
Now I can send displayValue to
calcVC. Cuz it's the type
that you actually
type it as that matters, not
what it's pointing to. So you
have to use as to get it to
be something that you really
wanna use. Okay, I'm gonna
go a little bit over here.
If you have to go, it's,
it's fine, just keep it quiet.
The last thing I'm gonna
talk about is user defaults.
User defaults is
a very lightweight,
limited database. It's a tiny
little database that persists
between launchings of
your app. It's great for
things like settings and
stuff like that.
Don't put anything big in
there. The only thing you can
put in this database is what's
called a property list.
A property list just means
any combination of array,
dictionary, string,
date, data, or
a number, like int,
float, double, whatever.
That's what a property list
is. It's just conceptual.
There's no actual type
property list, unfortunately.
If this were a Swift API, it
probably would be such a type.
It could be a protocol.
But anyway, there's not.
This is from Objective-C.
So since there's no type
that represents that
codgepodge of classes,
this API that I'm gonna show
user defaults uses Any. And
this is what it looks like.
It has this core, set, and
get. Set Any? Now that
Any can't really be Any,
it has to be one of those
types, string, dictionary,
array, whatever, it has
to be be a Property List,
forKey string. So you just
put it, anything you want
in this database
under a certain key.
And then you get it back out
by saying, object for key, and
it returns you an Any. And
it's an optional Any because
it might not be
in the database,
in which it is returned nil.
So it says any but
it's not really Any, it's Any
as long as the property lists,
which means it's one of
these ten classes or
whatever. The way you read and
write it, you don't create
a user default by saying let
x equal user defaults
with parentheses.
You say let defaults =
UserDefaults.standard, so
that's a type var on
the user default struct.
And you get this standard
UserDefaults and
then you can send
it things like set,
that thing I was telling you,
set Any. And here,
I've got three different sets,
one of them setting of double,
one setting an array of ints.
An array of ints is okay
because array is part of
property list. And so is int,
so that's okay. That's
a property list. An array
of ints is a property list, a
property list. So is a double,
cuz it's one of those types.
And I just set them in there.
And then when I get them out,
I use that object for key.
And actually for
some common types,
like doubles, arrays and
dictionaries, there's actually
a nice little method in there
to give you that type back.
That's so you that don't
get an Any back and
then have to do as. Because
you know that objects for
key returns an Any until
you give this Any and
you have to go if this
thing has a double,
then I've got it. That would
be annoying. So instead,
it just has a method called
double that does that as for
you. And if the as fails
then you, I think either,
I don't know if it returns a
double or an optional double,
but you might get zero back,
you might get a nil.
I don't remember exactly.
But for array in dictionary,
a couple of interesting
things to note. Obviously,
the Anys that are inside
the array in dictionary,
those will have to be property
lists as well, the things that
are returned to you.
And also know that dictionary,
this convenience
method dictionary,
it's the string is always
the key in the dictionary.
If you had a dictionary where
the keys were say, ints.
I think that's a valid key,
yeah, in the dictionary, yeah,
it is. Then you would not
use this convenience method.
You'd have to use object for
key and then use as to turn it
back into a dictionary
with int keys.
Saving the database is
autosave, so you actually
don't have to save it. If you
wanna force it to save because
you're worried that
the autosave might not happen.
You're gonna exit your program
or something, you can use this
method synchronize. It's
called synchronize defaults.
It will synchronize it.
That's almost it, assertions.
Sorry, one last quick thing.
Assertions are just a little
Swift function that takes a
closure as the first argument
and a message as
the second argument.
All it does is it executes the
closure. If that returns true,
it does not crash your
program. If it returns false,
it crashes your program and
prints that message out. So
you could put, you know, some
validation call. This line of
code will not even execute in
the version of your app that
you ship on the app store.
When you build the app for
release, the asserts
are completely ignored.
It doesn't even actually give
the closure, let alone crash.
It just ignores them, so this
is a debugging thing only,
okay? That's it! For Friday,
we do have Friday session,
it's at the normal time. And
it's gonna be on source
code management.
A really cool way to manage
your code even if you're just
one programmer working on a
project by yourself. And then
next week I'm going to talk
about doing custom drawing
in your own view. Multi-touch,
like pinches and swipes, and
things like that.
And finally, multiple MVCs so
we can build a more
powerful calculator.
Your assignment two has gone
out. It's already posted.
It's essentially enhancing
your calculator with a lot of
the things that I talked
about today like tuples and
defaulting values and
even value types.
All kinds of stuff. So we'll
have a lot of fun with that.
>> For more,
please visit us
at standford.edu