[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well,
welcome to Stanford CS193P.
This is Developing iOS
Application, Winter of 2017.
And the only topic for
today is a big one, Core Data,
which is an object
oriented database.
But before I dive into this,
I'm actually going to revisit
that demo we did last time
just briefly, because we
ran out of time and so
I wasn't able to show
you the refresh control.
Now I posted the code for
it, so
I'm not gonna type
all the code in here.
But I'm just gonna
briefly show you
how that refresh
control worked, okay?
Okay, so we missed that.
So here is the app we
had from last time.
By the way,
I have modified our app
here to change our
request a little bit.
If you remember this line
of code from last time,
it used to just
have the query.
But I've changed it to also
filter out retweets and
I've also put on the safe
filter, which hopefully will
make it so
that when I do these look ups,
these sort of up looks, we
don't get stuff on the screen,
you know this is
a family show,
so we don't want to see
some of that stuff.
Anyway, hopefully,
that'll work.
So let's go back here and
take a look at what
this looks like.
There's my simulator
right here.
So let's go ahead and search.
Let's try Trump again and
cross our fingers, all right.
So that's not, I don't see
anything too terrible there.
Okay so what we added was this
UI where we can pull down.
Okay and it adds more tweets,
you see how it added
a tweet there?
We have the second
pull right there,
this was with the first pull.
And we pull down again,
no tweets this time, okay?
So each time we pull down
it's doing another twitter
fetch, and
may get more tweets depending
if people are tweeting or not.
So let's take a look at
the code to do this, again,
I posted this code, but
we'll just look at it,
I'm not gonna type it all in,
we're just gonna look
at it real quick.
First of all, let's talk about
how do I get this UI where
we pull down and it calls
a method, or whatever?
So let's go to look
in our storyboard.
All right, so
here's our storyboard, and
what I did was I just selected
my table view controller and
I went down here to
this refreshing.
You see that
refreshing choice?
And I changed it from disabled
to enabled, and when I set it
to enabled nothing
changed here in the UI.
You can't see any
spinning thing, but
over here in the document
outline it created this
refresh control right here.
And so I can control drag from
the document outline just as I
can through here.
So all I did to make this
work is I just brought up
my controller right here.
And here's the method I
did it with right here.
I just Ctrl dragged from the
Refresh Control to this method
called refresh, okay?
That's all I did to,
to make that happen.
And inside refresh,
I just called that same method
I had before, searchForTweets.
This one right here, the one
that search for tweets.
And that used to
look like this,
I only changed one
thing in here.
It used to just get
the twitterRequest by
looking at our
search term up here.
Remember this function?
And all I did was added this,
which says, if
the lastTwitterRequest has a
newer version, then use that.
But if it doesn't, then
default back to doing to query
request the way we used to.
The only other things that I
had to do was turn the refresh
control off, you do that
with the end refreshing.
So I just did that when I went
back to the main queue here,
to get my results,
so I turned it off.
I also turned it off if for
some reason I couldn't get
any request or whatsoever.
Okay, there's nothing in
the search term field and
I couldn't get a newer
version of my last request.
So I just said, I'm gonna
make sure that thing is not
spinning and spinning forever.
They wanna get out
of here with that.
And the only other thing
I had to do was up here,
when the search text changes,
someone types#Stanford or
something like that, I need to
invalidate that last Twitter
request so that it's not
trying to get new versions
of the previous
one that I had.
I want it to do the new one.
And the way that I made it so
that we had these little
titles right here, see these
titles two, three, four, five?
I implemented another UI table
view data source method,
this one down here.
Called
titleForHeaderInSection.
I just put titles
on the sections.
Remember, each section is
another pull from Twitter.
And so I just have each title.
It's actually gonna be the
count of things I had minus
the section number.
So the top one
is section zero.
So section zero is gonna show
the number of pulls
that I've made.
tweets.count is how
many pulls I made.
And it's obviously gonna
decrement as
the sections go down.
Okay, so
that's what gave us this.
And you can see that
the longer we wait,
obviously it pulls
more information,
as tweets pile up.
Okay, let's go back
to our slides.
All right, here we go.
So Core Data is this big
framework inside of iOS for
doing object-oriented
databases.
So let's talk a little bit
about what that means.
So, when do you
need a database?
Well you need a database when
you have a large amount of
data, and especially if you
want to kind of make queries
into that data and find out
things about that data and
the relationships between
all the things in there.
You really can't
do that by like,
taking a big dictionary or
a big array and
searching through it,
you need a database.
And so there's a lot of
technologies for databases out
there but most of them
are not object-oriented.
So we have this framework
that Apple provides called
Core Data, it's what we call
an object-oriented database
but actually, it's really not
on the inside.
It's only an object-oriented
database on the outside.
The side that you look at.
Underneath, it's actually
a relational database usually.
Now Core Data is designed to
have any backend of storage.
But it's primary
implementation is on top of
SQL which is
a relational database.
How many people know
what SQL Database is?
Okay, almost all of you, good.
So, if we had to do databases
in our iOS apps using SQL,
we'd be like no, I have
to learn this whole query
language, and
how am I gonna do this?
Not to worry, we don't have to
know any SQL to use core Data.
No SQL whatsoever- we're
just gonna purely do this
on the object side.
So how does this work?
How does core Data work?
Well, first we're gonna
create a visual mapping
between things in
our database and
some objects that we're gonna
be able to program with
in our object-oriented
code that we like.
And kinda roughly, it's
the tables in the database
are kinda gonna be objects.
And the columns in
the tables are kind of vars.
But we don't even really
care what it's doing there.
What we're gonna focus
on is this visual map,
this visual description
basically of our schema.
Okay, how many people know
what the word schema means?
Okay, so two-thirds of you.
So schema is basically
the description of what's
in your database, not the
contents of it but how all its
data types are and how they
relate to each other, etc.
So we're gonna do all
that graphically.
And this is what
it looks like.
First, if I wanna use
Core Data in my app,
I'm almost certainly going
to wanna click this button
that says Use Core Data.
We've seen it every time we've
created an app, and we haven't
clicked it so far, but
now we are going to click it.
And clicking
Use Core Data there,
is gonna create two things for
us, this visual map,
and some code in
your App Delegate.
And I'm gonna talk about
both of those things.
Now before I go to
the next slide,
notice that the name of this
app is CoreDataExample.
That's the, just the name of
the app that I typed in there.
So when I create this app,
clicking that
Use Core Data on, you'll see
that it created this file,
CoreDataExample.xcdatamodeld.
So it chose the name
of my app as it.
And this is going to be
our data model, all right?
And so we'll, we'll talk
about the AppDelegate
code that Use Core Data also
generated a little bit later.
Right now we're gonna focus
on this data model file.
All right, but before we even
do that, what happens if we
have an existing app and you
did not click Use Core Data?
And now you decided, hey,
I wanna add core data.
Like maybe Smashtag Assignment
5 comes out and
I tell you to add some
Core Data to Smashtag.
And you're like, woh,
I can't go back and
click Use Core Data,
it's too late.
So you're gonna have to
create this data model file
using new file.
So you just go to File
> New > File like this.
You're not gonna pick any of
the things we've picked so
far.
You're gonna scroll down
to the section that
says Core Data.
And inside there these,
there's two things,
Data Model and Mapping Model.
And make sure you pick Data
Model because that's what you
want to do here is
create your data model,
your schema essentially,
for your database.
It's gonna ask you
what you wanna call it.
Now, you don't have to call
this the same as the name of
your application like
Use Core Data button does.
You can call it
anything you want.
So here, just to be different,
I've called it Model,
it's my model.
And by the way,
your core data is usually
the model of a lot of MVCs.
Okay, a lot of MVCs, their
job is going to be to display
the data in the database, and
so this data model is actually
the MVC model as well for
a lot of MVCs.
So I'll call this one model,
and
you can see it created
model.xedatamodeld.
So whether you get that file
by doing Use Core Data or
whether you get it by
creating it yourself,
you're gonna have
this mapping file.
Now, let me go back to
that AppDelegate thing.
I said they was gonna put some
code in your AppDelegate.
It's very small
amount of code.
But I wanted to show
it to you right here.
This is what it looks like.
It just creates this
one var right here.
By the way, if you didn't do
Use Core Data, of course,
you need this code
in your AppDelegate,
how are you gonna get it?
Just go create some
dummy application.
Call it Foo, it doesn't really
matter what you call it.
Click Use Core Data
when you create it and
then copy this code from
that AppDelegate to here.
Okay, the code is
identical from every app.
The only difference between
any of those things is this
one string right here.
You see that string?
That's the name of
that xcmodeld file, so
datamodeld file.
So with our core data example,
this string would
be CoreDataExample.
When we went back and created
it on our own with new file,
of course, we called it Model.
So just make sure this string
matches the name of the file,
the xcmodel datamodeld file,
okay?
So that's what you need to
do if you didn't do the use
Code Data originally
you are going back and
adding it- just copy and
paste.
It's only this one var really,
it does provide another thing
in your AppDelegate which is
a function called saveContext.
It's a very simple
little function.
I'm gonna show you how you
could write it yourself.
If you wanna copy it in,
you can.
Also I notice that they have
applicationWillTerminate which
is this application,
AppDelegate method,
that gets called right
before you get terminated or
you terminate it in any way
and they call saveContext.
Well, it's a kind of an idea,
a good idea.
saveContext() just
saves your database.
That's what saveContext does,
all right?
So this is how you can make
up if you didn't do it.
So anyway, you can see that
the only thing in here
is this lazy var
persistentContainer, and
I'm gonna talk all about
persistentContainer,
because that's the thing
that essentially contains
your database, all right?
But let's go back and
talk about the visual map.
Cuz we have to have a visual
map before we can do anything
in our database because we
have to have some things in
our database, some objects and
things like that.
And Core database stores
things in this kind of very
straightforward way.
It looks very object-oriented
in our code because
in Core Data terms
it's storing entities,
which look like
classes to our code.
Attributes, which look
like vars on our classes.
And relationship, which just
look like vars that point to
other objects in the database,
other entities, etc.
And so we're gonna use this
what I'm calling a storyboard.
It's not, don't get confused,
this is not a storyboard,
okay?
You know what a storyboard is,
your Interface Builder thing.
But it's kind of
like a storyboard,
that's why it's in quotes for
databases.
It's a graphical,
visual editor to create and
describe all these entities,
attributes and relationships,
okay, that's what
we're gonna do here.
So let's start by
adding an entity.
Very easy, we go down to this
button on the bottom here
called Add Entity.
Okay, to add an entity.
By the way, there's couple
other things in that if you
hold down on that button
you'll see Add Fetch Request,
and Add Configuration.
I don't have time to talk
about those unfortunately,
but especially Add Fetch
Request is kind of a cool one.
So, if you can take what I
teach you here and extend it
by going and learning about
that, that would be great.
So you click Add Entity,
it creates a new
entity called Entity.
Cuz it doesn't know what
name you want for it yet.
And like I say,
this analogous to a class.
Now in our code we're gonna
see any instances of this
entity as instances of a class
called NSManagedObject.
So NSManagedObject super
important in Core Data.
It is the super class or
the class of everything that
comes, all these entities that
come out of the database.
It's like the thing that
represents them in our code,
and we'll see all about that.
So for my kind of slides here,
what I'm gonna do is create
a database that would have
stuff like we got
from Twitter.
So it's gonna have tweets and
we're gonna have
Twitter users.
So those are gonna be two
entities that we have and
you're gonna see eventually,
we're gonna have Tweet and
TwitterUser classes
in our code and
we're gonna access vars and
all that stuff.
So I'm gonna rename
this entity,
this, that I added that
was defaulted to entity,
I'm gonna rename it and
call it Tweet.
So this is gonna be the first
entity that I'm creating
in the database.
Now, an entity can
have attributes.
Those are kind of like vars,
and relationships.
Those are like vars that
point to other entities.
And I told you this fetched
properties down at the bottom,
I'm not gonna talk about.
Very cool, but
not gonna talk about them.
Not just time-wise.
So let's go and add some
attributes to this entity.
Real easy,
you click this plus button,
there's also
an Add Attribute button,
see it down in the lower
right hand corner there.
But I'm gonna click
this little plus
button right there under
the section called Attributes.
And when I do there it adds a
new attribute called attribute
and I'm gonna edit
its name directly,
just like I did
the entity name.
I'm gonna change
this to be text.
So, this is gonna be our tweet
text, the 140 characters
of the tweet is gonna be
this particular attribute.
Now, notice as soon as I
did that, I got an error.
In the corner there,
this red error.
And the reason for
that is all attributes
have to have a type.
They can't just be undefined
type like this one is.
You see where it says
the type is undefined.
So, we need to change
that to be a type.
And it's really easy, right
there where it says undefined.
We're just going
to mouse down,
it's gonna bring up a menu and
we can choose our type.
Now, these are the types
we have to choose from.
A lot of different numeric
types like 16-bit integers,
32-bit integer, etc.
Doubles, floats,
can a be string of course,
a Boolean value, a date which
is going to look like a date,
you know,
the date struct in our code.
And binary data which is gonna
look like the data struct
inside our code.
So, these are gonna map to
very familiar data types
that we see.
There is that one at
the bottom there,
transformable, another thing
I'm not gonna talk about.
But transformable allows
you to store anything
into the database by
converting it to a data, and
then converting it
back on the way out.
And so if you pick
transformable there,
you're gonna have to
do some extra work.
To tell Core Data about that
transformation, and that's why
I don't really have time to
tell you about, but just know
that if you wanted to store
something like a CGRect.
Actually, if I was going to
store a CGRect, I might use
the function, there's some
function called something like
NSStringFromCGRect.
It gives you a string, and
then there's
NSCGRectFromString or
something like that.
So I'd probably store
it as a string,
but if I had something more
complicated than that,
then I might use
a transformable.
All right, these attributes
here are going to be accessed,
we're gonna get and
set their values.
Well actually, we're not going
to do this but fundamentally
the way you do it is you
have these two methods,
value(forKey) and
setValue (forKey).
And I'll talk about how
we're gonna use that, but
that's how we're gonna set and
get the values on an entity.
Notice the error went
away as soon as we
gave this thing, a type.
So here I'm gonna add some
more attributes, identifier,
which is just some string
that identifies the tweet and
then created,
which was when it was tweeted.
Notice I'm setting created's
type here to be date because
it is a date, obviously,
when the thing was created.
Now this is one way to look at
our entities and attributes,
this kind of table form.
But we can actually look at
it in graphical form as well.
If you see down in the corner
where it says editor style.
If I click on
the other button there,
the one that looks a little
more like a graph,
then it shows me
the same thing but
in this graphical form.
It's even on graph paper,
all right?
And in this form
right here we can do
all the things that we
did in the other one.
For example,
I can still add entity here.
So I'm gonna add another
entity for my Twitter User,
this is people who tweet.
And there it is,
it called it entity again,
that's the default.
We'll set its name
to be TwitterUser.
All right, so we now have two
entities, you see on there.
What's kinda cool is as you
drag these entities around,
this, this kind of editor,
this graphical
editor, will automatically
kind of keep them spaced apart
from each other.
Which is kind of fun,
especially since they're going
to start having wires
connecting them because
they're going to start
having relationships
to each other as you're
going to see in a moment.
We can add attributes in this
graphical style as well- you
can edit those right in there
just by double clicking on
them, change
whatever you want.
So, here I got a screenName,
now of course I got an error
again because I didn't set
the type of that screenName.
So, in this view you set
the types by bringing up
the inspector.
So you just bring up
your normal inspector,
attribute inspector.
And the, here you can see
it's inspecting screenName,
it's got the name there.
There's some other things
in here like transient,
indexed, optional.
By the way, that optional
doesn't mean this is optional
like the Swift thing optional.
This is optional like in
SQL database terms, right.
In relational
database optional.
So I'm not gonna talk
about any of the database
You rarely need to set any of
these properties right here.
stuff of it.
But you do need
to set the type.
So we're not gonna
talk about that, but
we have to set
the type right here.
And the screenName,
of course, is a string.
So I'm just gonna
change it to a string.
I'm adding another attribute
to the TwitterUser,
this one is the name,
the person's actual name,
not their @ sign handle,
but their actual name.
Now we've built a couple
of entities with a bunch of
attributes on them, okay,
and this is gonna look like
classes with vars in
our code eventually.
But what about relationships,
obviously a Tweet and
a TwitterUser have
a relationship to each other.
And to create relationships
between things we just
Ctrl+drag, this is our
favorite gesture in Xcode and
we're using it again.
Ctrl+drag to create
a relationship
between two things.
And it actually doesn't matter
which direction you Ctrl+drag,
because you're creating
kind of a bidirectional
relationship.
So here, I did Ctrl+drag, and
it automatically created this
relationship, which it called
newRelationship on both sides.
And this relationship is
essentially just gonna be
a var in our class.
But the var's type is either
going to be the type, if it's
like a Tweet, you know,
it's gonna be a single one, or
it could be an NSSet,
if it's many of them.
Like a Twitter user might
have many tweets, and
I'll talk about
that in a moment.
So, from a Tweet's perspective
this relationship to
a TwitterUser is the Tweeter.
The person who
tweeted this tweet.
So, I'm going to change the
name of this relationship on
the Tweet side to be tweeter
instead of newRelationship,
which was the default.
But, on the other, okay, so
that's why I call it tweeter.
On the other side
the TwitterUser from its
perspective though, okay, the
relationship of the tweet is
the tweets that this
Twitter user has tweeted.
Okay, it's not tweeter, the
Twitter user is the tweeter,
so he would never call
this relationship tweeter.
He's gonna call this
relationship tweets
because this is the tweet.
Now notice that's plural,
okay,
we'll talk about
that in a second.
Notice that when we do this,
Xcode tracks if I'm inspecting
the tweet's relationship there
on the TwitterUser side,
it knows the inverse.
It knows that tweeter goes
the opposite direction,
there's always gonna be
an inverse relationship.
So let's talk about that
tweets being a plural right?
So a tweet can only
have one tweeter.
Only one person can
have tweeted it, but
a Twitter user can tweet
thousands of tweets, okay?
And so
that's a little different
kind of relationship.
So how do we specify that?
We call the tweets
relationship the,
a to many relationship
because obviously the Twitter
user can have many tweets.
So that's called to many
in database parlance, and
you set that right
in the Inspector.
So you just click
on that tweets and
you go over here to
where it says Type,
and instead of having it be
To One you're gonna change it
to be To Many, okay, so now
it's a to many relationship.
Right there, you can see that
it's changed a little bit as,
and we'll show
that in a second.
But the type of this
relationship now on the tweet
side is still type
NSManagedObject,
because it points to another
entity in the database.
And we know that
the objects in the database
are represented by
an NSManagedObject.
So that's gonna be
the type of that var.
Although we're eventually
gonna make it even better than
that, but
on the other side though,
the type of that var is NSSet
of NSManagedObject, okay?
Now NSSet, there is
a Swift struct called set.
It's a generic type, it's just
like an array where you have
to say what's in an array,
same thing with a set you
have to say what's in it.
NSSet is kind of an older
Objective-C kind of set.
It's not generic,
it's untyped.
The things in NSSet are any,
which we kinda need a little
bit here cuz we really don't
know what kinds of things
are in there.
However, in your code you
can cast from this NSSet
of NSManagedObject to a set of
what you know to be in there
using as question mark, and
if that in fact is what's
in there, it will work.
So that's the NSSet there.
One last thing I'm gonna
show you here before
we get back to the slides
is this Delete Rule.
You see the delete
rule on the,
clicked on tweets on here so
we're inspecting tweets.
And this delete rule
tells you what happens
to the pointed-to tweets if
we deleted this Twitter user.
Cuz if I delete
this Twitter user,
does that mean I delete all
of the Twitter user's tweets?
Well, it depends on this
delete rule right here.
this delete rule is saying
nullify, which would mean no.
So right now,
Those tweets would stay in the
database, and their tweeter
will be set to nil because
their tweeter got deleted.
But there is a cascading
delete rule, which would say
if I delete this thing then
delete everything that it
points to, just go right
down the graph and
delete everything.
So that's what controls what
happens when you delete.
Now I'm not gonna ask
you to even do delete;
I guess I might ask you an
extra credit to do delete in
assignment five.
Because deletion kinda-
you're really gonna know what
you're doing- when you
can delete things, and
what kind of delete
rules you want.
But I just want to let
you know that you specify
the delete rule right
here in the inspector.
Okay, now that you've defined
all your entities, attributes
in relationships, then what
can we do with these things?
Well to do anything with it
we need to get a hold of them
in our code,
grab onto them basically, and
to do that we need
another important class,
NSManagedObjectContext, so
I told you
all those things in the
database are NSManagedObjects,
you need
an NSManagedObjectContext,
which represents a database
to do anything with them,
to get any of them,
to create any of them, etc,
this is the hub around which
Core Data activity turns,
as I say there.
So how do I get one of these
NSManagedObjectContext?
And the answer is, you need
a persistentContainer.
Woo-hoo, and you know
where to get one of those.
You just click,
Use Core Data, and
it's gonna appear in
your AppDelegate.
You're gonna get
that lazy var,
that's called
persistentContainer.
And that is gonna be
a persistentContainer.
And from that you
can get the context.
Now, if you have the lazy
var in your AppDelegate,
How the heck do
you call that var?
How do you get that var?
And this is how you do it,
okay?
You get a copy of the shared
UIApplication, now,
we didn't talk about this but
your app has this one and
only UIApplication object that
represents your application
and you get it by doing
UIApplication.shared,
it's a var.
Static var in
UIApplication class.
Gives you the shared one.
Then you're gonna access this
var in UIApplication which is
its delegate.
Now, its delegate is
automatically set up for
you to be this Swift class
AppDelegate that you see
always; we always put it
off in Supporting Files and
get it out of our way,
but it's created for you,
it's a nice little class.
We're going to talk about the
application life cycle, and
where it fits in, in a little
bit, but for now all
you need to know is you can
get AppDelegate, and you want
to send persistentContainer
to it to get that var, but of
course you have to as it to be
the AppDelegate class first.
So this is the code
you're going to use.
(UIApplication.shared.delegate
as!
AppDelegate) All that
in one expression
dot persistentContainer
now you're gonna get this
persistentContainer, and
notice I'm doing as
exclamation point this will
crash if my App Delegate is
not in fact App Delegate,
but it's already wired up
to be that for you when
you create a new project,
so that should
never be a problem.
Okay?
So
now I have this
persistentContainer,
I need to get
the context out of it.
And, so,
the container has an awesome
var called viewContext.
And the viewContext is an
NSManagedObjectContext that's
only suitable for
use on the main queue.
This is in red,
you know whenever you see
anything in red on my slides,
this means pay attention,
it will matter for
your homework,
and in life, but
you can only use this
viewContext in the main queue,
it called viewContext because
you use it with your views,
okay, your UI views, that's
why we call it viewContext.
So why do I make a point
about this main queue?
Well, the reason I do that is
because NSManagedObjectContext
is not thread-safe.
But I'm gonna talk you, talk
to you about how we can do
multithreaded database stuff
towards the end of this talk.
All right, so now you have
this viewContext then you can
use it to do things.
Now, it's so
{UIApplication.shared.delegate
as!
Appdelegate).persistentContai-
ner,
that's kind of
a messy line of code.
There's a lot of, there's as
and all these things in there.
So at times we'll just
create a static version of
persistentContainer in
our AppDelegate.
Okay, we'll just call
it the same thing.
persistentContainer but
it's static and
it's just gonna return
that messy line of code.
So now we can get that
persistentContainer with
AppDelegate.persistentContai-
ner.
See what I did there?
I just made it easier to get
up by making that be a static,
a class var, and we can do the
same thing with viewContext,
you might create a static
called viewContext and for
the rest of these slides you
can assume I've done this.
Which is good because typing
that long messy thing would
make all my slides
spill over the edge.
So I'm gonna use this
shorter version as well.
And you're welcome
to create the static
version in your
AppDelegate if you want
to make your code
a little cleaner.
Now this viewContext in
the persistentContainer
There's one of them that
represents your entire
are shared.
database.
So it's perfectly fine to
create a single static
that does this.
By the way, what if you
wanted multiple databases?
You could even have
multiple databases with
different schema.
Very easy,
if you go look at the code for
persistentContainer in
AppDelegate,
you'll see it's only
like four lines of code.
And you could just copy
it to create a different
persistentContainer using
a different xcmodeld file.
Instead of using model
according to the example,
create another one with
a different one and
you can just go file, new file
and create another data model.
You could even create two
persistent containers with
the same model.
So they would be
separate databases, but
have the same model,
the same entities to that and
the same relationship to that.
It's perfectly
allowed as well.
But for everything you're
going to do in this class, and
for really with most apps,
you're going to have
one big database.
And you're going to have this
one persistent container that
is the container for it.
All right.
So now I have a context in
my hand, this viewContext.
And what can I do?
Well, of course, I can insert
objects into the database.
I can delete objects
from the database.
And I can query for
objects in the database.
So, let's talk about
all those things.
Let's start with insert
because until we insert some
data in the database we can't
do any of those other things.
And the way you insert
an object in the database, or
a way to do it,
and actually for
the next few slide I'm going
to kind of show you the,
the essentials.
But, we're eventually going to
move up to a high level and
access this stuff in
a much nicer way.
But I'll tell you
the basics of it first.
So the basic way to put
something in the database is
with this really
interesting method.
NSEntityDescription.insertNew-
Object(forEntityName: into:
context).
Okay, that's a mouthful, used
to be even more of a mouthful
before they renamed it.
And you just specify
the name of the entity, so
Tweet or TwitterUser.
And you give it a context that
is gonna be the viewContext
you got from the AppDelegate.
And boom, it's gonna create
one of these in the database.
Now all of its
attributes will be nil.
Okay, although you can
inspect the attributes in
the data model editor and
specify default value.
And so it might start out
with the default value.
But if it doesn't,
then they'll start out as nil.
Okay, so that's great.
I can now create one.
And now I need to set those
vars to have some value.
I need to set the text of the
tweet and things like that and
I told you I'm gonna do
this with value for key and
set value for key.
So for example I wanted to
set the let's say the text,
I could just say tweet.
A set value for key quote
text, to be a string.
And you can do dot notation
here, with value for key path.
That's what I'm showing
in green right there.
You can have, if you had
a tweet you can actually set
the tweet's tweeter's name,
using this dot notation to set
value for key path tweeter dot
name and it would go through
the tweeter relationship
which is kinda fun.
I'm kinda going fast through
this because this is a really
terrible API.
First of all it's
got any in there so
there's not type checking
going on here, okay?
You could say, set value date
for key quote text, all right?
And that would be perfectly
accepted by Swift.
Date is an Any and
quote text is a String, but
of course that's gonna fail
miserably at run time, okay,
because the text is a Atring.
So we're not really gonna
use this API but this is
the underlying basic way that
Core Data is doing this.
Yes the key is just the name
of the attribute, and
the value is all the things
we've talked about before.
I do have the blue
Use Scalar Type there which
is interesting.
If the thing you're putting
in the database is a flow or
an Int32 or
one of these things.
It's actually gonna be stored
in a database as an NSNumber,
which is a class,
it's an object, kind of
generic holder of numbers.
But if you flip on the switch
in the inspector in your data
modeller for that attribute
saying use a scalar type,
then it'll make the type be
double or int or whatever,
instead of NSNumber, so.
I know, you had a question?
>> Yes, so the question is,
does set value reject
something where
the types don't match?
And the answer is, it can't.
It doesn't know the type,
the types are any,
as long as it matches any- and
everything matches any.
So, it can't.
There's no way for it to have
enough information to reject.
As long as it matches any,
it'll accept that as the type.
And then at runtime,
it will crash.
If you try to set a date
to be into a string field.
>> So
when it's like [INAUDIBLE]
save context,
do you have to like
make it go through.
Or is it.
>> Go and remove.
>> [CROSSTALK]
>> What do you
mean go and remove it?
Remove what?
Yeah, we'll talk
about saving in this.
So, the question is,
when the app terminates
it does save context and
they're trying to save this,
we'll talk all about saving in
a minute cause that's
an important piece of this.
That's the keys and values,
pretty straightforward there;
in fact we're going to talk
about saving right now.
We do a nice lead in.
All these changes that you
make with that set value even
insert entity description for
entity name context whatever
that thing is called.
All that stuff only
happens in memory,
if you want that to actually
happen permanently in
the database you
need to save it.
And you do that by
telling the context,
like that view context thing,
to save with the method save.
It couldn't be simpler,
except that it can throw.
Save is a method that
can throw because
maybe there's a problem
writing out to the database.
And there's many problems
that could happen writing
out to the database.
And you need to look
at documentation and
kind of figure out
what they all are.
But the take home message
here is you do need to save.
If you don't save, that
substance is gonna be lost
when your app exists or
whatever.
So you definitely just save.
And especially when talking
about multithreaded Core Data.
And one thread is working.
That thread needs to save if
it wants any of the other
threads to see the work
that it's done.
Okay, so you can use try
question mark here, remember,
which means try and
if it fails,
just return nil and ignore it.
You can do that, if you don't
mind that it didn't save.
And the kinda things that
can happen, saving errors.
You could obviously have
file system problems,
your disk is full or
something like that.
But you can also have
inconsistencies in
the database,
maybe you had conflicting
data of two threads trying to
save to the same database, and
they've tried to write over
the top of each other,
those kind of things.
Again, a lot of those problems
you're not gonna have,
unless you build
a pretty complicated,
multithreaded application,
or something like that,
but, again, you gotta check
the documentation, I couldn't,
it would take too long for
me to go through all of it.
Okay now, as I said value
forKey and setValue forKey.
Really ugly,
What we really want to do is
be able to set these vars
as vars, we just wanna
have a var called text
somewhere that we can set.
And of course we're
exactly going to do that.
And the way we're going to do
that is create a subclass of
NSManagedObject, instead of
having NSManagedObject in
the database we doing
set-value, get-value on it.
Instead we're going to create
a subclass of NSManageObjects
and it's going to have vars on
there for all the attributes,
like text, and screen name and
all those things.
And Xcode will generate
all that code for
you behind the scenes,
you don't have to do any
work to make that happen.
Quite quite simple, so let's
look and see how we do that.
You do that by
inspecting the entity.
So here I've chosen tweet.
Okay, not any of
its attributes but
tweet itself, and
I want to make it so
it generates this magic code,
and how do I do that?
Well, if you go down
on the inspector
a little ways you
see it says Codegen.
See that Codegen, that's for
generating this code,
this magic code.
Now, you actually have
a couple of choices here for
the Codegen.
The default I believe is
this one Class Definition.
If you choose this one it will
generate that subclass for
you and it will just work.
Okay, you'll be able to
access your tweets as a class
called tweet.
With all the vars.
Now this sounds good and
it is good; by the way if
you do this class definition
codegen it will not show
up in your navigator.
It's all behind the scenes-
you never really see this file
that is, this codegen
file that generates.
So don't look for
it there if you put this
on class definition.
This might even be
the default actually.
To be Class Definition
might be on.
But there's other
choices in here.
And the one we choose the most
often is Category/Extension.
By the way, category just
is the Objective-C word for
extension.
Objective-C has something like
extensions called categories.
So that's why it says
Category/Extension.
But you can think in your mind
that this just says extension.
And what this is gonna do is
only generate an extension
of your Tweet class.
You have to actually write
the Tweet class itself.
But it's all gonna have
only your code in it, or
it could be empty if you want.
The extension's gonna take
care of all making the vars.
Okay, the var
magic right there.
So let's see how this works.
Even when I switch to
Category/Extension.
Again, I don't get that
extension showing up in
my navigator.
It's kind of hidden from you.
Here I'm gonna add the
extension way of doing it for
TwitterUser too.
So both of them, both Tweet
and TwitterUser, I'm gonna
have an extension generated
and, why do we like this one?
Because, a lot of times for
our Tweet or TwitterUser we
want to add our own code.
Like in a tweet.
Imagine you wanted to add
a static method that took data
from Twitter and turned it
into a tweet in the database.
Where would you put that code?
Well, a great place to put it
would be in a tweet class,
if there was such a thing.
And so, you're in fact,
going to create such a thing.
And the extension is going to
handle all of the var business
for you.
If you did choose Manual/None,
right here for Codegen,
meaning don't do any Codegen,
then you're doing value for
set value for key.
Good luck with that, the
code's gonna be a mess, okay?
So, we almost always do it
this way with this extension.
Also, if we build our app
using multiple modules
like we have in Smash Tag,
we have a framework module and
then we have the main module.
Then you're probably
gonna wanna choose
from this pull-down here
where it says module,
current product module.
I think if you have a single
app that's not modularized
like that you probably
don't need to set that, but
in a multi-modual app
you probably do want to.
So, since we've chosen here
to create only the extension,
we obviously need to write the
code for the classes Tweet And
TwitterUser, we have to create
those classes ourselves.
So how do we do that?
Well, just like we
create anything,
we use file, new file.
Then we do file, new file,
this time we are back
to saying it's a cocoa touch
class because NSManageObject.
Why is it code called
cocoa touch class,
we wanna make sure we set
our super class to be in its
managed object, right?
So, I'm creating
a class called Tweet,
you see, which is a subclass
of NSManagedObject.
And is gonna create this for
us.
See?
Class Tweet: NSManagedObject.
No code in there.
That space is for us,
we get write anything we want.
The code that does the vars
is in that extension which we
don't even see, but but
I'm gonna show it to
yo in a second here.
Notice that I picked
the name of this class Tweet
to be the same as the name of
the entity in the database,
which, you want to do.
It is possible to not do that
by inspecting the entity
in the data model,
but, don't do it.
Just have the entity
with the same name.
People reading your code are
going to expect this class,
this subclass of
NSManageObject that
represents a tweet.
Entity to be called tweet,
so called it that.
Now, we've got an error here,
I'll just created this class,
how I'm gonna possibly
have an error,
I'm done anything how could
I've done anything wrong?
Well, the problem
the problem here is,
really, Xcode has
done something wrong.
When Xcode created this,
it didn't seem to realize that
NSManageObject is
not in UIKit.
You see how it put
import UIKit at the top?
Really, what we need there
is import CoreData, okay.
All the code that you write,
any time you're doing
something in CoreData,
you have to import CoreData.
It's a different framework
that the UIKit so
you must import it everywhere
that you're going to use it.
Just like we had to import
Twitter everywhere we want to
use that Twitter framework
that I gave you.
So, I don't know why Xcode,
I think it's just an oversight
Okay?
that Xcode when you
choose NSManagedObject
as your super class you should
know, that's in Core Data so
it should be import
Core Data there.
Don't know why it
doesn't do that.
So here I've created one for
the TwitterUser class.
Again you can put anything
you want in there.
This is your class.
You can do anything you want.
All the stuff about
the vars is off in
an extension somewhere.
In fact, let's go take
a look at that extension,
Even though it's not going to
show up in your next navigator
what it looks like.
you're probably never
going to look at it.
I thought I'd
show it to you so
you understand a little
bit what's going on.
So, this is the extension,
this generated for
TwitterUser.
You see that is an extension
of the TwitterUser class,
right?
Remember extensions and
it's got the vars.
They're defined not just
name and screenName but
it's got that relationship
var tweets as well.
All right?
And look at
the type of tweets.
As promised, it's an NSSet,
it's an optional because it
comes out of
the database as not set.
It's gonna get set.
So these are the vars.
And I'll talk
a little bit about
how these vars are actually
implemented in a minute but
all the vars are there.
There's also some functions,
now at the bottom you
see those functions,
those are kind of fun, those
are convenience functions for
adding and removing tweets
from the tweets set
because NSSet is immutable,
okay?
It's not var verses
let like swift things,
NS set is kind of old
Objective-C way, and NSSet,
like NSAttributedString, is
immutable, cannot be changed,
so how can I add any tweets
to my database here?
Well you used these functions
instead, add to tweets,
remove from tweets,
add to tweets,
remove from tweets, there's a
pair for doing a single tweet,
and there having adding
a whole bunch of tweets, or
removing a whole bunch
of tweets, okay?
So you're definitely going
to want those functions for
your assignment five.
Cuz you're gonna have some
relationships where you're
gonna want to add them
using these functions.
Now it adds those
functions for
any too many relationship, any
time you have a too many var
like tweets, it's going to add
these functions automatically
It actually put it in its own
little extension, this file
in the extensions.
has two extensions in it,
both through TwitterUser.
Any questions about extensions
there or any of that?
Okay, let's look at tweets
extension real quick.
Couple other things to look
at here that I didn't look
in the other one.
Notice this static func
called fetchRequest?
Put that in your mind.
I'm gonna talk about
that in a few slides.
fetchRequest is a really cool
little static func that will
give you something you
can use to fetch tweets.
And if you call fetchrRquest
on twitter users,
you'll get something to
fetch twitter users.
And we'll talk about all
about fetch in a moment here.
Notice the type of tweeter,
see the tweeter var.
Its type is TwitterUser.
Because of course that's
what the tweeter is,
we control drag between the
tweet and the tweeter user so
that tweeter var is of
course a tweeter user,
not an NSSet, because it's
a two one relationship, okay,
there's only one TwitterUser,
who is my tweeter.
And what about
this @NSManaged?
Okay, @NSManaged I'm just
gonna say it's magic.
It's not really magic.
It's essentially something
that says to the runtime, hey.
When someone
accesses this var,
Core Data's gonna
figure it out for you.
And what Core Data does,
is when you try to say
Tweet.created equals some
date, it gets trapped
at a low level in the runtime
and Core Data swoops in and
does set value for
key for you, okay.
Same thing if you get the
created var, it swoops in and
does value for key and
gets it that way.
But it's all happening at
a low level behind the scenes.
So this extension does satisfy
the extension limitation where
it can't have any storage.
All of the storage for these
vars isn't in the database.
And when you ask for it.
Or when you set it,
it's using its value for
key instead of value for key,
to set it in the database.
Now again, it sets in memory.
You have to save it for
it to actually go out
into the database.
But that what's happening.
All right, so
now that we have these
class so here's some
code that creates a tweets and
sets it's attributes, okay so
let's look at this piece by
piece and see what it does.
The first thing is to create
a tweet, we don't have to do
NSEntityDescription, Entity,
insert Entity for name into
contacts, or whatever that
huge, long terrible thing was-
we can just say, tweet,
parenthesis context.
You just say what context,
which means what database you
want the tweet to put in and
it creates a new tweet.
Okay, just use a normal
initializer for
new things so
that's super cool.
That's one of the coolest
features right there.
Not having to use an
NSEntityDescription thing, so
no more NSEntityDescription,
we'll not have to do that.
And then here,
I'm setting the text to be
140 characters of pure joy.
And I don't have to say set
value 140 characters of pure
joy for key text and have all
these literal strings like
text in there in
this untyped thing.
I just say tweet.text
equals that.
And the same thing here with
created, again, so we don't
even have to worry about
the thing, if we tried to say
tweet.created equals quote
hello, this Swift would say,
no, created is of type Date,
so you can't do that, so
it finds all of our,
it type checks everything,
finds all of our
possible errors.
What about relationships,
okay, setting relationships?
So here I've created another
object, a TwitterUser and
again I just set
TwitterUser with a context,
I'll talk about that argument
in just a second but
I told what database I wanna
create in TwitterUser and
I set my tweet's tweeter
equal to that TwitterUser.
So, it's exactly what you're,
would imagine right?
Just set it equal to Joe.
And what's interesting about
this is that when you set one
side of a relationship,
the other side gets updated
automatically, 100%
of the time.
This is call maintaining
the integrity of the database,
okay?
And Core Data always
maintains database integrity.
So, when you change
one side relationship.
It changes the other.
So, that means for
example if I say tweet.tweeter
equals Joe, then if I went
over to the Joe side and
said hey give me Joe's tweets
and I'm even gonna turn it
into a Swift kind of set
from an NSSet to a set of
tweet because we know that's
what tweets are, right?
Tweets are a set of Tweets, so
I'm gonna as it to do that.
Then I can say, if Joe's tweet
contains that tweet print yes
and of course it is
going to print yes.
Because when I said
tweet.tweeter = joe,
it automatically got
added to joe's tweets.
That make sense?
And same thing the other way.
If I added a tweet
into joe's tweets,
that tweet tweeter would
automatically set to be joe.
Okay?
Both sides will always
point to each other.
You never have to do anything
to make that happen.
tweet.tweeter=joe is exactly
the same as saying joe
dot addToTweets tweet.
Remember addToTweets is one of
those convenience functions
that it created for
us over there.
Now, notice
the argument I used for
the context to create
the Twitter user there.
I didn't say
AppDelegate.viewContext.
I didn't use that same
context bar that I had.
I said
tweet.manageObjectContext.
In other words, I got, I found
out what database the tweet is
in, and I put the Twitter
user in the same database.
And this is a common way
of programming in Core Data
where when you wanna
get a context and
you already have a object
in the database you
ask the object you already
have what context to use.
And you can see that if I ever
change my code to not put this
into this context, to put it
into another context, at least
the Twitter user and the tweet
would always be together
in whatever that context is.
So you can see why I
used the tweets can't
manage object context here to
create that instead of using
the context again.
So, it, it would work to
say context, of course,
but I'm just saying there's a
paradigm of development where
we're gonna try and use
the context of related object.
So they end up in the same
database for sure.
Okay?
All right, so
we can also use dot notation,
because these are just vars.
So when I say tweet.tweeter,
I get a TwitterUser object.
So, of course,
I can say dot name on it and
set it equal to Joe Schmo,
whatever, right?
tweet.tweeter.name =
"Joe Schmo", all right?
No restriction there
on those vars.
All right, remember I told
you about the scalars?
This is that switch I was
telling you about before.
If you don't do this,
then when you say,
if you had an int,
let's say you had retweet
count which was an int
here let's say on Int32.
If you don't switch
this button,
then that's going to be
an NSNumber not an Int32.
But when you click
this switch on,
now that var will
be of type Int32.
So you almost always
want this for numbers.
99.9% of the time, you want
to have this switch on.
Luckily, it's on by default so
you don't even have to
think about it much, but
I just wanted to let
you know about it.
All right, so
now lets talk about deletion.
Okay, now, I want to delete
something from the database.
And that's incredibly easy,
almost too easy because your
data's precious you don't want
to be deleting it to easily,
but you do that by asking
the context to delete the
NSManagedObject, so you can
pass any NSManagedObject
to this method delete and
it will delete it
from the database.
And it could cascade and
delete other things as well
depending on what delete
rule is, all right?
Most of the time by default,
when I delete something,
other things that point to it
get that pointer set to nil.
That's the nullify
delete rule.
Now, when things get deleted
from the database they got
sent this message first,
prepare for deletion.
Okay, and
this is a really good method.
Again, in here you don't
have to do anything
to worry about the other
pointers point to you
that's all fixed by
the delete rule.
But what if you had another
field in your database?
Back to the retweet
count example again.
Let's say I had an int
somewhere in TwitterUser,
which counted
the number of retweets
that this twitter
user had done.
And so if I was deleting
a tweet and it happened to be
a retweet then I need to set
that to be minus equal one.
And here's the perfect
place to do it.
So tweet, and
it's prepared for
deletion saying whoop,
I'm about to be deleted.
I'd better tell my Twitter
user, cuz I'm a retweet,
that he needs to decrement
his retweet count.
So you see why you would
use prepare for deletion?
It's a way to kind of update
other things in the database
when as you're
leaving the database.
All right, so
that's it for deletion.
Next topic, querying,
the most important piece of
this whole database thing.
It's really a waste of time
doing all this stuff if you're
not gonna query, okay?
If you're not gonna make
sophisticated requests for
the information based on
the relationships, etc.
So, to do a query the most
important thing you need to
know is NSFetchRequest,
this class NSFetchRequest.
And NSFetchRequest
encapsulates
what you want from
the database.
So let's talk about
an NSFetchRequest and
how we build one.
So when we're building one,
there's three important
things we need to know.
One, what entity
are we fetching?
Because a FetchRequest can
only Fetch one kind of entity.
You can, there's no such thing
a FetchRequest that will give
you some tweet and
some Twitter user.
No, okay?
A fetch always gives
you all tweets or
all Twitter users, make sense?
So that's the number
one thing,
is we're gonna create
the fetch request.
And it will be a fetch request
or a very specific entity.
And it will only be able
to fetch those entities.
The second thing is is
an array of sort descriptors.
And why do we want this?
Because when we execute this
fetch it's gonna come back
as an array, okay?
All the matching tweets or
Twitter user will come
back in an array.
And since it's an array,
arrays are not sets,
arrays are ordered and so
we have specify what order
the things are in the arrays.
So we do that with
these sort descriptors.
And finally, we just specify
or what is it that we want,
which tweets do we want, which
Twitter users do we want and
we do that with something
called a predicate.
Okay, so let's dive in and
look at all three
of these things.
This is what it looks like,
kinda top level to
create a fetch request.
Okay, you get a fetch request.
You set the source descriptor
and you set its predicate.
So you get each of
these three parts.
So getting the fetch
request is easy.
We're gonna use that
little static function
that the extension that
I talked about, made for
us called fetchRequest.
Now, this is one of the very
few times when Swift
cannot infer the type
of this return value.
Should've put this in red,
okay?
Because it's so
rare, Swift can almost
always infer things.
But in turns out
NSManagedObject
has a fetchRequest method and
it returns the more generic
kind of fetchRequest and
so when you're getting it,
it doesn't quite know
which one you want.
So when you ask a Tweet for
its fetch request right here,
you have to tell it did you
want the one in Tweet not
the one from its super class?
All right?
And so
say let request equal
NSFetchRequest.
It's a generic type like array
or something like that, right?
This is a fetch request
only for Tweets.
So you say
NSFetchRequest =
Tweet.fetchRequest().
And it knows, of course,
that the only one that
returns an NSFetchRequest for
tweets is the fetchRequest,
and that's Tweet extension.
So now,
you have a fetchRequest,
this is how you get a fetch
request- couldn't be easier.
You just have to remember
to do that static
typing right there.
Okay, now we need
the sortDescriptor, right?
It's got this
array coming back.
What order are they
going to be?
SortDescriptor looks
like this.
You create it with a key.
That is the key,
the attribute in
the database that you want to
sort on, so the screen name or
even the text in the tweet or
the actual name of
the tweeter,
whatever it's gonna be.
This right here,
sortDescriptor,
will be a sort descriptor only
suitable for fetching Twitter
users, because screenName
is a key in Twitter user,
not in tweet, so we're gonna
use this SortDescriptor
in a tweet request.
And I say that because
on the previous slide,
I just showed you how to make
a fetch request for a tweet.
Anyway, I should just, that
should have been Twitter user.
But anyway, so
this is a Twitter user.
SortDescriptor.
And notice it has ascending or
descending like us A to Z or
Z to A and then it has
this argument selector and
this one creates
some confusion.
But really this
selector just says,
what method am I gonna use to
compare items to do the sort.
All right now, you don't even
have to specify the selector
if you don't want to and for
almost all data types,
numbers,
dates, it's going to use
a method called compare, okay.
Compare returns something
called a comparison result
which is either, it's the
same, it's greater than, or
it's less than.
So, that's what this
compare method does.
And it's implemented by date.
It's implemented by Int32.
It's implemented by double.
It's even implemented
by string.
Okay?
So,
you could just use compare.
But, for strings.
You wanna think a little
bit about what kind
of comparison do you want?
Do you want
case-insensitive compare?
Or you could even use
this special compare,
called
localizedStandardCompare.
This will compare them so
that it is sourced just
like the finder on the Mac.
And what does the finder on
the Mac do that's different
than case insensitive?
Well, there's a lot of issues
with things like diacritic
marks, and you know,
things in your local language
where things sort differently,
depending on what language
you're in, what locale it is.
You'd, you sometimes you
ignore the diacritics,
like accent marks.
Sometimes they mean something.
And, so localized standard
compare is a special compare
for strings, that knows
how to do that, okay?
And this is very commonly the
one we will use for strings.
When we're gonna show
something in our UI,
maybe this array of thing for
fetching,
we're gonna put it in the UI.
We would want it
to be in order,
this localizedStandardCompare.
You notice that it's
an NSString dot method.
It's not
String.localizedStandardComp-
that's because this has to be
an Objective-C visible method.
are.
And
And you need
the NSString version.
So basically you're going
to say NSString dot, and
you can go look, search for
compare in NSString or string,
because a string implements
them all as well but
you need NSString dot and
then the name of the method.
And you can search, and
there is case insensitive and
the standard compare and then
the regular compare and etc.
Now one other thing
about this is that,
these methods some of
them are special in that,
it does to compare on
the database side, okay.
Using SQL to do it,
see what I'm saying?
It's not actually bringing
all the data over.
Calling this method
on every string, and
doing some kind of
quicksort or something.
It's using super powerful
sorting mechanisms that
are built into an SQL
database, okay.
So, in fact, all of the
NSString ones will do that.
Okay, so
they're super duper efficient.
Now, if you wanted to use
your own compare though,
it's not gonna be efficient.
Because it is gonna have to
bring all the data from the
database into your memory so
it can run your little
method over it.
So I strongly recommend
against using your
own selector here.
I would use
the standard selectors.
If you're gonna use
your own selector
it's gotta be on
a pretty small dataset.
Cuz it's not gonna
be very efficient.
Notice that when we
do the fetch request,
we don't just give it
a sort descriptor,
we give it an array
of sort descriptors.
That's the old sort by last
name, and then first name.
Right?
So if
we have 12 Smiths in there,
we'll sort them and
the Smiths will be
in the right spot.
And then all of the first
names of the Smiths
will be in order by that.
So we can have as many of
these sub sort by the one
thing, sub sort by
the next thing,
sub sort by the next thing.
Basically, we can break ties
with subsequent sorting and
that's why we give an array
of sort descriptors.
Okay, so,
that's the fetch request and
its sort descriptors and
now the predicate.
Okay, the predicate is the
guts of saying which tweets do
we want.
Which Twitter
users do we want?
We create them with kind
of interesting API.
It looks a lot like
printf from C.
NSPredicate format colon,
and then a string.
And the string is
a format string.
And again,
looks a lot like printf.
So the best way to explain
this is probably by example.
But the way you're gonna
learn this is you're gonna go
read the documentation for
NSPredicate, you've got to go
read that documentation,
in its class documentation,
there's gonna be a link that
says, creating predicates,
or something like that, click
on that, and go there, and
learn all the things you can
put in this format string,
cuz it's all very specific to
doing database queries, but
I'll show you some examples,
so
you get an idea of
what's going on here.
So here's the first one,
let's have the search
string called foo.
All these searches then
I'm gonna do right here
are tweet searches.
These are for predicates for
searching for a tweet.
So first, I'm gonna find
all the tweets whose text,
the actual tweet, the 140
characters of pure joy or
whatever, contains
case sensitive.
Case insensitively.
That's what [c] means.
%@.
%@ is a substitution variable,
and I have to give
its value at the end.
And so I'm substituting
search string.
Okay, note that I can't say,
text contains foo.
I have to say,
text contains %@ and then.
Put something at
the end there.
Okay, so
that's an obvious one,
I'm searching for all my
tweets that contain foo.
How about this one?
I want all the tweets
whose tweeter equals %@.
I'm going to put Joe in there
as the substitution variable
and created after some
date that I create.
See that?
I'm using greater
than to do that.
And I'm doing && for and,
you can also use the word and
there.
Okay?
So that's all gonna be
the tweets created by
Joe since that date.
You're starting to see the
power of building the query
into the database, right?
If I had thousands of tweets,
it'd be really easy to find
the ones since yesterday,
for example.
I'll show you that
in a second here.
Aand then I can also though,
search through dot notation,
on other fields,
in other entities, but
this tweeter.screenName equals
percent @ sign%@ with CS193P,
that's still searching for
tweets.
That's searching for
tweets whose tweeter's
screen name is CS193P.
Do you see what
it's doing there?
This is still
a tweet predicate.
This is not a twitter
user predicate.
Okay?
So here's a different
predicate.
This one is for Twitter user.
So here I'm searching for
all the Twitter users
Okay?
who has a Tweet whose
text contains foo.
Okay?
So it even knows how
to do a pluralistic
search right here where you've
got tweets dot text that means
all the tweets, texts and
doing contains and
we can do [c] if
we wanted foo.
So that's a twitter user
search right there.
the twitter users who have
tweeted anything that includes
We're looking for
foo, again a powerful search,
really easy to express.
Question.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> So the question,
does it infer this from
the name of the variable,
it's not inferring it,
it's actually using the name
of the attribute tweets
right there and the name of
the attribute text and it's
building a SQL statement that
will go and do this fetch.
Okay now it's doing all
that underneath the covers,
we don't care how,
but it's doing it.
Yeah, compound predicate.
You can build a compound
predicate like an and
predicate or an or predicate.
You could put or or
and in the string, or
you could create separate
predicates and and
them together by creating
an NSCompoundPredicate.
And predicate with
sub-predicates, and
just given an array
of predicates and
it ands them together.
Why would you ever want to do
this versus just putting and
or, or in there?
Well, maybe you're computing
what the predicates are,
based on some, depending on
what the user clicked on or
something, you're
computing it, and
so you want to add these
things you computed together.
All right, there's also
function predicates.
Now these are super
powerful predicates,
and you don't need these for
your homework, so
don't worry too much about
these, but they're cool.
You can even say, you have
a search like this one,
tweets.@count > 5,
this is a Twitter user search,
that finds
all the Twitter users who have
more than 5 Tweets, okay?
So, @count is actually
running, kind of a function in
the database, to go count
the number of Tweets that
the Twitter user has.
So, again, you'll see all
of this when you go look at
the NSPredicate documentation,
it's incredibly powerful,
you can see you barely have to
type anything in as the format
string, and you get these
really powerful searches.
All right, so let's put it
all together now to create
our fetch request, okay.
I'm gonna create,
in this case,
a Twitter user fetch request.
So I'm saying
a FetchRequest =
TwitterUser.fetchRequest(),
then I'm gonna
create a time which
was yesterday,
it's actually not,
it's 24 hours ago.
Time interval since now,
minus 24 times 60 times 60,
that's 24 hours ago, and
I'm creating a predicate
that says, find me any Twitter
users that have a Tweet that's
created before yesterday,
or since yesterday I guess,
yes, created is greater
than yesterday.
So I'm finding all the Twitter
users who have created Tweets
in the last twenty-four hours,
that's what this one does.
So any is a special term
that means match any
of these things, and
these things are Tweets that
are created since yesterday.
And I'm gonna sort the result
by the actual name,
the real name of
the Twitter user.
So I'm just doing
sortDescriptor, key of name,
ascending true, I'm not
specifying a selector, so
I'm gonna get kind of
the default comparison.
Okay, that's it, so that's how
you create a fetch request.
Now, since I have a fetch
request, how do I make it go?
Give me those Tweets,
give me those Twitter users.
We do that with the very
simple method in context, so
we ask the context to do the
fetch, and it will go out and
return an array of
all those things,
sorted in the way the fetch
request says to sort them.
Okay, simple as that.
The only thing not so
simple, it throws, okay?
Just like context save throws,
context execute also throws.
So, you could put in
a try question mark,
in that case, if the execute
fails, and usually it's gonna
fail because your predicate
is wrong, or something.
Like your predicate just makes
no sense then you could fail.
If it's gonna fail,
you're gonna get back nil,
if you do try question mark,
remember that's what try
question mark means.
It means try this, and
if it fails, give back nil.
But it if doesn't fail,
then you're gonna get
an optional array.
And that array is
gonna be empty,
if it couldn't find anything
that matches your request, or,
it's gonna be full of objects,
okay?
Tweets, or Twitter users,
an array of tweets, or
an array of Twitter users,
at least that's what it's
gonna look like to you,
it's not quite that,
looks like it, all right?
That's the result you're
gonna get back, so, again,
super simple querying.
Now, you might be a little
scared of doing this request,
what if it's matches
a million things, okay?
Are you gonna get a million
Tweets back in one
request like this?
The answer is no.
This array that you get back
is really super smart array.
It doesn't actually bring
the data in from the database,
until you start asking for
it, okay?
So until I ask for
the Twitter user,
a certain Twitter
user's information,
the Twitter user's name, the
Twitter user's screen name,
the Twitter user did not get
faulted from the database.
This is called faulting, okay?
And so, these objects,
you can imagine,
they're kind of shells,
empty shells.
And until you crack
open the shell and
start looking inside,
it doesn't actually
get the data for you.
And the reason this
matters to you is,
if you go in the debugger,
or you do a print statement,
like this one where you say,
for user in recentTweeters
fetched user whatever,
when you print that out,
it's not gonna print the,
a Tweeter user object,
it's gonna print some
kind of faulting shel.
Because you haven't
actually asked for
any of the data inside
that thing yet, so
it hasn't faulted yet.
But if you say, for
user in recentTweeters and
say fetched user named, and
now you say user.name, now you
are faulting this object in.
In fact, this for
loop would fault all these
objects in to memory.
Okay, fetch them all,
cuz you're asking for
the name of every single one.
Boom, fault, fault, fault,
they're all coming in.
Now, it doesn't do it one by
one, it faults in batches,
it's really high performance,
so,
you know,
don't worry about that.
But just, I just don't
want you to be surprised
when you go in
the debugger and
you're like, I printed out
this Twitter, user and
there's no screen name,
what's going on?
Well, it hasn't faulted it in.
In fact,
the debugger you could say,
print the user.name,
and it would fault it in,
okay, give it to you.
All right, I told you I was
gonna talk about Core Data
thread safety, so here it is.
NSManagedObjectContext,
the context thing,
that thing that you're
sending executes to,
that thing that you're hitting
save, the things that you're
using to create Tweet,
Tweet, subcontext,
colon whatever, that handle on
database is not thread safe.
A context can only
be used on the queue
that it was created on,
period.
If you past a context
to another queue,
like you tried to
dispatch off to some
global concurrent queue, and
you pasted the context, or
even just pasted a Tweet,
okay, that's not gonna work,
cuz that Tweet was created
on this other context.
So in fact,
not only the context,
but everything that you
create on that context
has to all be done
in the same queue.
So now you're
probably thinking,
well how the heck do I
do multithreading then?
Cuz a database especially,
you can imagine, for
temple one to load your
database off the main queue,
cuz you, you might be loading
lots and lots of things.
Now your queries,
your probably gonna do those
on the main queue because,
the user's looking
at that information.
You want it to be
highly responsive.
Okay, it's probably worth,
and core data is super fast,
especially with queries.
So, you could probably do
that on the main queue.
But loading it up,
you probably don't
want to do that.
All right, so,
how do we do multithreading?
Although that we do
multithreading in Core Data,
is each database can have
multiple contexts, okay?
So, the database underneath,
is multithreaded,
it can have multiple
contexts writing to it.
Okay, completely
different context,
writing to the same database,
in different queue's even, so
it's fully multithreaded.
So that means we had to have
a context for every queue.
Whatever queue we're going
to access the database,
we have to a context
in every queue.
Now I'm gonna show you how
to create a context, or
on another queue, so
you can do something with
that queue in a second here.
But first I want to talk
about this important
method in context
called performBlock.
performBlock just
takes a closure,
a closure that
takes no arguments,
returns no arguments, and
it will ensure, this is
an insurance method, it will
ensure that everything inside
that closure happens on the
right queue for that context.
Okay, so this,
don't get confused,
this method does not dispatch,
you know,
cause background thrading,
this is just making sure that,
that closure executes
on the right queue.
So this is a way that
you can kind of be safe.
And some might argue you
should put performBlock around
every single call to every
Core Data thing you ever do,
because that will ensure that
you'll never have a problem
where you're accessing
the context not on it's queue.
Okay, it accidentally,
you got some bad code.
Now, that might be a little
bit overkill especially if
you're mostly using
the main queue anyway, and
you really, maybe you only
use background queues for
this tiny little bit of
processing on the side.
It's not like you have
the tons context and
lots of different queues
all going at each other.
So, it might be overkill.
But if you're doing
anything where you have,
truly have multiple context
on multiple queues and
they're access and things,
this is a good way to be safe.
Okay, so all this does is it
makes it so you are safe.
The code inside that block
will be executed on the proper
queue for that context.
Even if it has to dispatch,
it will do it if it has to.
If it doesn't
have to dispatch,
if you're on the right queue,
it'll just execute it, fine.
But if you're on the wrong
queue right now and
you execute this,
it will dispatch it
to the right queue.
There's also
performBlockAndWait,
which will get it on
the right queue and
wait until it's done, and
then continue in your queue.
Okay, but this doesn't
really talk about,
how do I get another context
in a different thread, right?
I wanna do some code
on another thread.
Where do I get a context?
The only context I know how to
get right now is viewContext.
That's the main
queue's context,
that's the only
only one I can get.
Okay, well, you're gonna
use this really cool method
in persistentContainer.
This is new in iOS 10 and
a really cool method,
super cool.
It makes it really easy to
do background process on
Core Data.
It's called
performBackgroundTask.
Remember, this is a function
on persistentContainer that
you get from the AppDelegate.
And this takes a closure.
This closure has one argument,
the argument is a context.
And that context is
appropriate for use
on this other thread that this
is going to create for you.
So this performBackgroundTask
finds another queue,
not the main queue,
some other queue.
And it creates a context
in that other queue, and it
executes your closure on that
other queue in the background.
Now, it's
a convenience method.
So if you really needed
to control the quality of
service, for example, the
queue and all the, okay, well,
you can't use this.
But 99.99% of the time,
whatever quality of
service that queue is
getting is the right one for
Core Data cuz Core Data
knows its business.
So you're gonna do it.
Now, inside this closure
couple of things really
be careful of.
One, never use
viewContext in here.
Do you see why that would
be horrendously bad to
use viewContext
inside this closure?
Because this closure by
definition is not executing on
the main queue.
By definition this
closure is on a separate
queue on a background queue.
That's the whole
point of this thing,
is to put this thing
on another queue.
So never use
viewContext in there,
that's why it's in red, okay?
The second thing is don't
forget to save this context.
If you do a whole bunch
of stuff in here and
you don't save,
you just did for
nothing cuz you did in memory.
And then this block went away,
you're never gonna get that
context back again,
that data is lost.
Which all gonna leave the heap
and then nothing ever happens.
It never gonna get
committed to the database.
So, don't forget to
save before you leave.
Now, when you save,
it will push it down
to the database and
your other context like your
viewContext will see it, okay?
And so these two contexts, the
one that's happening on this
background and
the viewContext.
They're working on
the same database, so
when this one saves,
boom this guys is gonna
start seeing those changes.
I'm gonna talk a little bit
how react to seeing those
changes in a minute here.
Okay, so,
everyone understand this?
Cuz you're gonna have to
do this in assignment five.
And I want you to do all your
loading off the main queue,
and all your fetching
on the main queue.
All right, Core Data is huge.
Huge.
I can't cover it all.
It's got optimistic locking,
for
those of you that
know about database.
It's got optimistic locking
and all that database stuff.
It has full undo, redo,
which is incredible.
It obviously knows how to
roll back unsaved changes.
Okay, if you have
changes in memory and
you want to roll
some of them back,
you can do that
before you save.
It knows about staleness,
like, if I make a fetch,
how long before I really wanna
fetch it again because I don't
trust that the data
hasn't changed, right?
How long it takes for
the data to get stale.
And a lot of other
things in the Core Data.
So, I can't cover it all,
there's not enough
time to do that.
Cuz we're trying to talk about
a whole another topic about
But you'll want to check the
documentation, you won't need
Core Data here.
anything else of this stuff to
do your homeworks, of course,
I'm just trying to get
you started with this.
But you need to know that this
stuff is in there, so that
one day when you go out and do
some significant iOS database
stuff, you'll know that these
features are out there.
All right, the next topic here
is Core Data and UITableView.
As you can imagine, this is a
marriage made in heaven, okay?
Because you got this database,
got all this big data
sets in there and
what is the UI we use to
show big data sets in iOS?
UITableView.
Okay, UITableView is great
at showing arbitrary large
data sets in our
arbitrary UIs, right?
We can do custom
table view cell,
we can do anything UI we want.
So, this is so common that
Apple has invented this very
important class called
NSFetchedResultsController.
This is not a viewController,
okay?
This is a controller that
controls Core Data and
UITableView talking together,
but it's not in its fetch
results view controller, okay?
And all this
NSFetchedResultsController
does is it hooks up an
NSFetchRequest that you create
to a UITableView.
And it hooks them up in such
a strong way that if anything
changes in the database that
would cause that fetch request
to return different results,
it updates the table
automatically, you don't
have to do anything.
So this is an active
live hookup between
the NSFetchRequest and
the TableView, okay?
Even if some other context are
changing the data, it doesn't
matter, it's always keeping
that TableView up to date.
So I'm gonna talk
about how we do this,
how we use
an NSFetchedResultsController.
I'm even gonna provide you
some kind of free code
to do some of it.
You'll have to type in a
little bit of the rest of it.
But it's,
it's pretty easy to do.
So how fundamentally does
NSFetchedResultsController
work?
Two ways, one,
it has a delegate and
that delegate you set to be
your UITableViewController.
And whenever the
FetchResultsController sees
something happening
in the database that would
affect that fetchRequest,
it tells the table view
controller, hey, do this,
add this row, add a section,
reload this row, whatever,
it uses UITableView primitives
to update the table, okay?
I'm gonna show you,
I'm gonna give you the code
that does that part of it,
that implements the
NSFetchedResultsController's
delegate, okay, so
that's one way it does it.
The other way that
the NSFetchedResultsController
works is that it provides
implementation for
all of your UITableView data
sources methods, right?
Because the contents
of your table
are coming out
of the database,
so NSFetchedResultsController
lets you know all of them, how
many sections, how many rows
and sections all that stuff.
In fact,
this is what it looks like,
this is the implementation
that you're gonna put in to
your controller when you have
fetchedResultsController.
The first thing you're gonna
do is you're gonna create a
fetchedResultsController, and
I'm gonna show you how
to do that in a moment.
And so you're always
gonna have a var called
fetchedResultsController, and
it's gonna be of type
NSFetchedResultsController.
And when you have that var,
now you can implement your
sections, number of sections
in TableView by saying return
fetchedResultsController
.sections.count, okay?
Those are a lot of
optionals in there, so
we'll default to one section.
And then to get the number
of rows in a section,
you're just gonna say the,
you're gonna get
the sections first by saying
fetchedResultsController?.sec-
tions.
And as long as you have some
sections, sections.count
greater than zero, then you're
gonna return the sections in
that section that's passed
to you number of objects.
Okay, so that code, that's it,
that's all of your, those two
methods, that's the entire
implementation if you're using
a fetchedResultsController,
okay?
And then of course,
there's cellForRowAt, okay,
you gotta implement that,
that one too,
you're gonna use
fetchedResultsController.
And the most important thing
about cellForRowAt is you need
to know what's at that row,
which thing in my database is
at that row in that
section in my table.
And you get that by asking the
fetchedResultsController with
this method objectAtIndexPath.
So you just say
fetchedResultsController,
give me the object, and that
object is gonna be a tweet, or
a Twitter user, or
whatever, some entity.
Give me an object
at the index path
that cellForRowAt
indexPath is asking me for.
So now I have the Twitter
user or the tweet,
I can easily load up my UI.
You know, pass it off to my
UI, custom UITableView cell,
or if I have a subtitle cell,
just take a couple of
things out of there and
put it in the text label
in the detailed text label,
you see what I'm saying?
But you can see that
the fetchedResultsController,
that code in yellow right
there in the middle of
cellForRowAt indexPath,
that's doing all the work
to figure out what tweet or
what Twitter user is at this
row in the table, okay?
So those code on
the last slide and
the code on this slide, you'll
have to type that code in any
time you're using
an NSFetchedResultsController.
Now, on the previous slide,
one of the things was var
fetchedResultsController
equals something.
So now let's talk
about how we create
a fetchedResultsController,
okay?
So this is what
the initializer for
NSFetchedResultsController
looks like here.
It takes a request, a context.
Obviously, it doesn't
know what database
we're fetching in.
And then it's got
a sectionNameKeyPath.
That sectionNameKeyPath
is the var in
that entity that,
whose value is a string,
which is the title of
the section it's in, okay?
That's how you do sections
with fetchedResultsController.
You just have to, and you
might have to invent this or
even calculate this.
But all of your tweets or all
your Twitter users, if they're
gonna be in sections,
they all have to have a var,
which is a string, which is
the section they're in, okay,
the name of the section
they're in.
And as long as they have that,
then the fetchedResults will,
will make the sections and
put them all in there
in the right section.
And we'll talk about
cacheName in a second here.
So we have to create
a fetchRequest to put in here.
So here's an example of
creating a fetchRequest for
tweets, right?
So you recognize that
first line there,
creating a fetchRequest for
tweets.
And I'm gonna sort by when
the tweets were created, okay,
when the tweet
was tweeted out.
And I'm gonna look for all the
tweets whose tweeter's name
equals some name,
the name, okay?
So it's gonna get all
those tweets, and
I'm gonna set that request
as the first argument there,
to NSFetchedResultsController.
By the way, notice
NSFetchedResultsController is
also a generic type, and
NSFetchedResultsController can
only control fetches for
a certain type.
So you have to say what type,
okay, what type of entity that
your FetchController is doing,
and these are the same type of
things that are in
the rows of your table.
Now that cacheName at
the bottom is interesting.
That is actually going to
permanently cache the results.
it's gonna get the results
out of the database and
In other words,
store on disk the result
in some internal format.
And that's cool, and
that storage, by the way,
if you quit your app and
come back,
it will still use that cache,
so it's quite efficient.
But you have to be
a little bit careful.
You cannot change anything
about your request.
As soon as you change anything
about your request, like
the name, the tweeter.name
that you're searching for, or
what you're sorting by,
or anything.
Now that cache is invalid, and
you'll have to invalidate that
cache, okay, and there's an
API in there for doing that.
You can pass nil there if you
don't wanna do the caching,
which for most reasonable
sized datasets perfectly fine,
you don't really
need the caching.
But I just wanna emphasize
that if you change your
request, your cache
is now invalid.
And about that section key
thing, something to be careful
about there, too, is that
whatever your sortDescriptors
say that your rows would
sort in, that has to be
exactly the same order that
your sections was sorted in.
In other words,
the FetchedResultsController
doesn't know how to
like move things around
because they sort out of
order of their sections.
That's why a lot of times
that we're doing sections,
the first sortDescriptor will
be sort by the section key
name var, right?
And then the second one
will be sort by what we
really wanna sort by,
because we have to make sure
that our entire table is
sorted in section order.
You see why?
Cuz otherwise it's just weird,
things would all be
in the wrong places.
So
keyThatSaysWhichAttributeIsTh-
eSectionName has to sort
in the same order as your
sortDescriptors.
Okay, now, I told you that
NSFetchedResultsController
watches Core Data.
It sees changes happening in
there, and it updates it.
And it does that with
its delegate, okay?
Its delegate wants
to be the tableView,
be the tableViewController,
rather.
Cuz it's gonna tell
the tableViewController, and
it sends messages like this.
So this is a typical
NSFetchedResultsController
delegate method.
Controller did change add
indexPath for change type, and
here's the new indexPath.
Okay, and these change
types might be deleted or
inserted or
modified or whatever.
Now, you have to put the code
in there that would call
the right methods on the
tableView to get the sections
inserted or deleted or
rows added or whatever.
But I'm gonna give you that
code for free, okay, and
the demo that I'm
gonna do on Wednesday,
I'm gonna have a class called
fetchedResultsTableViewContro-
ller, which is
gonna be a class.
And you can make that to
be the super class of your
UITableViewController.
And you'll just inherit
this implementation of
the delegate, okay?
Yes, cuz that's
what I just said.
Okay, so when you're using
core data in UITableView,
the things to remember are,
you're going to subclass
fetchedResultsTableViewContro-
ller,
the thing I'm gonna give you,
so that you implement
NSFetchedResultsController
delegate.
You're going to add a var to
your UITableViewController
called
fetchedResultsController, and
you're gonna set
its value to be
an NSFetchedResultsController
with the fetchRequest that you
want, okay, that you want
to populate your table.
Then you're gonna implement
your UITableView data source
methods using
fetchedResultsController var
methods, just like I
showed you in the slides,
character for character,
you can use the exact same
things that are on the slide.
Okay, and then it's all gonna
magically work, all you'll
have to do is inside your
cellForRowAt indexPath,
you'll have the object,
the tweet,
or the Twitter user, you
just gotta load up your UI.
After you have
all this set up,
then you can proceed to using
the fetchedResultsController
in your tableViewController.
First thing you have to
do is perform fetch on
the fetchedResultsController.
That will cause it to go out
and do your NSFetchRequest,
basically.
It's not gonna pull
all the data over, but
it's going to basically bring
over, do the same thing as if
you had executed
the fetchRequest yourself, and
then you're gonna wanna do
tableView View.reloadData.
And that's because you want
all of your datasource
methods to be called, and you
know that we've implemented
all of them in terms of our
fetch results controller as
showed on the previous
slides there.
And the only other thing
you want to remember to do
is set your fetch results
controller's delegate to be
yourself and, again, we use
that fetch results table view
controller code that added
the delegate methods for
the fetch results controller
to the UITableView controller
until we can do all the things
that is necessary to
be a fetchedResultsController
delegate.
And what that buys you is
that anytime in the database
changes that would affect
the NSFetchedRequest
that you wired up to your
fetchedResultsController.
Then, it will use that
delegate to ask the table view
to update the rows or
sections,
whatever happened to change.
So let me talk a little bit
about what's coming up here,
on Wednesday, I'm gonna do a
big demo that shows you all of
this stuff, as usual.
Assignment five is
going out on Wednesday,
it'll be due
the next Wednesday.
It's going to be to add Core
Data stuff to your Smashtag.
On Friday,
very relevant section.
It's using CloudKit
to do a database.
Okay?
Now, Core Data and CloudKit,
what, what are they,
how are they related?
Well, Core Data is for
doing things that you would do
with a relational database,
these powerful queries and
searches and things like that.
Cloud Kit is, what if you
wanted to have a database
on the network,
in the cloud, okay?
A network that's being shared
between multiple people or
even by a single
person on multiple,
on multiple of their devices,
or whatever.
So there quite different in
the way they approach things.
In Core Data, we do the schema
using this visual mapper.
In CloudKit, it's essentially
schema on the fly.
As you start saving vars,
it starts making this
schema up for you, so
it's a very different kind
of way of thinking about.
You don't think of it from
a scheme of design point.
In advance, there's kind of
more organic as you go and
also you don't have to,
you know, kind of create this
whole scheme of front and
describe it, you can describe
it as you use it essentially.
So it's a very interesting
comparison between the two.
I wish I had time
to do CloudKit.
Last quarter,
I had the extra lectures.
I was able to do CloudKit
as a whole lecture but,
we'll have to do it as
a Friday section this week so,
don't miss that.
Next Monday is a holiday.
So no lecture and
then next Wednesday,
I'm gonna go over
your requirements for
the final project,
which are required to do.
And I'm also gonna have a
lecture as well on AutoLayout.
We'll finally get
to Autolayout and
how do that Autolayout stuff.
I'd say, I just wanted
to show you that and
I will see you
all on Wednesday.
>> For more please visit
us on Stanford.edu.