[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to
Standford CS 193P,
Developing Applications for
iOS, Winter of 2017.
This is lecture number 12, and
today our topic is
going to be Autolayout.
I'm going to review a little
bit of what we already know
about Autolayout and
then move onto a very
important part of auto layout
called size classes then we'll
demo everything as usual.
What have you seen in
Autolayout already?
Well, you know about
the dash blue lines.
When you drag things out and
move them around and
you make those dash blue lines
appear you know that it helps
Xcode when you wanna do Reset
to Suggested Constraints.
And you know that
sometimes Reset to
Suggested Constraints doesn't
really do what you want.
It really only works if those
blue lines just unambiguously
obviously.
That's what you wanted.
But you also know that
after you do something,
especially after you do reset
to suggest the constraints,
you can go over to
the Size Inspector and
click on any of the views
in your UI and you
can look at the constraints
and it shows you them.
You can even kind of hover
over them with the mouse and
they will show them
on the screen.
Highlight them, etc.
So that's a good tool to
know what's going on.
You also know that you can
click on the constraint
itself.
The little I beams or
whatever,
you can click on them and
bring up inspector on them and
you can see a lot of detail:
what the constants are,
what's on either end of them,
in other words what
the constraints, the two
things being involved and
constrained are, so
you already know that as well.
You also know about
control dragging
to edges, we did a lot of
control dragging to the edge
to make our UI kinda use
up all the space but
you also saw a little bit of
a hint in the smashtag demo
that you can actually control
drag between any two views.
This is the key thing
about Autolayout.
It sets constraints really
between any two views.
There's really almost
no restriction
between the things you
can set constraints.
Again so we'll see that in
the demo a little bit today.
Now in addition to control
dragging to set up these
constraints between things,
you can also select them.
I select one view or
select a couple of views.
And there's a couple little
menus in the corner down
there the pin menu or
the align menu and
then this other kinda generic
menu that has a lot of random
things you can set
constraints for.
And we'll use that
today as well, so
you can see that different
way of doing it.
Pretty much everything
in there you can do with
Ctrl+drag, but sometimes
it's hard to do Ctrl+drag.
Maybe the views are very
close together, or
they're really near the edge,
or they're overlapping
some other view.
And so when that starts
to be a problem, you can
click on them to select,
either using the control shift
click to drill down if
things are overlapping, or
maybe use the document outline
to select it, and then go to
these menus to apply whatever
constraints that you want.
Now the document outline,
we've showed briefly and
I'll show it again today,
is really the go to place to
resolve problems
with constraints.
Both constraints that are
insufficient, in other words
you, you haven't put enough
constraints on a view for
the Xcode to or the IOS to
know where the thing goes.
Or constraints that conflict.
Maybe you put two
constraints on a views
that is like they're pulling
against each other and
IOS doesn't know what to do.
So the document outline is
the place to go to resolve
all that stuff and we'll
see that in the demo today.
Now one thing to understand
about autolayout is it takes
experience to master it.
There's a lot of degrees
of freedom there with those
constraints in terms
of how you can
constrain views relative
to each other and
there's just no substitute for
experience.
You just have to do it.
So don't expect that after
you see the demo today.
And after what you've seen
earlier in the course.
Like, "now I am an auto
layout master".
You will have to be designing
a lot of user interfaces.
Lining up a lot of edges.
Making things the same widths,
those kinds of things.
Until you learn kind of
the tools enough to be a good
auto layout master.
But once you master it,
it can be really really super
powerful as you can see.
Autolayout is also
doable from code.
In other words,
there is a class and
it's layout constraint and
it has all the functionality
is in the story board.
We rarely use it
because we can do
pretty much anything
from a story board.
But I'm not gonna have
time to teach it.
Obviously I have to be
selective about what
I can show you in this
limited time available.
But you can do some pretty
tricky things in code that
you can't do in storyboard,
but they're pretty, I don't
want to say advanced, but they
are, let's say fairly obscure.
And so, if you're interested
in pursuing that, maybe for
your final project, or
something, you can just start
with NSLayout constraint in
the documentation, and
kind of go from there.
Let's talk a little about
rotation, auto rotation.
We know that when we rotate,
that's one of the biggest
times that autolayout has to
kick in and figure out where
things go because things
have dramatically changed.
They're much wider than they
are tall now or vice versa.
And sometimes unfortunately,
that rotation causes such
a dramatic change in your UI
that you want to actually move
views around in a way that you
just can't say by align these
edges, make these the same
width, keep this separation,
those kinds of things.
You actually want to pick
them up and move them.
And actually, a great example
of that is our calculator.
Our calculator, at least,
not your calculator but
the calculator we last saw
in demo had 20 buttons, and
we had it as four across and
five down.
And that made a lot
of sense because
in portrait mode we had
a lot of vertical space and
not a lot of horizontal space,
so we kinda went for the.
The five high, four wide.
But when we switch to
landscape, now it's not so
good, cuz all of the buttons
are squished down.
They're really wide and thin.
It would be much better if
when we get to landscape,
we could go to five across and
four down because we
have a lot less space.
Now, can you imagine trying
to do a control drag to
make that happen is
basically impossible.
It can't be done.
But it's possible to do
with a very important
feature which I'm gonna talk
about in a moment here.
Now, this kind of
rotation stuff is,
the problem where your view
changes from landscape
to portrait and you wanna
move all the views around
can happen in other
situations too.
Imagine that you have an MVC
that wants to look good in
Landscape, but also wants to
look good when it's the master
of a Split View Controller.
The master of a Split View
Controller kind of looks likes
it's in portrait, so
even though you're on an iPad,
let's say,
sometimes you have tall and
skinny, just like what
you have on an iPhone.
So it's not just iPhone issue
only or rotation issue only.
So, the solution to all this
is called size classes.
Now, Apple has chosen to take
an approach to dealing with
this which is fairly simple.
Which is a pretty good idea
because you could imagine
a very complicated solution
that tries to, basically, take
into effect every possible
geometry and every size.
You could end up writing a lot
of code or a massive number
of auto layout constraints
to make it work.
So they've boiled it down
to this very simple system
where they talk about size
classes and a view or
a view controller at any
given time exists with
a certain size class.
Both in the horizontal
direction and
the vertical direction.
And the only two values that
the size class can have is
compact or regular.
So regular is regular sized,
and
compact means that you're
constrained in that direction.
Let's look at all
our devices and
see when they're constrained
in either compact
in either height or width, and
when they're just regular.
Let's talk about the iPhone
first the iPhone in portraits
is regular in height,
plenty of height, but
it's compact in width.
It's kinda constrained in
width in that circumstance.
When you switch to landscape,
maybe surprisingly,
iPhones are compact in both
directions because even though
when you go to landscape,
it gets quite a bit wider,
it's still not that wide.
Okay, it's not
wide like an iPad.
It's still somewhat
constrained, so
they've decided
to make landscape
iPhone be compact
in both directions.
So in portrait it's regular in
height and compact in width.
But in Landscape, it's
compacted both directions.
We will encounter into it but
just see it works
out quite nicely.
Now, the iPhone +s, the 6+ and
the 7+,
those are a little different.
They're still
compact in width.
And regular in height
in portrait but
when you go to landscape,
since those iPhone
pluses are so
big, that they can actually
start showing that kind of
horizontal UI just like it
was an iPad or something.
So they are regular in
width in landscape mode.
iPhone is compact in both.
The iPhone Plus, still compact
in height, in landscape, but
it's regular in width.
Then the iPad.
Since it's huge, is always
regular in both dimensions.
Both width and height is
always irregular, but
that's only for
new controllers that are
taking over the whole screen.
If your view controller,
like I said in the master
of a split view,
you're compact width,
regular height.
Or if your multi-tasking MVC
that comes out from the right,
you all know about
multi-tasking
in the iPad hopefully.
You can drag anything
out from the right and
pick another app, and have two
apps running side by side.
Well, when you pull
that thing out,
that's also gonna be a compact
width, regular height.
Now this whole mechanism
of Compact and Regular in
size classes, of course, it's
built-in for devices as I've
described above here, but
it's also extensible.
So if you were to write your
own thing where an MVC was
embedded inside another MVC.
You could set or
communicate whether that
MVC is compact or regular.
In each of width and
height and kind of send
a message to the MVC.
Hey I've constrained
your height so
make sure you deal with that.
Or I've constrained
your width.
And so, it can react to it.
Now, again, I'm not gonna
have time to talk about that
in detail, but there is this
bar called trait collection
which you can look at
in a view controller.
And it will tell you what
your current size class is,
both horizontally and
vertically.
And there's a mechanism for
passing that along down to sub
MVCs and views and things.
We have the size classes,
compact width and
regular width, compact
height and regular height,
which makes for four different
combinations right here and
again, compact width and
height is iPhones in
landscape but not plus ones.
Compact height and
regular width is the iPhone
plus only in landscape.
Regular height and compact
width is iPhones in portrait,
both plusses and regular and
also like a split view master.
And then regular regular
is an iPad in portrait or
landscape, the whole thing.
So if we had this normal grid
and we wanted our calculator
to look good in all of them
conceivably we'd have to
write, do four different UIs
for our calculator like this.
When I Have some more
vertical height.
I go five high but
when I'm kind of compacted
I'll go to only four high.
So this would be a bit of a
pain in the neck to have to do
To make it a little easier,
when we are designing,
this.
we also have the concept
of any height or any width.
Now if we do that, now we're
down to only having to do two
things with our calculator.
So anytime we have compact
height and we don't care
what the width is,
we're going to go four high.
Anytime we have
regular height and
we don't care what the width
is, we'll go five high.
So that's reduced the amount
of work we have to do by half.
And actually we can reduce it
even more because we can also
design any any.
This any by the way doesn't
mean any like the Swift
type "any", it just means
any width, any height,
the English word any.
And so we can do our designing
and in fact our default design
in storyboards is to be
designing any width,
any height.
that are the same for the five
wide case or the four wide
case, we can build all
that in the any any mode.
And then only have to do
the stuff that's specific to
the size class being
different in that case.
So, that reduces even more
the design we have to do.
Cuz we're doing most
of our design any any,
and then a little bit to
make the other two work.
So, you can see it in
the calculator here, the only
things I can do in any/any is
the base keyboard there, not
including the buttons that are
either gonna be on the top or
because those depending on
the vertical size class there.
on the side,
And also I can do my
display at the top.
If that's all I can do.
But most of my UI we'll see in
the demo I'll do exactly this.
That's a lot.
Let's jump into that.
To make the demo a little
easier to understand what's
going on here the developer,
here's our calculator.
I actually added a little
bit of code to my
calculator and
I'll show it to you.
This is the calculator
that we've left off.
The last thing we did
in this calculator was
the green square root.
Remember so it was not changed
since then except for this.
In the view controller for
this guy.
I added this blue
code right here.
I added this function
showSizeClasses
which hijacks the display.
You know our blue display on
the top, it hijacks it and
writes in there
what the width and
height size classes are of the
calculator in the moment okay.
And then I just Implemented
a couple of ViewController
life-cycle methods here,
viewDidAppear calls it.
And then,
view will transition to size,
which is what happens
when you rotate.
And I just call this
showSizeClasses there.
I also added a little
extension to
UI user interface size
class to just have it
implement custom
string convertible.
So it implements that
method description.
And just returns compact and
regular.
That's so that I can do this
line of code right here,
where I'm printing
out the size classes.
So, it's not really important
that you understand this.
You'll just notice
that when we run it.
So I'll go ahead and run here.
You're gonna see that that
blue thing is gonna get
taken over to show
you the size class.
It's just cuz when you're
running I want you to be clear
on what size classes we're
doing both horizontally and
vertically.
When we are in, and
this is iPhone 7, So we are in
portrait mode, so you can see
that our width is compact and
our height is regular.
If I rotate, so I'm just
gonna hit the Cmd key here,
rotate, you can see that now
we are width compact and
height compact cuz
we're on the iPhone 7.
If we were on iPhone 7 Plus,
right now it would be width
regular height compact.
So, in the interest of
time I won't run there,
but when we do come to running
it we'll be able to always see
what size class we're in.
So, here is our UI right here.
And there's a couple of things
we can do with size classes
that are actually really,
really simple.
For example, you can click
on certain UI elements,
like a label, and when you go
to the attribute inspector
over here you'll notice that
some of the attributes have
these little pluses.
See that?
Plus, plus?
And down here, plus and plus?
And what these
pluses let you do,
is change these fields
in that size clause.
We can do the any/any.
We can do compact with
compact height any,
any combination we want.
So for example here,
let's go ahead and
have our background color
of our display up here
vary depending on our
height size class.
If we're height compact,
we'll do one thing.
If we're height regular
we'll do another.
So, we do that by pressing
this little plus.
You see when you do that.
And here we can pick
the width that we want.
And since we're varying on
the height I'm just gonna say
any width.
And I'm gonna say height
compact, so this will,
means that this background
that it's gonna,
this variation
it's gonna create,
will only take effect when
the height is compact,
if the height is regular, this
is not going to take effect.
So, I'm gonna add a variation,
you see it added it here,
you see the little hC,
that means height compact all
right, the width is any, so
it doesn't say
anything about width.
And now we can change it.
Let's pick, this is for
high compact, so
I'm going to pick cyan.
C for cyan, C for compact,
hopefully you can
remember that.
So, I've changed that.
Now, when I changed this,
notice nothing changed here.
Why did nothing change there?
Anyone know?
It's because we are in
portrait on an iPhone here.
iPhone portrait, that is size
class height regular, see,
down here it will always tell
you what your size class is or
what you are looking at
this is height regular.
So, since height regular
is not height compact,
we get the default.
But if I switch over to here,
landscape, it turned cyan.
Because now, I'm in
landscape mode of an iPhone,
which is height compact,
width compact, as well.
And if I go to iPhone 7,
is it gonna be cyan here?
Yes, it is, because in iPhone
7 Plus, we're regular width,
but we're still
compact height,
so we're still getting
that cyan there.
Now, we could add another one,
for example, right here,
we could go add this one and
say, what about any width and
height is regular add
a variation for that and
go up here maybe we'll pick
red for regular, and so
now any time the height is
regular we're gonna see red.
So let's go look at
potrait>iPhone 7 Plus
that's clearly regular.
How about iPad?
Red.
It's regular.
Let's go iPhone.
Red.
Regular height.
Let's go landscape.
Back to compact,
so we get cyan.
So you see how I'm just
adding these variations.
And you can do that for
lots of different things.
For example, when we look
at this UI on an iPad,
it doesn't look that good.
Because, look how tiny
all the fonts are here.
Maybe we would want to go up
here and add a variation when
it's regular, regular,
okay, iPad only,
where we increase the font on
the buttons up to 80 or 90.
We could do that.
That's not always gonna be
the best way to do things like
vary your font, but it's
certainly possible to do that.
Understand all that business?
So, let's talk a little bit of
how we are going to make this
UI do the five by four or
the four by five thing here.
And we know that we
want to have as much
of the UI as we can that's
common to both be shared.
So, what I'm gonna
do is try to
work on that shared
part of the UI here.
And it doesn't really matter
what device I'm looking at
while I'm doing this.
Could be a iPhone Plus,
could be a regular iPhone,
doesn't matter,
because I'm editing stuff that
applies to all size classes.
And I'll show you in a moment
how we're gonna edit stuff
that applies to
a specific size class.
So how I'm gonna do this,
you saw in the slides
that really only this
part right here, these
bottom 16 are common to all.
These four across the top
are either across the top or
they're off, off to the left
in a horizontally compact
situation.
I'm gonna kind of have to
unbundle all these things, so
let's start by just selecting
this top level StackView and
unstackviewifying it.
Take everything out of
the StackView because clearly
these things can't be
inside that StackView.
And one thing to understand
when you're doing these
size classes,
you can have views come and
go based on size classes, but
you can't have them come and
go inside StackViews.
It doesn't know how to put
a view in inside another view.
It has to be kind of a top
level, coming and going, or
inclusion or not inclusion.
So, how do we undo
a stack view?
Actually you can just
go to editor up here,
the same place that we
said embed in stack view,
you can actually do unembed
and that will take everything
out of stack view,
back to where we were before.
The other thing I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna get rid of
all the constraints on here,
cuz I had these constraints
that were holding this to
the edge, but they just don't
make any sense anymore
cuz I've unbundled this.
So, how can I do that?
Right down here in the lower
corner where it says resolve
auto layout issues.
You can go down here and
for all views in
the view controller,
you can say clear constraints.
So that's what
I'm gonna go and
it's gonna wipe out all
the constraints in this
view controller.
Clear them all out.
So now that I don't have
the constraints in here,
I can move this staff
around and kind of put
new constraints that I want on
here and we can see that our
constraints are cleared
because if I select something
like this top label and I go
to size inspector over here,
there's no constraint
at the bottom.
So let's go ahead and
move this out of the way.
Let's put this back
tied to the top and
left and right in exactly
the same way as we did before.
So to kind of review,
I'm just gonna control
drag to the top notch.
I'm gonna do something
interesting.
I'm gonna Ctrl+Drag kinda
up to the corner up here.
When I do that, I can
actually do both leading and
vertical space.
And what I'm doing
here to make,
to pick more than one
constraint, is Shift.
So, if you do Shift, you can
pick more than one thing.
So here, I want both
the leading edge on the left
there, and the top edge,
the vertical space to be tied,
to be constrained.
So, I just pick all the ones
I want and then I click
add constraints right here,
and it adds those two.
And same thing, I can do
this one over here then.
That's the trailing one.
So now, when we look
at our label up there,
it's got these constraints.
That's good,
that's what we want.
Now, what about this
bottom constraint?
Well, it use to be that
the bottom of this was tied to
the top of this, and
then the bottom of this was
tied to the bottom of this.
But we can't do that anymore.
Because in five high
by four wide, this is
gonna be on the top, but
in four high and five wide,
these are gonna be over here
and this is gonna be the top.
So that's something we can't
do in the any/any mode.
We just can't do it.
But we can take this
stack down view and
put it down in this
corner over here.
And use our same control drags
to do the trailing
space there, and
the control drag to the bottom
to do the vertical space.
So I've tied this
thing to the bottom.
So this actually works,
in quotes,
it works in both modes.
Keeps them both on screen it's
doing what I said keeping
the display at the top and
keeping this stuff
in the lower right.
But it's clearly insufficient
to do what we want in the two
So, in the two cases, it's
this stack view right here,
different cases.
let me zoom in a little.
This stack view right here
is the one that's at issue.
So I'm just gonna
take this thing and
lift it up out of the stack
view, which you can do,
you can lift things up and
out.
So I lift it out and drop it,
and it's sitting there.
Now it doesn't want to be in
the any, any case at all.
It wants to only be in
certain size classes.
So, I'm going to take it and
cut it, because I'm gonna
paste it back in when we
get to other size classes.
So this is our
any/any right here.
This is the best we can do in
terms of common UI to both
the compact vertical case, and
the regular vertical case.
Now let's go on and
do the compact case let's say.
Let's do the UI
that's compact.
Now since all the work that
we're going to be doing right
now is only for the compact
case we depress this super
important button right here,
vary for traits.
This, this is what it's all
about when it comes to doing
the size class variations.
So first you're gonna pick
something that has the height
or width class or
both that you want to vary.
So here I wanna do
the horizontally or
the height compact, see height
compact, I wanna do that one.
So this is a pretty good
one to work in, but
I can pick any of the ones
that are height compact.
And I'm gonna say vary for
traits.
And I'm gonna vary in
the height direction.
Notice that that bar at
the bottom turned bright blue.
That's to warn you,
" watch out here
now because you are editing
UI only for height compact".
And it's even showing
you all devices that
are height compact.
Which is all the iPhones,
including the pluses.
They're all in landscape,
they're all height compact,
and those are the only ones.
So all the editing we're doing
now is only going to have
effect on these devices until
we stop making this thing blue
by pressing done varying.
So, building this UI now
we can, here's the two
big things you can do when
in the blue mode here.
One is you can add views or
remove views actually, and
the other you can
add constraints.
So, that's exactly
what I wanna do here,
I wanna put those four
buttons over here.
And then we wanna do some
constraints to make those
buttons be in the right place.
So let's start by adding these
back, remember I cut them so
I'm just gonna paste.
Here it is, here's that
stack view that had them.
It used to be inside this
stack view at the top.
Now we wanna kinda
put it on this side.
And when I put it on this
side I want it to like
seem like it's inside
the stack view,
but I can't actually put
it inside the stack view.
Cuz like I said,
this variation for
traits cannot put things
inside stock views.
But it's a great
opportunity for
me to show you other auto
layout constraints that can
make it seem like it's
in that stack view.
And basically do the same
thing that the stock view is
doing internally which is just
adding auto layout constraints
to make things work.
Now the first thing we want is
we want these buttons to be
vertical.
We want them up and down and
that's simple to do.
We have this selected,
I'm just gonna go to
the attributes inspector and
change the stack
view to be vertical.
So it's switching
over to vertical,
that's a really good start.
I could drag this up next to
it and use the blue lines.
That's nice, although the blue
lines are probably not gonna
get it right here.
If you notice when I drop
that blue line down, look,
it's trying to do
all kinds of things.
Centering here, stuff like
that along the bottom.
No, so I'm gonna do all my
constraints here to make
this hook up, I'm gonna
do them all manually.
Also it's a good chance to
show you how to do them all.
So what, how are we gonna make
this vertical piece right
here, this vertical
stack view,
look like it's a part of
this other stack view?
One thing we want to do is we
clearly want the height of
this stack view to always
be tracking the height of
the other one.
We want the top and bottom
edges, basically, of this
stack view and of this stack
view to always be pinned.
Well that sounds, pinning,
sounds like a constraint.
We wanna constrain them,
so, how can we do that?
Here's how we do it,
we're gonna select them both.
A good way to select things,
by the way, is dragging.
Dragging is a great
way to select things.
So I'm gonna select both
of them right here.
And then I'm gonna use
this menu down here.
Which is called the align
menu, and that's exactly what
I wanna do,
I wanna align these things.
I click on it, and you can see
that I can align things like
the centers or
even the text base lines.
But what I want here is
that I wanna align the top
and bottom.
So I'm gonna click top and
bottom.
These numbers over here
by the way are an offset.
So if you wanted it
to align the tops but
you want one to be ten higher,
you can put a ten in here.
But I want them be
right along the top.
I wanna have the constraint
where this is
exactly the same, this is
exactly the same at all times.
So I pick whichevers
I want and
just say, add constraints and
I added them.
Now, woah,
it turn red, why am I getting
those red lines right there?
Now, you can always
find out about your
problems that you have with
constraints by clicking on
this little thing
right up here.
You see this yellow guy,
click on him and it says,
the horizontal position is
ambiguous for stack view.
Well, I've got multiple
stack views, so
which one's it talking about.
This is kind of a bummer.
This is really just
an overview of the errors.
Usually we don't look here.
The place we look is in
the document outline okay.
The document outline
here which I have shown.
I can hide it and show it.
This is the place where for
example we had to wire up
to the refresh control.
This is the place we go
when it's hard to click on
something, cuz we can just
click on a view here.
This is also the place we
go to deal with all auto
layout problems.
And the magic place to look is
this upper corner right here.
You see that red right there?
This red is saying that
there is either a lack
of constraints or
conflicting constraints.
In other words, there are
constraint problems that are
so bad that your app is not
going to work when you run.
So we can click on this red
thing and it will show us
all the details of all
the constraint problems.
So now when we
mouse over this,
it still says need
constraints for x position.
But we can find out which
stack view it's talking about.
And of course,
it's talking about that one.
This other stack
view over here,
it has an x position,
it's tied to the left edge.
But this one is not
tied to anything.
It's top and
bottom are tied but
it could be sliding
horizontally any which way.
So that's not tied, so
we don't know where it's
exposition is supposed to be.
We need to fix that.
How are we gonna fix that?
Well probably the best way to
do that is to hook it up to
the edge of this stack view.
Cuz if it, we tie this edge
right here to this stack view,
then it'll, its horizontal
position will be set because
it'll be tied to this
guy's horizontal position.
So how do we hook
this guy up to here?
Well we could of course
control drag, all right, but
I'm gonna use this opportunity
to show you a different way to
Which is I selected it and I'm
going down to this other menu
hook it up.
down here, this one that says
add new constraints, and
I'm clicking on it.
And we've actually seen
this one briefly, I think.
But here you can do things
like make things to be
affixed with.
Or you can set the distance
from your nearest neighbor.
That's what these are.
These are the distance
to the nearest neighbor.
Now these little red I-beams
are all grayed out right here
or transparency'd out.
So right now,
this guy is not hooked up to
his nearest neighbor at all.
But we clearly wanna hook him
up to his nearest neighbor on
the right, that's this one.
So, I'm gonna click this
I-beam,it turns it on and now,
he's clamped to his nearest
neighbor on the right and
he's eight pixels away
because that's what the dash
blue lines put, but
we dont want that,
we want ten pixels away,
so we're gonna put ten.
We have 10 pixels away clamped
to the nearest neighbor.
Let's add that
constraint as well.
Our red went away but
now we have yellow.
What does yellow
mean in auto layout?
Yellow means,
"your constraints are okay and
when you run it's
probably gonna work, but
what you're looking at in
your storyboard is not
what your constraints
are saying".
Your constraints are not
equal to what you see here.
You can see right here, for
example, it's expecting
the X position of this stack
view that's highlighted right
here to be at 385, but
it's actually at 387.
And if we zoom way in,
in fact, with option.
There's a option zooming here.
You can see there's
a dashed yellow line.
I don't know if
you can see that.
Yeah, you can see that.
This dashed yellow line,
that's where the constraint
system thinks this
Stack View should be.
The solid yellow line is
where it actually is.
And even the i-beam between
the two has a little -2
right there, saying yeah,
I got this i-beam here, but
it seems like it should be
2 points over to the left.
How do we fix this.
When we have these yellow
problems how do we
get things to be put in
the right place or something.
And the answer is we're gonna
go over to our document
outline.
By the way we can get here
with the same way we got
to the red by clicking in this
upper corner with the yellow.
And we're gonna click on this
triangle cuz that's gonna,
the string will let you
resolve the problem.
So, I click on it and
actually have some choices
how to resolve that problem,
one is I can update the frame,
that means move the views
to match the constrains,
which is definitely what
I want in this case.
Because I do want it to be 10
pixels apart there not eight.
But I could also do
other things like
updating the constraints.
And that would go and
Even thought I typed 10, this
would clamp it back to 8, so
that it would match
what's going on here.
Or you can do the dreaded
reset to suggested
constraints.
Which probably also
would at least do that,
probably do some other
things we don't want.
In other words it kinda try
do what the blue line said.
Reset to suggest
the constraints we rarely use.
It's only good for when you're
like dragging something
right into the middle or
right out to the edges
those kind of things.
It's not super good
guessing what you want
in other scenarios.
Now, this update frames,
I can apply it just to
this view right here that's
having the problem or
I can apply it to all the
views in my entire controller.
And whether you have
this switched or not,
it's about 50/50 when we
switch this is whether you
have other views that you're
in the middle of working on.
That you haven't quite fully
specified their constraints.
Then you'd probably
don't want apply to all,
because it's going to
try to move them and
you haven't finished
specifying them.
But in this case,
this is the only view that has
any misplaced views, you see.
So, I can go ahead and
say all or not.
It's not going to
make a difference,
because this is the only
one that is going to move.
I'm just going to
leave it at all.
And I'm gonna say Fix.
And you're gonna see
that it moved it.
Moved it two pixels over here.
If we zoom in again here,
we'll see now that this is
tan, just like this is ten.
And it also says No Autolayout
issues over here.
It moved it.
If we go back here,
there's nothing in the corner.
All is well.
We're in good
shape right there.
Now, there's one other
problem with this,
look how narrow these buttons
are compared to these buttons.
We want these buttons to
be exactly the same width
as all of these buttons.
Now since it's not in the same
stack view it's not getting
the fill equally and so
it's not getting that.
So, how can I make these
buttons inside this
stack view right here be
exactly the same width
as the buttons over here.
Well, I'm going to
just control drag.
Actually, I'm gonna control
drag from the entire
stack view.
See I'm dragging
from the stack view.
To any button over here and
just say
that I want it to be the same
width as any button over here.
So, we'll just
pick this one and
here's all the things
we can choose and
then I'm gonna go down
here to the bottom and
pick Equal Widths
okay cuz I want those
buttons to be the same width.
And I'm gonna add
that constraint and
it applies the constraint.
And you can even see this
constraint right there.
Again, I'll zoom in.
You can see the constraints
right here.
This equals and
this equals are saying
those two things are equal.
So we're almost there.
We've got these four
buttons that we've added
looking like they're in the
stack view by putting our own
constraints on there.
The only thing that's left is,
we're not using
the whole space.
We're not connected
to the whole space.
Now here, we can do exactly
what we did before,
I'm just gonna select this
StackView right here.
Not this one, but
just this one.
I'm gonna Ctrl drag
up to here and
I'm gonna set its
vertical spacing.
Put's this I-beam
in here to the top.
Now when I double-click on it.
Well also by the way, you know
that we can click on these and
inspect them, remember that,
so it's showing that this
I-beam connects the stack
views top to the displays
button and it sets them to be
equal with an offset of 57.
That's what this constant is.
It's an offset of 57.
So that's why we're
getting this 57 high bar.
And we don't want that.
We want to change that
to be standard value.
Actually, we don't even
want standard value,
we probably want 10 because we
probably want this distance to
be the same as the distance
between all of our buttons.
I'm not sure which
one we want but
I think that one's
probably pretty good.
So that's good now notice as
soon as constrained the top of
this stack view to go up here
it automatically dragged
this stack view's
top up there.
That's because we
have a constrained
that hooks the tops
of these together.
If I click on here,
I look in the size inspector,
you can see that I've got
a line top to this top and
bottom to this
other stack view.
Do you see that?
So that's good.
What about this edge?
Same thing here, we can just
take this stack view and
hook it to edge, this leading
space to contain a margin,
just like we did before, and
here we get this, obviously
we can inspect it over here.
We can also double click
on it to inspect it, which
we saw before, and here I've
picked standard value, there's
no standard value available,
so I'm just gonna do zero and
it's gonna zoom
that think over.
That's it.
So we've done everything
we need to do no for
this height-compact situation.
And so,
this is a very important
thing to remember to do.
When you're done,
click Done varying down here.
Because a lot of
times you'll do this,
and you're like all
right it's working.
And then, you'll go on to work
on some other sized class, and
you'll forgot to have
clicked this off.
And now, you'll be editing
only in the height-compact.
So, we're gonna
hit Done varying.
Get's rid of our blue.
And we, so
we know we're in good shape.
Now what happens if I
go back to portrait?
What's this gonna look
like in portrait?
Anyone wanna volunteer?
Yes, so all of this
work that we did here
has had no effect
whatsoever on portrait.
Because portrait
is height regular.
And all that work we did here,
every single bit we did since
we clicked into the blue bar,
only happens in high compact.
So when we click back to
portrait it looks just like it
used to, unaffected by
all that work we did.
Make sense,
understand why that happened?
So now, we need to, in this
case, the height regular case,
we need to put those buttons
in along the top here.
So, I'm gonna do this
pretty quickly, so
you can kind of see
a review of it.
Actually, before
I do that review,
let's let this soak
in a little bit,
because I wanna show you
the document outline.
So, I'm going over
the document outline and
I'm just gonna make it wider.
And why do you wanna
make this wider?
Well, the document outline
shows not only all your views,
but it also show all
of your constraints.
You see all these
constraints down here?
And you notice that
some of them are, like,
grayed out here.
And why are they grayed out?
Because they apply to
a different size class
than is being shown here.
We are looking at height
regular, these grayed out
constraints are only over
here in height compact.
So, when we go to
height compact,
all of them apply because
we haven't done any
constraints that are in
height regular only yet.
So, all of these apply
in that circumstance.
Now, looking at
your constraints
right here is a really
good kind of tool for
finding tiny little
problems with your UI.
And that's when you
have magic numbers.
You see this magic
numbers in here?
8 8 20 10 and 10.
By the way, we never wanna
look at the magic numbers for
things that are grade out.
Like this 347 when I
look at that because it
doesn't apply here.
We only wanna look at the ones
that are dark blue here.
So we don't like to see
these magic numbers here,
unless we intend for
that magic number to be there.
So, 8 8 20,
we never typed those in.
Why are they there?
We don't want them there.
10 and
10 however we do want those.
We wanted those,
those are a magic number
we want in our UI.
That's our spacing in between
that we decided we want.
So, how to we get rid of these
magic numbers, like 8, 8, 20?
Well, you're gonna click
on them to select it.
This is just like if you
had clicked on it in here,
cuz the document outline,
you remember, you click there.
It's just like you're clicking
in, in here, except for
sometimes it's even easier to
click on the document outline.
We could also click on the
thing that it's attached to
like the display.
So, this is the display's
top equals top layout
guide plus eight.
And go to the size
inspector here and see it.
And we'll see the magic
numbers here also,
not just in
the document outline.
But, we're seeing them here
in our size inspector.
So, any time we see these
magic numbers we want to
inspect them,
either here or by clicking
on them and edit them.
So, in the size inspector
we've always gone in to check
to make sure things are good,
but we can also change
them if they're not good.
And so, here I'm clicking
on it and editing it, and
this constant, I don't
want it to be eight, so
let's see what my choices are.
I don't have standard value,
use canvas value means
use what's currently
showing in the story board,
we rarely want that.
It's almost never want that,
that would mean that we had
to have dragged it right in
position they will
use the blue lines.
It might be right but,
almost never do you
want the canvas value.
Instead, we're gonna
do what we do here,
to say what we want, so maybe,
this one, actually I'm gonna
do this one down here first,
let's look at this one.
So this top layout guide here,
this one, we can use
a standard value, to do it
to the top layout guide.
And look,
I did standard value and
it got rid of the plus eight.
It's still eight pixel, eight
points over there because that
is the standard value but
it stopped showing it as that.
And same thing up here when we
go up to this one and we look,
there's no standard value
here so what do we put, 0.
And we will have zero.
That actually fixed a bug
because it move this display
right up to the edge
right there.
And you can see that
got rid of that one.
Same thing here,
we can go to this one.
Let's do this one
by inspecting it.
Here's the constant right
here, 20, we don't want that.
We go here and say,
standard value.
What's the standard value and
the 20 is gone,
that also fixed a bug
cuz the thing was not all
the way down at the bottom.
So, you see how we
fixed bugs by going and
chasing down all of our
magic numbers in this view,
okay in the document outline.
So, you almost always want to
be chasing those things down.
The only problem can happen
here when you're chasing them
is when you have a magic
number like 8 or
20 that you actually
intend to be 8 or 20.
Cuz then you're like is
that a magic wand or not?
Because there's no way to
down like a variable in
there or something.
But these tens,
we know those are right.
All right, so,
just a little side track there
to show you how to use that.
Let's go back to our
height regular and
make this look
like what we want.
So, let's start by pasting
back in these things.
Actually, before we do that.
And this is a common
mistake you'll make to.
What mistake did I
make right there?
I wanted to start doing
height regular and
I didn't hit vary for
traits, so
I wasn't acctually
editing height regular,
I was editing any/any.
So, don't miss that,
so I'm gonna vary for
traits in heights and
this gonna use this height
were I'm looking at, height
regular this gonna show me all
gonna show me all devices with
height regular which is
all the iPads, Split View,
Masters, all the iPhone,
they're all height regulars.
So it's just showing me and
I can actually do this
editing in anyone of those.
Because they're all
height regular.
All right, so
now let's paste this in.
Now, when I pasted this in,
by the way an interesting
thing happened.
If I go to my attributes
inspector and
go all the way to the bottom.
Look right here.
Okay, I selected this
stake view right here.
And you see that it
says installed not.
But, in height regular
it's installed.
That's saying this stack view
only is installed in the view
hierarchy.
When we're height regular.
If I click on this one notice
it's installed everywhere.
Doesn't say not installed and
height regular.
It says installed everywhere.
So, you can always
tell which user and
you can of course click
these on and off.
And you can even add a plus
here to add variation
to remove them.
I find it easier just to
Enter this varying mode and
then drag these things in.
Anyway, here we go.
Let's get this
thing down here.
Again, we want the both
edges to be lined up.
So, let's go ahead and
do that remember we do that
by selecting them both.
And in going over
here to a line.
This time it's the leading and
trailing edges that we
want to be the same.
And add those constraints.
Again, as soon as I had
those constraints now I have
a problem with a vertical
position of this stack view,
is not defined.
You need constraints for
the Y position.
Cuz, I've only constrained
it horizontally right there.
So, let's go ahead and
constrain it for
a vertical by
pinning it to this.
So, I'm gonna use this other
one over here this time.
And I'm gonna show you
something interesting here.
So, here I'm gonna pin to its
bottom nearest neighbor, and
I'm gonna use ten, which is
my magic number that I want.
And I'm gonna pick something
in here cuz remember last time
we did this and
when I put this in here it
turned from red to yellow.
Because things weren't in the
right position cuz I had added
constraints and
it didn't move them.
Well, if you go down here and
say update frames either to
the items of the new
constraints,
involved in the new
constraints which would be.
This nearest neighbor and
us, or
you can do it all the frames
in your container.
If you turn this on, then when
you add this constraints,
it will automatically
move them.
And then,
you won't get the yellow.
You won't have to go over and
click, update frames and
all that.
So watch this, when I add this
constraint, it moved them.
You see that?
No yellow.
Right here.
I am in
my document outline nothing
on in the upper corner
like there was when
we did the other one.
Now, we still have one
other things to do here.
It's not obvious that
we need to do this but
the height of these just
happens to to be the same
height as all of these.
But that's just
happy circumstance.
And the other time it was
obvious that they weren't.
So I need to do the same thing
here where I'm gonna control,
drag from this stack view.
And then again I could do
either an individual button or
one of these sub stack
views right here.
And I'm gonna set them
to be equal heights.
Other was, just so
that no matter what
mathematical symbol I put
in those buttons up there
then it's never gonna
squinch down and be smaller.
Or grow up and
be bigger than the other ones.
So I'm gonna say equal
height right there.
See the two equals that
got generated there?
So same thing as before.
We've done a good job
of adding this on and
making it seem like this
is part of the stack view.
So this time we're going to
attach this stack view up to
here.
So I'm just gonna
control drag up to here,
set the vertical spacing, and
I'm gonna put the edge of this
big stack view right
here over to the edge.
And same thing as always we
want to double click here.
Standard if we can.
We can't, we'll do zero.
Same thing with
this one over here.
Double click.
Here we want our
magic number of ten.
So now we've done all
that we need to do for
our height regulars so we
can done varying right here.
And did this effect
height compact, no,
no effect on height compact.
And if we run,
we've got width is compact but
height is regular so
we're getting five high and
four across, in a regular
height we go five high.
And when we switch over here,
we get width compact,
height compact and we're gonna
to four high and five across.
Hopefully that showed
you pretty much all
the things you need to
know about auto layout.
Not just how we vary major
UI differences between
the size classes.
But also how you are gonna
use the document outline over
here to look at all
of your constraints.
And fix the dark blue ones
that have magic numbers that
you didn't intend.
You can also use this to
click on your constraints and
look at them.
It's highlighting them here.
And inspect them over here.
And we're still often
using the size inspector,
right here, to look at
all of our constraints.
In the hugging priority we
briefly showed that's just if
you have two things that
are trying to share a space.
And you want one to hug and
one to use the other space,
you can do the hugging.
We also didn't really talk
about the content compression
resistance but
that's the opposite thing.
That's where it's trying
to collapse things down.
One of them wants to
keep its height and
the other one is happy
to be collapsed down.
So that's just kinda
the opposite of hugging.
That compressing so
we can set that as well.
Any questions about all
that autolayout business?
Okay, so that is it for
the demo.
And just a little bit
about what's coming up.
So tomorrow your assignment
five is due by midnight.
No section Friday this week.
Next week the lectures
are gonna be about animation.
A really important part
obviously of an iPhone device
or iOS device is animating
things on screen.
So we're gonna talk
about that next week.
>> For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.