[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well,
welcome to Stanford CS193P,
Developing Applications for
iOS, Winter 2017,
this is lecture number 13.
And this week's topic is
gonna be animation, and
I'm gonna talk first
today about timers.
Timer is just a way to
execute a block of code,
some periodic amount of time.
We don't really use timers for
animation per se,
but often, when we're doing
something that's animated,
we'll have some
timers involved.
And you'll see that especially
on Wednesday's big demo,
how we're gonna use the timer
in with our animation tools.
Then after we talk
about timer, I,
I do a demo there, we're gonna
dive into animation proper.
And I'm gonna talk about
all the different kinds of
animation mechanisms there
are and then dive into,
a couple of them with a bit
of a demo in between.
And then on Wednesday, I'll do
a demo of the last animation
style, that I'm gonna cover.
So timer, timer is this,
very simple class,
very simple to use.
You're only probably
gonna use two or
maybe three, methods or
vars in it ever.
And all it allows you to
do is take a closure,
a block of code, and execute
it some time in the future,
either once or repeatedly,
in the future.
And, this is kind of not
really real-time programming.
This timer's not gonna go off
exactly when you say, but
it's gonna be pretty close
because it's going off on
the main queue.
And the main queue
is sometimes is busy
handling an event or
something like that.
So it's not exact, but
it's pretty darn close,
to going off.
So you can't use it for real
time programming, but you can,
use it to have any kind of
repeating thing going on.
Now, timer is based
on a technology,
which I'm not gonna talk
about called run loops.
And run loops are how, you
know, a certain thread gets
all this information, like
events from the, touch screen
and, or, you know, events from
the network, or whatever.
It gets all these things
coming in, and it manages to
hand them all out to whoever
needs to handle them.
And run loops aren't
super complicated, but
the reason I don't really talk
about them is the run loop
just kinda works on
the main queue, and
you don't really need
to think about it.
But if you ever find yourself,
I wanna use a timer off the
main queue, then you're gonna
have to teach yourself
about run loops, okay,
because the timers are totally
based, on the run loop.
your purposes in this course
as a starting, iOS developer,
But for
you can assume that timers
are a main queue thing, okay?
Now, there's really, there's,
you can create timers
by instantiating them,
but then you gotta put them
on a run loop and all that.
But, so there's really
just one method,
class method you're
gonna use in timer.
And what this one method does
is it takes a block of code,
And it takes how, when you
wanna execute it some time in
a closure.
the future and whether you
wanna keep repeating executing
it, and it goes and does that.
It puts the thing on the run
loop to make sure that it
executes that block of
code with that interval.
Really couldn't be simpler,
it's a very, very, simple and
powerful UI right there.
So down at the bottom,
here's an example of it,
this method is called
scheduled timer.
And it returns the timer that
it creates when it schedules
it and
puts it on the run loop.
And so
here I'm just saying timer =,
I have a local var timer.
Notice it's of type timer,
it's an optional timer here.
And so I do timer =
scheduledTimer(withTimeInter-
val: 2.0, repreat,
repeats: true).
And then the block,
I put some code.
Well, that's gonna execute
that code two seconds from now
approximately.
And since it's repeats true,
it's gonna execute it again
two seconds later and
then two seconds after that
until I stop this thing, okay?
Now, one thing to note about
this little example here,
is notice my timer is weak.
Okay, see that, weak?
Why do I make that timer weak?
Well, when I scheduled
this timer, and
it puts it on the run loop,
the run loop is gonna grab
a strong reference to it.
So I don't need a strong
reference to it.
And in fact, if I make my
reference weak, then when
this run loop is done with it,
when this thing finally
stops running, my ti, timer
var there will be set to nil.
Perfect, exactly what I want,
because it's really no use
tabbing a pointer to this
timer if it's not
running anymore.
And if I ever wanted to
start a timer up again
that I'd stopped, I would just
call scheduledTimer again,
it's such a simple, API.
So how do you stop a timer?
So you got a timer and
it's got repeating true and
it's going off and
it's doing this closure every
two seconds or whatever.
You stop it by sending
the message invalidate to
the timer, and so invalidate
tells the run loop to stop,
scheduling this thing and
invalidates the timer.
Now, again, this timer is
going to not, if you do
invalidate right there, and
you have a weak var to it,
it's gonna go out of the heap,
which is really convenient.
There's one last thing I'm
gonna do about timers,
which is tolerance.
So this is not a real-time
thing, and you might be quite
tolerant of it not
executing exactly on time.
This makes more sense for
timers that take longer, like
let's say you have a timer
that goes off every minute,
and it does something.
Well, you might be happy if it
goes off 50 seconds from now
or 70 seconds from now.
So you would set a tolerance
of 10 on the timer, and
it means it'll go off in the
window plus or minus that 10.
By the way,
this does not have any drift.
So, if it, if the system
decided it was gonna go off in
50 seconds this time, the next
time, it wouldn't, you know,
be shorter and shorter and
shorter with each time.
So, the time it goes off
is the amount of time from
the time you
started the timer.
Even if it's two days later,
it's still going off
once per minute.
It's once per minute since
you started the timer.
It's just that when it
goes off, it'll be plus or
minus a little bit each time.
Now why would you want
to tell the system this?
Well, when your timer
goes off, you know,
it might be that the system
is actually asleep.
Your phone surprisingly
sleeps a little,
takes a little micro naps all
the time, okay, to save power,
especially to save battery.
And wakes up every
once in a while, and
it kinda knows when it's
gonna wake up again.
And so the tolerance allows
it to maybe take a micro nap
a little longer cuz it's gonna
wake up for something else,
and then it could
be your timer.
You see, so this is
a little micro performance.
But if you have
something to go on and
off every minute over,
you know,
long periods of time,
it can add up.
Okay, so that's tolerance.
All right, so,
let's do a little demo,
see this in action, it's kinda
obvious, once you see it.
So I'm gonna take FaceIt,
remember the FaceIt demo we
had, this is
a picture of a face,
I'm gonna make the eyes
blink using a timer, okay?
The timer's just gonna
open the eyes and
then close the eyes, open the
eyes and then close the eyes,
super simple.
So let's go back and
get FaceIt, here it is.
All right, so
here is our face view now.
The thing about the blinking,
I'm gonna,
I wanna show you this again
because it's so important.
I'm gonna actually put this
blinking code in a separate
view controller, which is
a sub class of the other one.
So we have this existing
FaceViewController right here
as the thing that controls
this MBC right here, okay?
Where this face is, it's, it's
loading up the face right now.
And so I could just put this
code in FaceViewController,
but just to show you it again,
this,
this thing of, sub-classing
another MBC to make one.
I'm gonna create a new
FaceViewController called
a blinking FaceViewController,
I'm gonna put all my
blinking code, into that.
So let's just go File > New >
File, and Cocoa Touch Class.
And I'm, it's a subclass
of FaceViewController.
And I'm gonna call it
BlinkingFaceViewController.
And that's gonna
create a new class.
I'll put it in same place
everything else is.
Okay, here it is, just delete
all the code in here, again,
just not to, so
as not to distract you.
And you can see that it is a
subclass of FaceViewController
which is this thing right here
that has all our stuff in it.
And all the code that I'm
gonna put inside here is
only gonna be for blinking.
And I'm gonna change,
in my storyboard I'm gonna
select this MVC down here and
right now, its identity
is FaceViewController.
And I'm gonna change it to be
a BlinkingFaceViewController.
And that change alone
is gonna make it so
that this particular face view
right there is going to blink.
So how do we do that,
how do we make this
BlinkingFaceViewController
work?
Well, what's going
to be its model?
Well, its model is
going to be public and
I'm gonna call it blinking,
and
it's just gonna be a whether
or not we're blinking, okay?
And if someone sets this model
of this blinking controller
then I'm going to call some
method like blinkIfNeeded,
blinkIfNeeded, private
func blinkIfNeeded,
okay?
it's just going to
blink if needed.
Now if blinking is false,
obviously the blinking is not
needed so it won't be blinking
but if it is blinking,
then we need to blink.
Now, just for
demo purposes right here,
or maybe this is even what I
would want, I'm gonna turn on
my blinking when I appear,
when my MVC appears on screen,
and I'm gonna turn it
off when I disappear.
And you do need to think
about this when you're using
a timer.
That when your MVC goes
off screen because it's in
a navigation controller and
someone navigates to something
else or someone hits back,
or some of that.
You wanna make sure that
you stop your timer.
You don't want that timer,
sitting there running,
doing something,
the MVC is not even on screen
unless it's doing something
I guess that's not UI based.
But I'm gonna say here
in my viewDidAppear,
super.viewDidAppear.
I'm gonna say here
blinking = true.
So every time my MVC
appears on screen,
it's gonna start blinking and
in viewWillDisappear
I'm going to say
blinking = false.
So, I'm gonna stop blinking
when it disappears,
does it make sense?
Okay, so, that's going to
obviously cause my stimer,
timer to stop going cuz my
timer is only gonna be going
when I'm blinking, all right?
So, how am I gonna
implement blinkIfNeeded?
Well, it's only if needed so
I'm gonna say, if I'm blinking
then I'm gonna do something,
that is the if needed part of
this blink thing right here.
And what do I need to do?
Well, first of all I'm gonna
just have some constants here.
I think I called it,
what did I call this.
I don't know, what did I
call the constants here.
Hm, well,
we'll just typing them in.
So I'm gonna have a little
struct here called BlinkRate.
And I'm gonna have how long
my eyes stays closed when I'm
blinking, and how long it
stays open when I'm blinking.
So, let's have a static let
closedDuration which is
gonna be a TimeInterval.
TimeInterval is just a little
class or a little type that
represents elapse time,
it's pretty much a double.
But whenever we're talking
about TimeIntervals we kinda
let people know in our code by
using the TimeInterval type.
And then I'm gonna have the
same thing openDuration which
is gonna be a TimeInterval.
And, you know,
usually when we're blinking,
our eyes stay open a lot
longer than they're closed.
So let's say something like,
I don't know, 2.5 seconds or
something like that.
Okay, now if I was
doing this for real,
I'd probably have the amount
it stays open be random
within some tolerance, right?
Cuz when we're blinking we
don't go blink, blink, we,
you know kind of
sometimes we blink and
then this short amount
of time, but again, for
demo purposes here we'll
just fix it to be 2.5.
All right, so we have that.
Now, all we're
gonna do to blink,
is we're gonna start by
setting our eyes to be closed.
So I'm gonna say self.
I don't even need self here.
faceView.eyesOpen = false.
Remember faceView is our,
one of our superclass's vars,
a public var in
our superclass.
That's maybe unfortunate it
has to be a var, or public.
It'd be nice if it
was protected, maybe,
we'd have no such thing, so
it's public, outlet there.
And we're setting it
to eyesOpen to false.
So we're starting our
blink by closing our eyes.
Now, after
the closed duration,
we wanna open them back up.
So, I'm gonna say,
Timer.scheduledTimer and
notice I'm not even looking at
the return value of the timer
cuz I never have
to invalidate it.
This is gonna be
a one shot deal, and
it's gonna automatically
invalidate itself when
it's done.
And so the time interval
here we want is
BlinkRate.closeDuration,
right?
We just closed our eyes.
eyesOpen = false, and
it repeats false,
it's just gonna do it once.
I'm going to call
blinkIfNeeded again
after I've blinked once.
So I'm just gonna kind of keep
calling blinkIfNeeded until
blinking is not true anymore.
And then here's the block of
code that it, it's gonna call
each time, and so it takes
a timer as an argument there.
Oops, yeah.
Timer and we don't,
we can use a closing, Trailing
closure syntax notation here,
put that on the end.
So here is the timer.
So what do we need to
do inside this timer?
Well, we're just gonna
open our eyes back up,
so faceView.eyesOpen = true.
And of course,
we're inside a closure here so
we're gonna need self..
And of course, we don't
want to have the memory
cycle here although
this timer's so
short duration, probably
that's not gonna be an issue.
But we'll go ahead here and
do weak self up here and
just do Okay?
So now,
eyes are back open, right?
And what do we need to do now?
Well, if we're still blinking,
we need to blink again.
So, we need, basically need to
call blinkIfNeeded again, but
we got to wait for
our openDuration,
leave our eyes open for
that long and then,
if we're still blinking,
then we'll blink again.
So blinkIfNeeded again.
So, I'm just gonna do
another timer inside here,
which is perfectly fine.
Even though I'm in a closure
that's being executed
0.4 seconds in the future, I,
there's no law that says in
that closure I couldn't
schedule another timer,
which is exactly
what I'm gonna do.
And this one,
the BlinkRate.openDuration,
so I'm just gonna wait
the amount open time,
again it's not repeating.
Okay and then in this guy's
closure, which I'm also gonna
do with trailing closure
notation, timer.
And heck, let's go ahead and
do weak self,
we're not gonna know
we're gonna want that In
here I'm just gonna say
self.blinkIfNeeded.
And of course,
it will stop blinking if
blinking has been set to false
at any point here, okay?
So, this is always gonna do
one blink and then if it needs
two, it'll do it'll go
back and do another blink.
So, yes, ?, at this weak.
Okay, we got this code.
So, that's it, that's all
we need to do to blink,
we're just gonna open or
we're just gonna close
your eyes rather,
wait a little bit,
open them back up,
wait a little bit more and
then blink again if
w're still blinking.
So let's see what
that looks like.
Okay, there he is.
He's blinking.
Okay, and he'll work.
Here, we'll just
switch him around.
He works no matter what.
Whether he's happy or sad,
he's always blinking.
Now, one thing about
this blink that's not so
good is it's kind of abrupt.
That's why I'm saying it's
not really animation, right?
We don't blink like this.
Okay, nobody blinks like that.
Okay, we kind of close our
eyes a little bit slow.
There's a little bit
of motion to it.
And so
we'd really like to do that.
And so let's talk about some
more animation capabilities we
have and how we can do really
more true animation of that,
than just using a timer.
So let's go back to
our Slides here.
Alright, so before I do that
though, let me talk about and
summarize not all actually,
but most of the animation
capabilities that
you get with iOS,
so the when I am gonna
talk about in detail and
demo today is animating
UIView properties.
There's only a few of
the properties Vars,
in other words, in UIView
that you can animate.
But they're pretty powerful
few as you're gonna see, and
allows us to do,
a lot of animation.
There's also, you can also
obviously animate those
controller animations like in
a navigation controller when
you click to go to the next
card on the stack,
it slides in, right,
that's animated.
And when you rotate your split
view, those are animated
transitions, that's
all controllable.
even though I'm not gonna talk
at all about it in this class,
And in fact,
might be a good final project,
not covered in lecture
thing for you, by the way.
You, there's a whole
infrastructure for
writing your own
controllers of controllers,
like navigation controller,
split controller,
tab bar controller.
And so, part of that
mechanism includes
full animation support.
Now, underneath all of this
animation I'm talking is
Core Animation,
it's a framework, okay?
Like UI kind of a framework.
And Core Animation has
a lot of mechanism for
doing very sophisticated
animation.
Now, not a lot of it
bubbles up to the UI view
animation that we're
gonna talk about but
kind of the simplest most
straight forward once do.
Again, this is something for
your final project maybe you
wanna do some more
sophisticated animation.
You could drop down into
the core animationlLater
is a little bit
about window in
the core animation
from UI view.
It's a bar in UI view called
I think it's called there's
a lot of makings in for
doing 3D animation.
OpenGL as full OpenGL
>> [COUGH]
>> There's another cool little
kit might put this in some of
your final projects called
spritekit, spritekit is kind
of 2.5 D animation typical
animation we have like little
character running around and
he's jumping over things,
shooting at things.
That would likely be
done with spritekit,
it knows how to do
things like fire.
Things like that in addition
to knowing how to layer
images on top of each other
and have them move around.
So that's kinda fun, not gonna
be able to talk about that.
And lastly is physics-based
animation, and we're
gonna talk all about that at
the end of this lecture, and
then I'll demo
that on Wednesday.
So the two I'm gonna talk
about is the first one and
the last one,
UIView animations, and
then physics-based animation.
All right, so let's talk
about this UIView Animation.
What can you animate.
Well, these are the things
you can animate.
You can animate
the position of your view.
So, you can make it animated,
moving,
sliding around on screen.
The view's moving around.
You can animate
it's transform,
which primarily means,
it's size or it's rotation.
Okay?
Cuz the translation part of it
transport, transform,
you're pretty much gonna do
with frame or center, okay?
So you can rotate your view or
scale it up and down.
There's alpha, okay.
Alpha you remember number is
I didn't remember is opacity.
So, how
much it's
transparent.
So that, takes closures.
And inside these closures,
you're gonna change
these values, okay.
And what the method,
the class method's gonna do,
is animate those changes,
that you make.
All right, so
let's take a look
at one of these class methods.
This one's called
animate withDuration.
And you can see here
that it takes these two
closures right there.
You see the two
green closures?
And the first green
closure there,
inside there, you change any
of those special vars, okay?
Frame, center, alpha,
etc, you change them.
By the way, it makes those
changes immediately.
It does not take
time to change them.
Even though it takes time for
it to appear on screen
it happens immediately.
And then the completion
block is called
after the animation is done.
So, you know, however your
animation you take when it's
completely done.
Then this gets called and
the finished
variable, err the finished
argument to that closure
is whether the animation
got all the way to the end.
And why could it might
not get to the end?
Some other animation might
pick it up in the middle and
start animating that
bar to somewhere else.
Okay, so,
here's what it looks like.
To call that,
here's an example of it.
So, here I have
a view called myView.
[SOUND] And what I'm gonna do
with this code right here is,
I'm gonna take a view as
long as it's fully opaque,
fully visible on screen,
I'm going to wait two seconds.
And then, over three seconds,
I'm gonna fade it out.
Fade it to alpha,
down to zero.
And then,
when it's fully faded out,
I'm gonna remove it from
the view hierarchy, okay?
That's what this code does.
So, you can see,
So, if it's full power.
And if it is, then I'm doing
animate with duration.
The duration of three seconds,
that's how long it's
gonna take this,
the green code there to
execute to, not to execute,
but to show up on the screen.
And then delay is how long I'm
gonna wait till I start that
animation.
we'll talk all about options,
in a couple of slides.
The options,
But here, curve linear
means it's gonna go from
alpha one to 1.0 in a linear,
linear over time.
So after one second it's gonna
be a third of the way there.
After two seconds it'll
be two thirds of the way.
And after the full time
it'll be down to zero.
In animations, you can
see what I'm animating.
I'm changing the alpha
to zero, okay?
That's the change I'm making
to those special bars.
And then at completion you can
say, if $0, which means if I
finished, then remove
this view from Superview.
And remember, that
completion applock is only
called after
the animation is done.
In other words,
five seconds from now.
All right?
Now what's really interesting
is on the next line there I
say print myView.alpha equals
the value of myView.alpha,
that is going to immediately
print zero, okay?
That method animate
withDuration, it only executes
the first green closure there,
myView.alpha = 0.0,
and then it returns
immediately after that.
And at that point,
myView.alpha is 0.0.
The animation is just queued
up to happen in the future.
So always think of the changes
you make with the animation
system as happening right now.
You're just executing that
closer right now, but
by putting it in this little
wrap of this animate with
duration, you're queueing
up an animation to show
the user that change that
you've already made over time.
Now it seems a little
weird because, whoa,
I changed it right now and so
inside my code alpha is zero,
but the user still
sees it fully.
Opaque, which they do,
for five seconds.
It's still gonna be opaque
until it completely fades out.
But that's just
the way this works.
You just gotta
get used to that.
The animations always
happen after the fact,
over time, okay?
But the changes you make
happen immediately.
All right?
Here's some of the options
we can do when we animate,
I talked about
the curveLinear,
which is at the very bottom,
right above it,
you see curveEaseInEaseOut,
and curveEaseIn.
These basically make it so
that, instead of just linearly
going from the start value
to the end value of that var
change, it starts off slowly,
then goes up to normal speed,
and then slows down at the end
now, why do you want this?
This is especially good for
moving, when you're
moving a view.
You don't want a view to be
on screen and go [sound].
You want to kinda go and
then slow down at the end.
It just feels, if you move
something in real life,
if you don't jerk it up here,
you lift it up and
then, you set it down.
Same thing here.
You want to lift it a few up,
move it over, and
then set it down, okay?
So, that's why curve ease in,
ease out.
So, you can control whether
it eases on either end.
Going to the one on the top,
begin from current state.
Remember I said
that that finished,
argument to the completion
handler would
only be true if the animation
got all the way finished.
Well, if you issue another
animation while this
ones like the previous one's
still in flight during that
If you issue another one that
changes alpha in some other
five seconds.
way, well, either that
animation's gonna start from
the new value of
alpha which is zero.
Okay, even though it's
still in flight and
hasn't shown that zero to
the user, it still is zero.
Or, whether the animation of
the alpha, the new animation's
gonna pick up wherever
the other one is, okay?
So, in another word, this is
gonna pick up mid-flight and
make the alpha go
somewhere else.
So that's what begin from
current state says should I
look at what the user
perceives, or is seeing
as that alpha, or should I
just use the real alpha,
which has already
been changed to zero?
Okay.
So you can look through
the documentation for
all these options,
I think there's 25 of them,
so there's a lot of cool
things you can do there.
And we'll talk about
some more of them
some of these other
UIView animations.
All right.
So that's the UIView animation
where you're animating one
of these five special bars.
So it's another thing you can
do with UIView animation,
is what if I have a view, and
Imma change a whole lot of
things about it, not just
those special bars and
to redrawn a different way,
and
I wanna animate that
whole change on screen.
And there is a number of
ways you can animate it.
One, you can animate
it by flipping over.
So kind of like a plane card,
would flip over
from the old view.
Make all your changes,
flips over.
Shows the new one.
Another one is cross dissolve.
Okay the old one showing.
Then the new one dissolves in
another one is curling up.
The new one is kind
of in the back.
The old one sitting up front.
And the old one curls up like
a piece of paper and shows
part of the new one in the
back, which is kind of fun.
That transition really
only make sense if you're
covering the whole screen.
It wouldn't make sense to have
a curl up be in just a like
view inside another view.
The whole screen was a view,
you wanna curl up would
make sense, okay?
So, this is entire view
contents animation,
not just those special things.
It's done with a class method.
It's called animate width.
And it's, sorry,
transition width.
Not animate with.
And transition width takes the
view that it has all the stuff
you wanna change.
Duration obviously,
some options like whether
you're curling or
cross dissolving or
flipping and
then the animations now in
this case the green animations
can change anything
about the view.
Not just the five
special things but
absolutely anything.
So that's what these
animations are gonna do there,
and then the completion
is the same.
Okay, when the animation
is done it tells you.
So what's an example of
this let's say I'm making
a poker game and
I want to show a playing
card flipping over okay.
So let's have a playing card
view myPlayingCardView
right there.
And it's got some bar
on it cardIsFaceUp And
if cards face up this true,
then I got to see all
the kings and
ace of hearts or whatever.
And if the cards face
down then I just see
the back of the card.
So I got this view.
And I got it currently in
one side and another and
I want it to flip over and
show the other state.
Well here all I do is I do
animate I do transition width
my playing card view.
I'm gonna do it in three
quarter of a seconds.
So it's gonna be
pretty fast flip over.
I'm using the option
transition flip from left,
which takes the left edge and
flips it over.
And then inside animation so
I'm just changing that
cardIsFaceUp bar,
the thing that controls which
one my view is showing.
And so
this is going to flip over and
show the card in the other
direction, okay?
So that's cool,
that's when you wanna change
the whole view.
But you're limit even
what kind of you know,
animation you can do,
just flipping, dissolving and
curling up in
it's full screen.
there's another kind of change
of views you wanna make which
All right,
is a change to view hierarchy.
So, this means you wanna put
views in or take views out of
the view hierarchy or
replace one view with another.
So this method is
transition from two.
So the from view is
the view that's gonna be
leaving the view hierarchy,
and the two view is
the view that's gonna be
coming into the hierarchy.
They don't have to be in
the same place, by the way,
they can be in different
places on the screen,
that's absolutely fine.
usually they are in
the same place.
And this animation here you
notice that there is no
animation block because
implicitly what you're doing
in this animation is replacing
the one view with the other.
I'm going from one view to
another, so you've got the new
view all set up the way
you want presumably and
you've got the old view and
you just transition across.
Now, Sometimes you don't want
to actually remove these
from the hierarchy, you just
want to show and hide them.
And so in the options you put
.showHideTransitionViews.
Then instead of remove
from superview and
adding subview,
it will just set the .hidden.
Remember view has a .hidden
bar that will hide it.
And it'd set one to hidden and
one to not hidden.
All right?
I don't know maybe
that property is called
these days, anyway.
All right so those are all
ways to animate view so
let's look at doing a couple
of those in FaceIt so
first I'm gonna do
the animation where we
change the entire view,
and do flipping or
cross-dissolving, to cause the
blinking to be a lot smoother.
And what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna take the two eyes
in my face, replace them with
views, that draw the eye,
and then I'm gonna have
the view change from
open to closed doing
a flip from top.
See how that's gonna make
it the eyes blinking.
It's gonna flip over.
That little circle is
gonna flip over like that.
And then,
we're gonna shake the head.
This is a 2D head, so
it's gonna shake it side to
side instead of like this.
Cuz it's only 2D.
And we're gonna do that
with the thing where we're
gonna change one of
the special bars.
The bar we're gonna change is
transform because we're gonna
rotate our entire face.
Okay, so let's do those.
Let's go back to Xcode here.
All right, so, to do the eye
blinking, we need to
have the eyes not be drawn, so
right now, if we go to, oops,
if we go to our FaceView right
here, you can see that we
draw our eyes by doing
this UIBezierPath Right?
And then down here if
you remember in draw,
we get the path for the I.
And for both I's and
we stroke it.
So we're not gonna
do this anymore.
Instead, we're gonna add two
I views, which I'm gonna show
you in a second, as subviews
of this phase view.
So we're not gonna do that.
And we're not gonna need this.
Actually I am gonna
grab this Center
of Eye out of here because
I still will need to
put my new Eye views somewhere
and that knows how to do it.
So the rest of this though,
I'm just gonna comment out.
Okay?
So we're not using
that mechanism for
drawing, instead
we're gonna Eye view.
Now in interest of time, I'm
gonna drag this Eye view in.
And show it to you.
So we'll copy it in here.
All right, so what is
this EyeView look like?
And super simple, it has line,
width, and color too,
just like the face does.
It has eyesOpen,
which would be the Bool
whether they're true or
not, and then it's draw-rect
just if the eyes are open it
uses an oval bezierpath,
which is actually circle, and
if the eyes are closed it
just does move to line two.
Okay, this is pretty much the
exact same code that was in
the The faceview and then here
at setting it's line with
setting it's color, stroking
color and then stroking it.
And what this does?
Any question about this code?
Super straightforward,
all right?
So we need to fix our faceview
over here to use those eye's,
those eye views instead.
So how are we gonna do that?
It's really just a matter of
creating these eyeViews and
then putting them
in a right place.
All right?
So
let's start with
creating them.
So I'm gonna have a private
var and I'm gonna try to say,
leftEye = createEye, and then
have a private funk called
createEye Which returns
an EyeView let's say okay and
it will return it now,
I wanna do this but
it's not gonna work,
does anyone see what's
definitely not gonna work
about code just like this?
Okay, what I'm I doing here?
I'm initializing
leftEye right?
And am I allowed to call
a method on my self before
I fully initialized?
No, okay, so that's why
that's not gonna work there.
And you can see that the error
is cannot use instance member
'createEye' cuz property
initializers run before 'self'
is available.
That's exactly what
we think here.
So a fix for
this is to make this lazy.
Cause if you make this lazy,
it's not going to actually
run this initialization, this
initialization is not going to
run until we are fully
initialized.
By definition because no
one can call this LeftEye,
no one can access this until
we're fully initialized.
So,that's great.
Now this doesn't work either,
okay?
And why doesn't this work?
This doesn't work bec-, and
maybe we'll even see
an error here, yeah.
Let's see, yeah, okay.
So you see it says you
cannot use member createEye.
When you do lazy vars you
need to specify the type.
Okay, so you need to say.
You have to explicitly type.
You can't,
let it infer the type.
So that thing.
Now, there's still
a problem here.
Another problem.
It's saying here,
use of instance me,
member create type
on face view.
Type face view.
Did you mean on a value
of face view instead.
And in fact, exactly, we did.
It's trying to find
a static function called
createEye, right?
A static function.
But we don't want that.
We want an instance one, and
the way we specify
that is with self.
Self says I want createEye
that's on an instance like
this, not one that's static.
So that can be a little
complicated, right there.
Okay?
Let's get through that but
just to know this
is the way to get around
having to write and
an initializer now obviously
I'm not providing a frame, so
I'm gonna have to set its size
and position here sometime.
Notice my eye is not
going to be opaque.
That's because I,
if my face was blue or
something, I would want
that blue to show through.
I wouldn't want it to
be opaque and so this
eye is going to be completely
transparent except for
the parts that I draw with
non-transparent colored ink,
basically.
I'm going to set my color
equal to the color of my face.
I'm going to set my eyes lines
with to be the same lines with
the face.
Remember this is
just bars here.
And face view right?
Color in line with color.
And I'm also going to just add
subview, this eye because
I'm at face view I'm gonna
add this subview as a subview
of myself and I'm gonna return
the eye because this is
the createEye returns the eye.
Okay, everyone understand
this little method?
Quite simple.
I'm just configuring this eye,
and using it for
the left and the right eye.
What about
positioning this eye?
There, I didn't say
where this eye is.
the sub-view it's in the upper
left corner size zero zero, so
I added it for
that's no good.
Lets create a private here.
Called positionEye,
and it's positionEye.
Hello.
PositionEye.
And it's gonna take an eye,
it's gonna be an eye view.
And it's gonna take
the position to put it,
where to put it center which
is gonna be a CGPoint.
And we need to get the size
of the eye, well, the size of
the eye remember depends
on the size of the face, so
in a big face the eye is big,
in a small face the eye is
small and if you remember
we have these nice little
score radius constants.
So, I have this ratios,
score radius to eye radius,
remember that?
And I'm gonna make it
two cuz here I'm talking
about the width and
height of my view, and
the radius is only radius,
not diameter.
So I'm having to say
times two there.
So now, I know how big this
little EyeView needs to be.
And so I'm gonna say
eye.frame = CGReft For
now we'll have the origin be,
CGPoint.zero, I'll,
I'll put it in this center
right here in a second, but
right now I'm gonna make
the origin zero, and
the size is a CGSize, where
the width is the size and
the height is the size,
it's square Okay and now
we'll just set the eyes center
equal to the center there.
Okay, an equal
sign right there.
this little guy right here is
just gonna position the eye.
Okay, so
Now, when do we wanna
position that eye?
Okay now this is
very important.
When we're in a view
controller, we know when our
bounds of our top level
view changes, because we
get viewDidLayoutSubviews
sent to us, remember that?
If we're a view,
this faceView is a view,
not a controller, a view.
It gets told whenever its
bounds changes by being sent
the message, layoutSubviews.
Okay?
So, lay out subviews,
you said sent to all views
when it's bound changes or
anytime that its subviews
need to be relaid out.
And that's exactly
what we want here,
we gotta relay out those Eyes.
We've gotta move those Eyes
to their current position.
So, what is that position?
We're just gonna say position
Eye, we'll do both eyes so
let's do the left eye first.
And to get the position of the
eye we have this nice method,
center of eye that we pulled
out of the thing that we
commented here, path for eye.
It knows how to calculate
the position of a given eye.
So, we'll just say that
the position here is center
of eye.
And we'll say we want
the left eye in this case.
That, and all right, and
there's something, sorry
this is positionEye center,
okay, so that's our left eye.
Now let's do our right eye.
Okay, everybody got that?
So every time our
balance changes,
we get layoutSubviews,
we're gonna move those eyes
to wherever they're
supposed to be,
the centerOfEye thing, okay?
We got an extra argument,
I guess I didn't,
I made that be that.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Okay?
All right,
what else do we need to do?
Only one other thing
we need to do is that,
remember that the eyes want to
have the same color in line
with and whether or
not they're.
Open as the face.
Okay, so all these places up
here where we set eyes open
and where set the line within
color we need to forward that
on to our left and right eyes,
so let's do it here for
color first.
Let's go down here.
Now, for color we still need
setNeedDispaly because other
things in the view besides
the eyes are certain color,
the mouth, etcetera.
But we do need to say,
that our left eyes color
equals this new color.
And also our right eyes color
equals the new color and
exactly the same here.
For the lineWidth we
want to say that our left
eye's lineWidth equals
our lineWidth and
our right eye's lineWidth
equals our lineWidth.
And probably most importantly,
when the eyes are opened and
closed on our face view
we want to have that set.
In our views, now, notice that
we don't need setNeedsDisplay
anymore because we don't draw
the eyes in our draw(_rect's.
See in our draw(
_rect) down here?
We commented that out.
We don't draw the eyes.
The eyes are drawn by these
two sub views that we
added with add sub view there.
So here we can get rid
of setNeedsDisplay.
and instead we're just gonna
say leftEye.eyesOpen =
eyesOpen and rightEye.eyesOpen
= eyesOpen, okay?
See how we're just forwarding
that on to those two views.
Right, any questions
about that?
Let's go make sure we haven't
broken anything here by
making our eyes be
separate views.
Our views, overall our
face views should look
exactly the same.
It's just using sub-views
to draw part of itself
rather than,
drawing it in DrawRec.
And sure enough
it's working fine.
It's even continuing
to blink because that
blinking is done
by the controller.
The controller is setting
eyes open, eyes closed,
eyes open eyes closed and
that's being forwarded on.
To the view and is blinking.
Now of course, this, we
haven't changed the animation
so it's still kind
of this instablink.
So now we want to use the UI
view animation to make that
blinking a lot smoother.
So how are we gonna do that?
Let's go over to our
eye view right here.
And every time eyes open
is changed, instead of just
changing it, we're going
to animate that change.
So we are going to
instantly change it.
But on screen it's going
to be animated, All right?
So to do that I'm actually
going to make eyes open
be private var right there and
I'm going to create
the public eyes open.
Which is a Bool and
this thing is going to be the
thing that does the animation.
Okay?
And, because setting
this eyesOpen does
the NeedsDisplay,
which causes this,
I still want all
that functionality,
it's just that when someone
publicly sets my eyes open,
I want to animate, the change
that's going on there, so,
how am I gonna do this?
All right, when someone gets
whether the eyes are open,
I'm just gonna return the
private eyesOpen All right.
And if they set this
eyes opening thing.
And they're gonna say, if
the new I'm gonna
do this UIView.transition
with view, okay?
Not this one.
I want transition with view,
not from to, which
remember is removing things
from the view hierarchy.
This one is transitioning
inside of view and so
I'm gonna do self as the view.
This is the EyeView.
The duration, I should
make it constant here, but
I'll just say point four
to make this expedient.
The options I want to
transition from top to bottom
because an eye blink kind
of comes from the top, so
we'll do that and
then here are the animations
we're going to do right here.
And, I don't actually need
this completion because we're
not gonna do anything
when it's done.
Notice that that's
an optional closure.
You see how it's
got a question mark
on the end of it?
So, I will just not
include that whole thing.
All right, so
what do I wanna do in here?
In here, I wanna make all
the changes to the view
that I want to be animated.
Well here, it's super simple.
I'm just gonna set my underbar
i's open to be the new value.
All right,
we're in set here so
new value is whatever sum
of that eyes open equal.
So here I'm just gonna
set it to the new value.
That's going to change my view
to I, the new eyeOpen state.
And I'm going to animate
getting to there, all right?
So let's take a look.
This guy should
still be blinking.
But he should be blinking
a lot smoother, you see?
Cuz it's animating the actual
motion of the eyes closing.
Like that, and
again works in all.
All right,
now the next thing we gonna do
is have this guy
shake his head, so
I'm just gonna rotate
the entire view okay?
He's gonna shake his head by
going little to the left.
All the way back
over to the right,
and then back to the middle.
That's gonna be shaking
his head, okay?
That's the best I can
do in 2D right here.
So, how are we
gonna do that one?
We're gonna do that one by
animating one of those special
bars in UI View,
which is the transform.
So let's go,
we're gonna do this in
our FaceView controller.
Okay.
So, it's gonna something about
is kind of all phases can do,
so, we'll put it in there.
Let's put it right in here,
I think, it's a good space for
it, some room, and
I have some Constance for
this, a headshake Constance.
So, angle is just the angle
I'm gonna to turn to the left
and angle back
to the right and
remember that we're
in radians in here.
So it's zero two pi to go all
the way around a circle so
I'm going to go pi over six,
which is a little bit
around the circle.
And then segment duration is
how long I'm gong to take
to do each turn, to the left,
back to the right, and
back to the middle, okay so
each of those are going
to take, in this case,
half a second.
So before I write
the animation code,
I'm gonna make a nice
little private func here
called rotateFace(by:).
And it's gonna take
a CGFloat which is radians,
number of degrees
to rotate the face.
And it's gonna rotate it.
And the way we
do this is just,
we take
the faceView.transform.
Okay remember we're on
the control over here so
faceView a vara vars and we're
gonna make it equal to the
faceViews.transform.rotated
by.
Rotated by that amount.
Okay, to make to make
this a little nicer,
we'll say, by angle, by angle.
Okay, so, this is just a nice
little function that rotates
the face at any amount of
degrees and 'm gonna use this
inside my animation code
to rotate the face.
Anybody cool with that
of what that code does?
So, transform right here.
Is alpine transform
rotated by,
is just a method on
CGF transform.
ShakeHead cuz it's gonna shake
the head back and forth.
And it's gonna be animated, so
I'm gonna say right off the
bat right, UIView.animate and
the one I want here for
animation is this one right
here because I need
the completion.
Why do I need the completion?
Because the way I'm gonna
make this rotation happen is
I'm gonna rotate to the left
and when it completes.
I rotate to the right.
And when that one completes,
I rotate back to the middle.
So, do you see why I need
to know when each rotation
is completed.
So, that's why I need this
animate with duration that
has completion at the end.
Now, this one also has
completion but it has options.
We don't need any option.
We're just gonna use standard,
animation.
We're not gonna ease in, ease
out or any of that business.
Okay, so
this is the one we want.
Just to make this
a little more readable,
I'm gonna do this little
trick that I often do.
Just so you can see each
argument one by one.
So the duration of a tilt is
the HeadShake.segmentDuration,
okay, that constant
that I put up here.
The animations, okay,
this is what we're going to do
to cause this
animation to happen.
Well, we're just gonna
rotate the face.
Now this ro, first rotation
is to rotate to the left.
And in iOS, different
from Mac OS by the way.
In iOS, positive values of
angles are counter clockwise.
So we want a positive angle,
cuz we're going
to the left here.
So I'm gonna make this
be my HeadShake.angle.
Okay, it's gonna rotate
by the HeadShake.angle.
That's gonna head it
off to the left there.
Now when it's done here,
this completion code
which has finished,
whether it's finished or not,
and I do want to wait for
it to be finished.
Actually, I'm going to,
I think, yeah, put this inside
here just to make this a
little easier for you to see.
But this is the completion,
okay.
So that guy there,
that guy there, okay.
So this is the code that
happens when it's completed.
And if it has yeah,
sorry, self.rotate.
By the way, do we need memory
cycle breakage here, etc?
No, because we're in the
middle of an animation, okay?
That view controller
is on the screen.
We do not have to worry about
creating memory cycles here.
Because we know that thing
is gonna be in the heap.
Because it better
be in the heap,
cuz we're animating right now!
So this is a case where
we don't really need
to do weak self and
all that stuff.
All right, so
when it completes,
we're gonna say if it
finished, which it should.
Because I'm not issuing
any other animations here.
But one day, maybe I'll
add some new animation.
In which case,
I might interrupt this.
But, so it's always
good to check finished,
even if you're 100% sure this
thing is always gonna finish.
Which we are in this case,
as our code is written now.
So if it's finished,
what I want to do now is
animate going back
over to the right.
So I'm just gonna
UIView.animate withDuration
again, okay.
And again, I want the one
with completion here.
Okay, and this time, I'm gonna
do the same amount of time
to go back to the right.
So let's HeadShake.
You could imagine that maybe
this duration would wanna be
different since
I'm going farther.
But actually, I think it's
probably right to have to be
this way, as you'll see.
And these are kinda concepts
you can play with to make your
HeadShake look like
the way you want.
And here at the animations,
I'm gonna rotate my face
back the other way.
So it's gonna have to
be a negative value.
And I want to go twice as far,
so
I'm gonna do
HeadShake.angl*2.
Okay, I'm gonna go all the way
back, past the middle, and
over to the right.
And then here, for the
completion here, I'm going to
again line this up so you can
see it a little better, click.
So inside the completion here,
I'm gonna rotate
back to the middle.
So yet another,
in fact, watch this.
Copy, paste.
Although with this one,
I don't need a completion one
at the end because I
have completed it.
And here obviously,
I'm not going backwards.
I'm going forwards again,
which forwards is
counter clockwise there.
All right,
that's everything there.
And what else do we got here?
Oops, forgot a curly
brace there, comma.
What else?
We're missing some curly
braces or something, yeah.
What do we got here?
This is finished in,
That's it.
No, wait, what else do we got?
This doesn't match anything.
Yeah it does, it matches this.
Okay, hold on.
Anybody see where I'm
missing a Animations,
another curly brace
missing right there.
And I do think we're gonna
need a curly brace there.
Okay, lots of curly braces and
parentheses there.
We're doing it, we got it.
Okay, so everyone understand
what's going on here?
So we're just shaking back and
forth.
You know, I know that's gonna
finish because I don't have
any other animations going on
that might interfere with it.
But to be correct, I should
probably always put that,
if finished, in there if
that's what I intend.
Sometimes I gonna do something
even if it doesn't finish.
But in this case,
I do want it.
All right,
let's take a look at this.
And this is a very interesting
combination of animations
going on here,
as you're gonna see.
All right, so, sorry.
Let's make some action
cause it to shake its head.
Okay, let's do taps.
Right now if we tap,
it blinks the eyes.
But we already got
a blinking eye right now, so
we don't need tap anymore.
So I'm gonna go up
here to tap right here,
this tapRecognizer.
And I'm gonna
comment this out.
And I'm gonna show you
a different way to do
just a recognizer.
Did I show you how to
do just your recognizer
directly in the storyboard?
I don't think I've
shown that yet, so
let me show you
how to do that.
It's really easy,
we're gonna go to our
storyboard right here.
And this will actually
show another cool thing.
So here is my MVC.
I'm gonna bring up my
assistant editor so
that I can connect to it.
And you're gonna see
that it brings up
BlinkingFaceViewController.
Now I wanna make a connection
to a gestureRecognizer here.
I don't want it to be in
BlinkingFace controller,
I want it to be in
the super class.
But it knows that this
MVC right here is a
BlinkingFacingViewController,
so it's trying to
automatic show it to me.
So how can I get
FaceViewController here, and
am I allowed to hook
up to the super class?
And the answer is,
you are allowed to hook it up.
And the easiest way to do
it is to hold down Option,
the Option key, and
click on it over here.
Cuz Option means open it
up in the assistant editor.
So now I have
the FaceViewController here.
And so now I could wire
up a gesture to that.
All right, so how do I wire up
a gesture from my UI without
typing code like all
this stuff right here?
And the answer is,
we go to the Utilities window
and search for gesture.
And you'll see that there's
quite a few gestures here,
that you can do tap gestures,
pinch gestures, rotation,
swipe gestures, etc.
And you just get the view
that you want here,
let me zoom in on it some.
So you got this,
this FaceView right here.
And you just drag the kind
of gesture you want,
like a tap gesture,
on top of it.
And that's gonna make this
view recognize a tap gesture.
Now where did it appear?
It appeared right
here at the top.
And I can click on it and
inspect it over here actually.
I can set how many
taps we want,
how many fingers we
want to go down.
All that stuff we do in code,
we can do it here.
And then how do I get this
tap gesture to actually
do something in my code?
Well I just Ctrl + drag,
of course.
I'm gonna hold
down Control and
drag from this tap
gesture in here.
I want an Action.
Okay, it's going to be
TapGesture as the argument.
I'm gonna call this
also shakeHead.
Same name, but
this one has the argument of
the tapGestureRecognizer.
Okay, everyone see that,
how to hook up a gesture
in the storyboard?
It's pretty simple actually.
I prefer actually
to do it in code.
And why do I prefer
to do these gestures
in code like this?
I just find that
those gestures that
are in the storyboard
are a little hidden.
They're up in that
tiny bar up there, and
I don't really notice
them sometimes.
So, so,
I kind of like to do this.
But it's personal
preference really.
There's nothing wrong with
doing them in the storyboard.
Some people would
say that's better
cuz then everything
is in the storyboard.
It's really easy to see
what the gestures are.
Eh, either way.
All right, so
here's our shakeHead gesture.
What are we gonna do?
Well, we're gonna shakeHead,
all right?
We're just gonna call this
animated one up here.
Everybody got that?
Let's clean up our white
space a little bit here.
All right, so
let's run this time.
And now we can tap on our face
and it should shake its head
left and then right,
and back to left.
Sorry left and then, right
back the middle, all right.
So, here we go,
this guy is blinking, okay,
it's done again, no matter
what kind of guy is and
let's tap,
he went the other way.
So, I was wrong,
I was get this wrong about
which way is which in iOS.
So actually, I guess
positive values are yes,
clockwise, I guess.
I think the documentation
is backwards on this,
if I remember correct, and
they might have fixed it,
but anyway.
So we go forward and
then back.
Now, a couple interesting
things to note here.
Look at our other animation.
It continues perfectly happy.
It does not care that
we're rotating this view.
It's completely
irrelevant to that, and
that's the way
animations work.
As long as they're not
touching the same values,
they can work completely
independently.
Another thing to note here
is this is a sub view
of this view.
And when I transform it,
it moves
all of the sub views with it,
which is kinda cool, okay.
So even if you build
a view out of sub views,
then if you animate it,
rotate it or
whatever, the sub views
will get rotated as well.
All right, everybody got that?
All right.
That's all l wanted
to show you.
So that's the power
of UIB animation.
I'm not even shown you a lot
of the cool things you can do
like moving views.
Okay, having views moving
across the screen.
The reason I didn't show you
that with this view animation
is pretty obvious how
would you do it but
also because on Wednesday,
I'm gonna be showing you
really powerful way to
move you with this across
the screen with this
physic phase one which is
the next thing we're gonna
talk about with the slides.
All right,
let's back into the slides.
All right, so,
dynamic animation.
Now, this is a different
approach than the UI-based
animation I just said.
what you do is set up all
this physics like gravity and
In this case,
things like that and then you
just put the UIViews in there
and they get affected by those
physics, and they move around.
Okay, this is the best of
fundamental I do it now,
how do you do it?
What's the mechanism for
doing it?
First, you're gonna wanna
create an instance of this
class called
UIDynamicAnimator, okay?
A UIDynamicAnimator is
the thing that controls all
the physics based animation
in a view hierarchy.
Okay?
We'll show you
how to create
that in a second.
Then, you're gonna add what
are called UIDynamicBehaviors
to that animator.
And as soon as you add
a behavior to an animator,
it will start
behaving that way.
And then finally you're gonna
add UIDynamicItems, which
are usually UIViews, 99% of
the time, to those behaviors.
And then, those behaviors will
start acting on those views.
So that's it, it's a three
stage, three level thing.
You got the animator,
you add behaviors to it,
those behaviors
start happening.
You add UIViews
to the behaviors,
now they start being
effected by the behaviors.
You can do it in any order.
You could put the views in
the behaviors first and
behaviors and the animator,
whichever you want to do.
So how do you create
a UIDynamicAnimator?
All it needs is the coordinate
system it's going to work in.
Okay?
So UIDynamicAnumator,
it's constructor here takes
the argument ref into view.
This is just the UI view whose
coordinate system is gonna be
the coordinate system for
all the animation
that we're doing.
Now, the views don't have be,
all the drawing doesn't have
to be in one view it can be
in a whole bunch of views but
they have to be in the same
view hierarchy and
you're gonna want reference
view at the top of that
view hierarchy, okay?
That's the only
restriction there.
So now,
you start adding behaviors.
So you do that by creating
concrete instances
of UIDynamicBehavior,
in other words sub classes
to do what you want.
So, there's
a gravity behavior,
which creates what seems to be
gravity, pulling the views.
a collision behavior where the
views run into something like
And, or
the edge of the screen or
another view and
they bounce off.
Okay?
And we're gonna talk about
all these dynamic
behaviors and
how we configure
them in a minute.
And then the UIDynamicItems,
one thing to note about
the UIDynamicItems is that
if you add, let's say
you have item1 and item2 like
in this example right here.
I've added Item 1 and
2 to the gravity.
So they're both affected by
the gravity behavior, but
I only added Item
1 to the collider.
Let's say,
it's a collision behavior and
let's say there's
a boundary at the bottom.
So one, let's say
the gravity goes down, and
there's a boundary at
the bottom for the collider.
Items 1 and
2 are gonna accelerate down
towards where the gravity
is pulling them but
then item2 is gonna
keep on going.
And item1 is gonna bounce
off the boundary, okay.
So if you don't add the UIView
to a certain behavior,
it won't be affected
by that behavior.
Now, these items that
you add to behaviors
implement this protocol
called UIDynamicItem,
which UIView already
was implementing.
Okay, before they
even invented this,
because all this in
the UIDynamicItem protocol is
balance, which you
just get because your
balance are affected
by your transform, and
so, you get your balance so
you know where to draw.
And then, setter, sorry,
the center and the transform
are things that can be set.
So, the animator can really
only change where the view is
and its rotation and scale.
Okay, that's all that
the animator did, but
that's a lot.
Okay, rotation scale you can
see, especially center where
the thing is, is a lot of what
the animator is, is doing.
Now, one interesting thing is
once you add a dynamic item
to a behavior that's been
added to an animator,
then the animator has control
over its center and transform.
And if you wanna
change the center and
transform without removing it
from the Dynamic animator,
you've gotta tell the Dynamic
animator, hey, I change this.
Otherwise, it's gonna change
it right back to what it
thinks it is.
Right.
So don't fight your
dynamic animator if you
wanna change the center or
transform a view that you've
added to an animator.
You have to tell the animator
using this method right here.
Update item using
current state.
And you just pass the UIView
that you change the center or
transform of.
And it will pick up what
you changed it to, and
continue from there.
Let's talk about some of
the specific behaviors.
All right?
There's gravity behavior.
So, gravity behavior,
it's just like gravity.
And by default, when you
create a gravity behavior,
the gravity is down
which means kind of down
towards the home button,
basically in portrait mode.
And, its, magnitude is 1g.
[LAUGH] Okay, 1.0.
And 1.0 means 1,000 points per
second per second per second.
Remember that gravity
is an acceleration.
Okay, hopefully you all have
enough physics to know that
gravity is an acceleration.
Anybody know what
the gravity on Earth is?
9.8 meters per second square,
right?
So, in screen it's
a thousand points per second
squared and what's really
interesting about a thousand
points per second squared
it's a very round number but
it feels a lot like 9.8
meters per second squared.
Now, if you have your
phone you put the UI,
a view at the top and
you apply this gravity
behaviour to it, it will fall
almost exactly the same as
real life object would fall.
It's really pretty
amazing actually.
And yet it's such a round
number like that.
So you can tweet
these numbers though,
you could have
the gravity be up.
For example,
when I pull out my phone and
I swipe up from the bottom,
okay.
Feel free to do it if
you want right now.
When you swipe up
from the bottom,
the little control
panel comes up.
If kind of flies up,
that's actually using this
mechanism and its gravity up.
So, gravity is actually
pulling that thing up
when you swipe.
And what's more, when it hits,
you notice it doesn't
just come up and
stop, it kind of bounces
a little, off the end, okay?
And that's
a collision behavior.
So that thing coming up is
a combination of a gravity
behavior and a collision
behavior or it might be using
a snap behavior, which
we'll see in a second too.
So anyway, that's gravity,
and you can see gravity
in any direction, and
we're going to do that in our
demo on Wednesday quite a bit.
Another one is
an attachment behaviour.
This allows you to take
two dynamic items, or
a dynamic, dynamic item and
a fixed point and
attach them at some
distance apart.
And how would this play out?
Well, let's say I
had a UIView and
I attached it to this
a center point and
let's say that UIView, in
addition to being affected by
this attachment behavior was
also affected by gravity.
Then it would come down and
swing like a pendulum.
Okay, because the attachment
behavior would
be constantly attaching
it to this point.
But the gravity would be
constantly trying to pull it
down and it would swing.
Do you see?
So that's an attachment
behavior.
The attachment behavior,
one thing that's
really cool about it,
you can change the length of
the attachment in real time.
So the thing is animating and
you can be changing the
distance that is attached, so
you can create all kinds of
crazy, motions using that.
All right, CollisionBehavior.
CollisionBehavior is
exactly what you think.
You can setup collisions.
The collisions can either
be between all the items
that are in the behavior.
They're being affected
by the behavior.
And or
any number of boundaries and
these boundaries are just
UIBezierPaths so you can
register these UIBezierPaths
with the CollisionBehavior and
all the items that
are affected by behavior will
bounce off of those
boundaries, okay?
They could be round,
they could be curved,
they could be any
path that you want.
A common boundary by the way
you want to put is a boundary
all the way around
the reference area.
Just to contain all
the items inside.
And you can do that with this
var translate reference bounds
If you set that on a collision
behavior, then it will
into boundary.
kind of automatically put
a boundary around the edge and
keep everything Inside
the reference bounds.
Now you notice the argument
here these boundaries have
identifiers so
that you can tell which ones
you hit when they hit and I'm
gonna show you how you find
out about that in a second but
you notice the identifier is
an NSCopying you've never
seen NSCopying there before,
NSCopying for the purposes of
this basically means NSString
or NSNumber Okay, so the
identifier could be a number
or a string but there's NSs.
Now, that's no problem
because you can just
as them to a string or
to an Int if you wanna,
use Int as your identifiers
but you do have to do that as.
So, NSCopying is basically
NSString or NSNumber Number,
now, why do we need
that identifier?
Because when a collision
happens with a boundary,
the collision, behavior has a
delegate, and it'll tell you.
So, if you set yourself as the
collision behavior's delegate,
then, if you have any
boundaries set in there, or
if two items are colliding
with each other, you're gonna
get this sent to you, this is
a collisionDelegate method
CollisionBehavior begin or
ended contact for
some UIDynamicItem, UI View,
if this bouncing around
in there with the boundary
identifier NSCopying.
So, there's that identifier
telling you this boundary that
you sent is doing this and
leave and
tell you the point at which
those two things collided
If you're, if it's talking
about collision within two UI
dynamic items then it'll say
with UIDynamicItem instead of
withBoundaryIdentifier.
Okay?
So this is really cool.
When the collisions happen
you get to find out
that they happen.
And again, we're gonna use
that in our demo as well.
All right.
SnapBehavior.
So a SnapBehavior is basically
move this view from here
to over here behavior.
And why it's called
the snap behavior is,
it doesn't move it over
there really jerky and
kind of stiff, it moves it
over and when it gets there,
it's almost like four springs
are attached to the corners
and it kind of
vibrates a little bit.
It flies over there, probably
eases in, then eases out, and
then when it gets there, it
kind of shakes a little bit.
Okay, like there's
springs in the corner.
And you can set the stiffness
of those springs with damping.
So, highly damped, they'll
come in and just [SOUND] stop.
And really springy springs,
they'll come in and
kinda really bounce around
when it arrives in there.
go [SOUND],
So, why do we do that?
Because when we move things
across screen to a new place
In real life we don't want
it to feel so abrupt.
Right.
When we move things,
again we want things
to feel smooth, and
so snap to is
definitely the way to
move something to a known
place with the system.
Similarly there is something
called pushBehavior,
a pushBehavior gives
a UIview a push.
Okay, so we already know how
to make the UIviews accelerate
towards somewhere
with gravity.
Push is almost like
imparting a velocity to it.
Now, there is two
kinds of push.
There is instantaneous push
which is just one time push,
okay in parts
a certain energy to it.
There you can see magnitude
1.0 is a 100 x100 view,
would get a 100 pts/s/s.
Is kinda push to it.
But then there's also
continuous push which is
you just push along behind.
So that's velocity.
Okay, you're giving
the thing velocity.
Cuz you're just constantly
pushing it at some rate.
So you can do both
things there.
One thing that's really
annoying about push behaviors
is the instantaneous ones.
You add the behavior to the,
animator.
Right?
And then, it pushes it and
then just sits there
doing nothing,
okay it doesn't like disappear
after you spontaneous push,
even though I mean I'm
not gonna push it again.
So we want to clean that up
and I'm gonna show you towards
the end of this talk how those
instantaneous pushes, but
it is a little
annoying that does it.
Now continuous push is
different because it's
constantly pushing so you
don't want it to be cleaned up
if you want to be
sitting there pushing.
There's another kind of
behavior which is kind of
a meta behavior, called
the dynamic item behavior.
Okay?
Dynamic item behavior,
not dynamic behavior,
dynamic item behavior.
And, this I like to think
of as the physics behavior.
This is essentially
describing the physics
that apply when all the other
behaviors do stuff, okay?
So this is things like,
allows rotation.
That's saying like,
if two things collide, should
they be allowed to spin off?
Or do they have to keep,
you know, non-rotated,
bounce off non-rotated.
Friction, after things bounce
off each other, or if they're
just moving around, do they
get slowed down by friction?
Okay, so if you have gravity
and there's friction.
They're not gonna
accelerate as fast because
they're being slow down.
Elasticity when things
banging to each other do they
bounce off with the same
energy they had coming in?
That would be elasticity
1.0 or do they gain
energy by collision that would
be elasticity above 1.0.
Or did they lose energy as
they collide each other that
would be elasticity
less than 1.0.
Okay, so you see how this,
is the behaviour just like
a collision behaviour or
a grably behaviour or
push behaviour.
But it's a behavior
that's like meta,
it's like describing how these
things should behave and
all the other behaviors.
These behaviour also can
tell you the linear velocity
of an item which is actually
interesting to know.
And why do I wanna know the
linear velocity of an item?
A lot of times,
if I got a view, an MBC and
it's animating.
And then, I click away from
it like a Tab bar or I,
in the navigation controller,
I push something else on.
I wanna pause that animation.
Well, there's no
real way to pause.
Okay, when your view goes
off screen, when your view
controller disappears,
you're going to want to remove
the behaviors from the
animator and stop animating.
cuz you don't want to be
animating not on screen.
Okay, it's a waste of energy.
But when you go to the view,
you want all of the animated
things to continue
as they were.
Well they will except for
they'll have lost
all their velocity.
So you have to put
their velocity back.
So you grab all their
linear velocities,
store them away somewhere and
when you come back,
add the linear velocity back.
You could also use the linear
velocity here to put a speed
limit on objects.
If we have time on Wednesday,
which I doubt we'll have time,
but.
If we could get to
the speed limit feature.
By the way we're building
like space game where we're
flying through asteroids.
That's what we're going
to build with this thing.
Maybe we want the asteroids to
have a speed limit where just
aren't going so
fast that there's no way
our ship could possible
dodge them or whatever.
So we use linear velocity for
that.
So you can ask any item that
a dynamic behavior is behaving
on, you can ask for
its linear velocity.
Okay now here's all these
behaviors, gravity behavior,
push behavior, all these.
These are all subclasses
of a class called
UI Dynamic Behavior.
Not dynamic item behavior.
That's the previous slide.
This is UIDynamicBehavior.
Now a UIDynamicBehavior
is something you often
create your own subclass of.
Now how that hap,
you're probably like what?
I'm gonna write my
own gravity thing, or
my own collision thing?
They're too complicated and
the answer is you're right,
it's way too complicated.
So your subclasses of
UI Dynamic behaviour, what
they're gonna be is composites
of other dynamic behaviours.
So if you had some space l,
where there's boundaries and
gravity is applying
to things and
they have a certain
friction and elasticity.
You would combine our
gravity behaviour,
collision behaviour and
UI Dynamic item behaviour.
Into your subclass of
UIDynamicBehavior.
And the way you combine them
is with this very important
method in UIDynamicBehavior
called addChildBehavior.
That means composite this
behavior into my behavior.
And, we almost always do this,
okay?
Create our own subclass
of UIDynamicBehavior, and
put all our other behaviors
that are related in it,
as child behaviors.
It's it's just a good way
to collect the ff total
behavior that's being imparted
to things into one place.
And we're going to do
that in our demo as well.
Most of the code we're
gonna write on Wednesday
is gonna be in a big
UIDynamicBehavior subclass
'cuz we're gonna put a lot
of behavior on our asteroids
that are moving around they
gotta bounce off the ship and
they gotta be affected by
the ship's acceleration and
all kinds of things we
gotta put that all in
our own subclass
UIDynamicBehaviour okay?
Remember I said there's this
UIDynamic animator at the top,
you add all
the behaviors to it.
That thing, all the behaviors?
No, the one they're in.
They have a var called
dynamicAnimator, which could
be nil, because they might not
be currently being animated,
that tells them that.
They also find out with this
method will move to dynamic
animator every time they're
either removed from a dynamic
animator or
added to a different one.
They can only be
animated by one.
So I think it can never be
reanimated by multiple dynamic
animators, that would
make no sense at all.
It'll be fighting each other.
So this is just time
the one that they moved to.
So you can find out
when they move too.
Why do you want to know this,
by the way?
It's sometimes very
interesting to know when
you leave a DynamicAnimator,
okay,
because maybe you have
something else going on,
like in our demo,
if we get to it on Wednesday,
we'll have a little timer
that's going on all the time.
But if we're not
being animated,
we don't want
that timer going.
So we'll start and
stop that timer and
we'll move to Animator.
Okay?
UI dynamic behavior also has a
really cool bar called action.
Okay.
Action is just a closure,
takes no arguments,
returns no arguments.
This action closure, is called
every time this behavior acts.
Okay, so collision behavior,
when it collides it's gonna
call this action thing.
Gravity is calling this
thing all the time.
Because gravity is
always accelerating
the items more and more.
A push behavior, it's called,
if it's instantaneous,
it's called when it
does its one push.
If it is continuous, it's
gonna be called all the time
as it pushes on the thing.
So this, these little
closures are called a lot.
So don't do anything expensive
inside an action closer.
Okay?
You want to
really make this code when if
you go into instruments and
you look at your code, if you
do something expensive here it
will come to the top pretty
fast because it gets called
a lot, as you might imagine.
And the but you can do a lot
of really cool things in here.
this is where you would
implement your speed limit,
For example,
okay check the linear
velocity, if it's too fast you
would add some negative linear
velocity to slow it back down.
Okay?
It's really easy to get memory
cycles with this thing,
because of course this action
var is a var in the behavior
and a lot of times
inside the closure,
you're going to be
referencing the behavior.
Doing something about
the behavior, right?
So they're gonna point
to each other right,
rather directly there.
Now, another thing that's
interesting about dynamic
animator is it usually,
most of the time,
runs to stasis, kay?
So things are happening like,
again,
swipe up from the bottom
of your phone,
the thing,
gravity pulls it out,
it bounces off the top
a little, and then it stops.
And when it stops can
the animator still on, but
has nothing to do?
You'll get this delegate
methods sent to you,
animator did pause.
So now you now, the animator,
it's still running,
it's still looking for
something to change,
but nothing is currently
changing, so has paused.
And then if something changes,
like you do a push
behavior and
things start moving again,
it's gonna say resumed,
until everything
reaches stasis again.
Now, you don't always reach
stasis, in our little asteroid
space game,
it's never gonna reach stasis,
cuz the asteroids are always
flying by, constant asteroid
activity, but in the flip
up from the bottom, okay,
then it does reach stasis so
if you wanna find out
when it reaches a stasis,
you just set yourself as
the UIDynamicAnimatorDelegate,
that top level animating
controller thing, and
it'll tell you.
Now, let's combine.
Well, let's go back and
fix that problem we
had with the push.
Okay, so we have this
instantaneous push and so
we do this one push.
W-, well first of all,
we create the push behavior.
We add the items we want to
push to it just by saying,
right there, UIPushBehavior
items put an array of UI
view that we want to push,
and then we set the mode.
And if we set the mode
to be inten-,
instantaneous right here.
Then, when we add this
behavior to an animator okay,
cuz we have to add
it to an animator
When we add it to an animator,
it's gonna push those items.
for anything to happen.
And then the animator is going
to continue to have a strong
pointer to it.
And so it's wasted memory.
the push behavior is just
sitting there unused.
It's just sitting,
It was instantaneous,
it already pushed,
there's nothing to do.
So, a lot of times what we'll
do is we'll use that action
thing to have a little closure
that removes the pushBehavior
from the animator.
[LAUGH] Okay?
And since we know action
gets calls right after it's
instantaneously pushed, it's
a perfect time to remove it.
However, you can see
that this creates
a horrible memory cycle.
Look inside that closure,
the very first thing we do,
say pushBehavior that's going
to capture push behavior.
And of course pushBehavior,
the action bar is
on pushBehavior.
So that point right
back to each other,
directly to each other,
keeping each other in memory.
So how do we break this cycle?
So I bring this example out
because it shows the way to
break a cycle that we haven't
really shown example of
which is to use unowned, okay?
We don't need to do
weak self here, and
in fact we wouldn't do weak
self, because we know that
inside this closure push
behavior can never be nil,
it could never be
outside the heap,
because we're in the action
method that push behavior.
The only reason we'd be here
is because we just pushed with
that push behavior, so
it couldn't possibly
be out of the heap.
So it's guaranteed
to be there, so
we do not need doing in this
week or anything about,
we can just say unowned, and
unowned means do not keep
the strong pointer inside
the closure to pushBehavior,
because I know it's
gonna be in the heap.
You see how unowned
works there?
So unowned is kind
of more of a force-
way of breaking
a memory cycle.
And you gotta be really
sure that that thing you're
gonna mark unowned is in
fact going to be there,
otherwise it will
crash your app.
But here we know for a fact.
All right, that's it.
On Wednesday I will do
a gigantic space demo.
To show you how all this
stuff works, if I have time,
which I almost am certain I
will not I'll try to work some
core motion in there which is
the accelerometer in Gyro and
that stuff how we
make that work.
There's no Friday section this
week, next week we're going to
be doing a lot of stuff
kind of the general
how things work in IOS that
we haven't had a chance
to cover like the application
life-cycle, you know, what
happens when your application
launches, runs, quits, etc.
And then things like alerts,
puting alerts up on
the screen,
which you will all need for
your final projects, and
there's a couple more segues.
A little more rare
kind of segues than
the show segues
that you know about
that I'm going to cover
next week as well.
And you probably want all this
stuff as you're doing your
final project.
And I'll, so that's why
I'm going to try and
cover it all next week so
you have time.
To get to it before the end,
alright that's it.
>> For more please visit
us at stanford.edu.