[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well welcome to
Stanford CS193P developing
applications for
iOS Winter 2017.
This is Lecture 15, I think.
Yeah, 14, something like that.
And today is all demo.
We're gonna do a demo of this
dynamic animation stuff.
And I'm gonna cover
push behaviors, and
collision behaviors, and
dynamic item behaviors,
collision delegates,
gravity behaviors, etc.
I'm not gonna get
back to the slides.
So, let me talk about what's
coming up now which is we
have no section this week.
And then next week,
I actually posted what I'm
gonna talk about next week.
But it's application
lifecycle, alerts and action
sheets, segues, might even get
core motion to fit in there.
I'll try and cover as much of
the general infrastructure
stuff that might help you,
with your assignment.
Okay, so
let's get right to the demo.
And this, now, we're demoing
Dynamic Animator here.
And generally, dynamic
animation is mostly used to
animate things that are
happening in your UI normally.
And I use that example of when
you swipe up from the bottom
on your iPhone and it brings
that little UI view comes up.
And it kinda bounces a bit and
then sits steady.
That is really what dynamic
animation kind of is used for
You wouldn't probably use it
for building a video game,
the most.
even though that's the demo
I'm gonna do today.
There are other things
like Spy Kid and
things like that that
you might use for that.
But I like doing the video
game because this is kinda fun
and it also as a opportunity
for me to quickly and densely
show you lots of different
kinds of behaviors and
how they work.
So, we're gonna build
a space game, asteroid game.
We're just gonna have a field
of asteroids flying by, and
we're gonna have a ship
in the middle, and
our ship is gonna
have some shields.
And every time an asteroid
hits the shields,
the shields will turn on and
get depleted.
And eventually our ship
will probably be destroyed
from too many asteroid hits.
And, we're gonna be able to do
all of those behaviors that I
mentioned before.
So, let's get started here,
I'm gonna create a new app.
I'm gonna call this
app asteroids and
we'll make it work on both
iPad and all the iPhones.
That's no problem for
this one and
I'll put it in the same place
that I always put everything.
Now I wanna focus all my
demonstration time here on
the dynamic animation stuff.
So, this is one of those demos
where I actually do have some
code and
some stuff I'm gonna drag in.
I'll show it to you briefly,
but it's mostly just
drawing things, drawing
the ship, drawing an asteroid.
And, all the animations
stuff that we're gonna do,
100% of it is gonna be in code
that I do in the demo here.
So, let's start by moving some
of these things out of the way
as we usually do, put these
things in supporting files.
Just to clean up what
we're looking at here.
I'll even put main
storyboard up here.
Now, I've left XC Assets
out of supporting files at
Cuz I actually am going to
have some assets, some image
the time.
assets, specifically my
asteroids and my ship.
So, let's drag those in, so
I'm just gonna go over here to
this little directory
I have of stuff.
And you can see that I've got
some kind of random pictures
of asteroids here.
And I'm just gonna take
these asteroids and
add them to my
images down here.
I'm gonna do it for explosion,
also my ship knows how to
explode, so we'll have that.
And then here's my ship,
cute little ship, here's where
it's, it's engines are firing.
Okay, so we have those
two images right there.
Now when you drag images into
your XE assets you'll see that
they have a one times, a two
times and a three times slot.
And that's talking
about the resolution.
Okay, it's really talking
about the number of pixels per
point, okay?
In the size of the image.
Normally you're gonna
have all three.
I'm only gonna use the 1x
because my 1x is pretty high
resolution, it'll look
fine on 2x and 3x.
But if you got a real app,
you'd wanna pick resolutions
at these different sizes.
Because it allows a one X
app to be much smaller,
cuz obviously a lower
resolution is much smaller.
And it's really
cool actually when
people download things
from the App Store.
You only get the resolutions
that are appropriate
for your device.
So, it's kind of fun.
You don't get all that extra
junk that you don't need.
So anyway, so
those are my images.
And then I do have
a bit of code here too,
at least four files.
Just like I said we're
gonna take a look at here.
Drag those in and
we will copy them, yes.
All right, so let's look at
the code we just
dragged in there.
First one here is
asteroid view.
This is the entire thing that
you see on the screen right
here, very simple little
subclass of UI image view.
It just picks a random one of
those asteroids images, right?
See these asteroid images one,
two through asteroid nine,
this thing just picks
one of those and
makes an image view out of it.
Okay, that's all AsteriodView
is, so that looks really easy
when we move that into
supporting files as well.
Here is a little exte, file
of extensions that I made to
CGFloat, and CGSize and
CGRect, and CGPoint.
And these are just little
convenience functions, like
here's the area of a CGSize
right just with time height.
Or here's a CG float, it
generates a random number in
a certain range of floats
which is kind of cool.
A random float,
okay and returns it.
Here's CGRect.
I have a random point which
generates a random point
inside the rectangle anywhere.
Cuz obviously I'm
It's nice to have a little,
var here,
random points, for rect.
So, you can go look
at these later,
as I'm writing the code,
I'll try and reference
these are one of my little
CGRect extensions that I did.
And I do this but I think my
code reads a lot nicer when I,
kinda condense this math into
these nice little, extensions.
you know,
But all of these make perfect
sense as extensions of
each of their classes.
None of them are spaceship or
asteroid specific extensions
to core graphics.
So, move that to
supporting files as well.
Then next we have
the spaceship view.
Okay, the spaceship view
just draws that little
spaceship I showed you.
It knows how to draw it
with the little flame
coming out the back if
the engines are firing.
This is the entire public
API of it right here,
this is the only
API we'll be using.
So, that's just a bully that
turns on that little fire
coming out the back or
not is all it does.
Direction is the direction
the ship is pointing and
that's you know zero to two
pi, so it's in radians.
You know, we've hopefully
learned by now the zero two pi
circle where zero is out to
the right and we go around.
Shield level, so this ship has
a little round shield around
it and the shield level goes
from zero to a hundred.
When a hundred,
it's a full shield and
it doesn't even
show the shield.
But as soon as
the shield gets damaged,
It kinda shows the shield
partially damaged,
until you get to shield level
zero, the ship explodes, okay?
This shield is active,
it's purely a drawing thing.
When the shield is active it
kinda glows a little bit.
And so,
we're gonna have our ship,
just to make our UI simple,
it's going to automatically
turn it's shields on when
an asteroid impacts it.
Okay, so we're kind of
a auto shield deployment, so
we're gonna turn this on so
we can see it,
the asteroids causing
the shields to turn on.
And then finally there's this
little shield boundary guy,
that just gives us
a UIBezierPath that describes
the shield.
It's just gonna be a simple
arc around because
it's a circle,
just gives us that back.
Notice that it can give it to
us in any views coordinate
space and that's because we're
gonna find that when we do
animation.
We're gonna specify
a reference view for
all of our animation, and
when we have these
things like boundaries.
We have to always specify
them in that reference view's
coordinate system.
So, if we're gonna get the
boundary of the ship's shields
as a UIBezierPath,
it has to be in the right
coordinate system.
So, that's why it has this in
view argument right there, but
it's just returned to
UIBezierPath Okay so that's
the spaceship view I can
do anything else with that.
And then here is the last one
the asteroid field view this
is the entire
thing right here.
It only have one method in it,
which is add some asteroids.
Okay, and all this code here
is doing is just putting
a random sized asteroid at
a random point
inside it's bounds.
Okay, so really very
super simple right here.
It does have this little thing
of exclusion zone where it
won't put an asteroid there,
and
you'll see why we want that.
We don't wanna put
an asteroid on top of
our ship when we start.
Now this one I'm not gonna put
in supporting files, cuz we
are gonna actually add a small
amount of code to this guide.
Because we want our
asteroid behaviors,
how our asteroids behave using
dynamic animation to apply to
all of our asteroids.
And so we're gonna end
up adding a var here so
we can set the asteroid
behavior in this asteroid
field view as you
might have imagined.
Okay, so I'm gonna rename
my generic view controller
here to be asteroid's
view controller,
just good review of how
we do that by the way.
We have to do kinda
four things again,
I renamed the comment.
The actual name of the class,
I'm gonna rename the file,
gonna be typing the word
asteroid a lot today.
And I'm gonna go to
the storyboard of course, and
select this thing.
And make sure that it's
identity over here is not
generic view controller, it's
asteroids view controller.
Okay, everybody remembers that
how to change things pretty
And then don't need any
of this code for now.
easy to do.
And also obviously as you
imagine when you do a game you
have a lot of constants.
Okay, constants for
ship acceleration and
the size of things, whatever.
So I have a bunch
of constants,
which I'm going
to type in here.
And I'm gonna go over these
constants as I use them.
But like I say,
burnAcceleration,
initialAsteroidCount, these
kind of things so
pretty obvious what most
of these constants are.
Okay, so now we're all set
up to write our app and
focus on our UI dynamic
animation that we need to do.
The first thing I'm gonna do
is put the asteroid field view
in my self dot view.
Okay, so basically put it
onscreen, and I'm gonna do
that in code instead of
doing it in the storyboard.
But it's pretty straight
forward I'm gonna have
a private var which is gonna
be my asteroid field and
it's gonna be type
AsteroidFieldView.
Okay that's this thing right
here that I showed you that,
we know how to add
asteroids to right there.
And I'm gonna make this
implicitly unwrap optional
because once I initialize that
field it always gonna be set
for the entire
lifetime of this MVC.
So It's okay to make it
implicitly wrapped after all.
I just have to be a little
bit careful just like with
an outlet, not to access this.
Or at least to check that it's
nil before I initialize it.
And when am I gonna
initialize it?
I'm actually gonna initialize
it in viewDidAppear.
Okay, so in viewDidAppear I'm
gonna initialize this and
why am I doing it there?
Well, I really don't need to
do it before then, right?
Until my view appears, I don't
really need to initialize its
asteroid field and
all that stuff.
Also it's nice in
viewDidAppear,
all your bounds are set,
right?
Your geometry is all set up so
you can count on that.
But I'm not gonna rely on that
because I'm also gonna have my
asteroid field thing
work when I rotate.
So I'm also gonna have to kind
of adjust my asteroid field in
my viewDid layout subviews,
right?
Cuz that's tells me that
my balance have changed.
So I'm gonna do both.
So all I'm gonna do here in
viewDidAppear is I'm gonna
call something called
initializeIfNeeded,
cuz it might not be needed.
Remember that viewDidAppear
gets called multiple times cuz
it could appear then go away,
then come back and go away.
So I'm gonna initialize
the first time.
So I'm going to initialize
IfNeeded and so
I have this private func for
that.
Initialize if needed and
if the If needed part is just
if the asteroidField is nil,
then I need to initialize
the asteroidField.
Okay, so everybody cool with
where we stand right now?
So what do we need to do to
create this asteroid field is
just a UIView, so
I'm gonna create it and
I'm gonna say AsteroidField.
So make some more space here.
Just get a little wide here.
It's an AsteroidFieldView,
AsteroidFieldView, okay?
View.
Capital A.
All right.
[LAUGH] And a view?
How do we create a view?
Well, we're just gonna
use a normal frame
initializer there.
And what is the rectangle
of my field, my view here?
I'm actually gonna
start by having my
entire asteroid field.
Fit inside my views balance so
you can see the whole thing.
But when I really get
going with my game,
I'm gonna make the Azure
feel quite large.
So that my ship has a lot
of space to fly around in.
And then I'm gonna use
a little bit trick,
gaming design trick to make
it so that it seems infinite.
But of course I can't build
an infinitely large view.
So, I'm going to build
this with a rect that
is centered at my self
dot views bounds mid.
So mid is something I added
in my CGRectit extensions.
It just gives you
the mid point of it.
And my size is gonna be
my view.bounds.size.
Okay now I'm gonna start it
out there as in the center,
cover my whole
view again just so
you can see what's
going on there.
And one more parenthesis.
What else do we need to do?
We need to add it
as a sub view.
Okay, so I'm just going to
add this asteroid field,
this sub view of
my self dot view.
I'm gonna control
over here and
then let's add some asteroids,
asteroidfield.addasteroids.
We'll add 20 asteroids, that's
a good number of asteroids.
I think it might even
have a constance for
this,
constant.initialAsteroidCount.
Initial yeah,
initial asteroid account
that's better,
add a constant there.
The other thing like I said
is when my bounds changed,
I wanna make sure I
move my asteroid field
always to the center
of my new bounds.
Now that's gonna be a little
funny now because my as,my
field is gonna start out,
in this you know,
the bound size that
I started out with.
And I'm not gonna change it,
but
when I make my bounds really
big I'll make it so big.
That no matter what I
rotate my device to
it'll always be showing
part of the field, so
I don't worry about
that too much.
All I'll do for now is in
viewdDidLayoutSubviews,
I'll just make sure to always
recenter myself by saying that
my asteroidfield is center.
Equals my bounds mid, right.
So just always put it
back in the middle.
Okay, everybody cool,
what I've done so far?
All I did was created
this asteroid view.
Let's run it and see what our
asteroid field looks like.
It's just going to be
a bunch of randomly sized and
positioned asteroids,
popped in there.
All right, here it is.
Okay, here's my iPhone 7 plus.
Nice big one.
And you can see I've got all
these randomly sized and
shaped and you know,
different ones.
Those nine different
asteroids in here.
Now, it's time to learn
about dynamic animation.
We're going to make
these things move.
Now, how do we make these
asteroids start floating
around in space?
And the answer is we're
going to push them.
We're gonna use
a push behavior and
give it an instantaneous push
to this things just fly off.
So we push them all a random
amount in a random direction.
So they all starting to moving
it all a different directions.
Now to do that animation we
always need this top level
thing which is an animator,
okay.
The animator thing that
controls all the animations.
So you field that animation,
you always gonna had
a private var which is you
usually called the animator.
Which is going to be
a UI dynamic animator.
Animator.
And its initializer
takes a reference view.
And this reference view is
just defining the coordinate
system that all the boundaries
for collisions and
things like that
are gonna occur in.
Now what I want this
reference view to be is my
asteroid field.
That makes the most sense,
right.
Everything's an asteroid
field, that's a good view.
I can choose really any
view that's high up
in the hierarchy that
I wanna animate.
Now, here we're having the
same exact problem we had in
the last demo where I'm trying
to initialize a var and
in part of the initialization,
I'm trying to use a var and
we know we can't do that.
We can't use any
of our own vars or
funcs untill we fully
initialize ourself.
So, we're gonna do lazy.
And we know that when we
do this lazy approach,
we have to explicitly type.
We can't use the static typer.
Here, animator.
And also we know that if
we just say asteroid field,
it's gonna be looking for
a static.
A class.
Method called asteroid field.
So to tell it we want
an instance one,
we're gonna say self.asteroid.
And this is gonna work because
it's gonna be lazy, and so
it's not gona actually execute
this initialize in here until
somebody asks for it, and
nobody's allowed to ask for
it until we're fully
initialized; and
thus we've gotten out
of the conundrum there.
Okay, everybody
cool with that?
So now we have an animator.
What's the next
step in animation?
Behaviors.
We have to create behaviors.
And so, our
asteroids are gonna have
a lot of behaviors on them.
Okay?
They're gonna be colliding
with things,
they're gonna get pushed,
they're gonna have general
kind of physics, they're even,
when the ship is accelerating
through space, they're gonna
even be experiencing opposite
direction acceleration.
So we're gonna combine
all of those into one,
single behavior.
Okay, a subclause behavior,
and that subclause behavior is
gonna be a composite of all
those other kind of behaviors.
So let's do that right now.
Let's go File > New and
create a new
class which is gonna be
a UI dynamic behavior.
You see it says Subclass
of: UIDynamicBehavior here.
I'm gonna call it
AsteriodBehavior because
that's what it is.
It's the behavior.
It's gonna collect all the
behavior that has to do with
asteroids.
Put it where I put
everything here.
And so
here's my dynamic behavior.
All I'm gonna do to start
is have an add asteroid and
a remove asteroid method so
I can collect
the asteroids then I am
causing to behave somehow.
So let's have a private var
which we'll call asteroids.
And it's just gonna
be an array of
asteroids views, okay.
And then, we'll have a private
or actually a public funk
called addAsteroid and you are
gonna give it an asteroid and
it is just going to add
this asteroid, okay.
Pin this asteroid on
to the Our dictionary,
our array of asteroids here.
And then we're also gonna
have removeAsteroid.
And this one has to first make
sure that we actually have
this asteroid by saying
if we can let index
= asteroids.index of
this asteroid, okay?
If we can find it
in there then we're
just gonna say asteroids
remove at that index.
Okay, so this is it so
far for our behavior.
It's not actually doing any
behavior but now we can add
asteroids or remove
asteroids from the behavior.
Which is a critical
part of animation,
remember there's
always three steps.
Got the animator, you add
the behaviors to the animator,
then you add the items,
the asteroids in this case,
to the behaviors.
And so this is, we've gone
all three of those steps.
Now we haven't actually picked
any behaviors to composite,
to build our thing out of yet.
But at least we've got
the infrastructure to do that.
Now, now we have
a behavior here,
let's go back to our
view controller and
create one of these behaviors,
instantiate one, okay?
And add it to our animator.
So we can instantiate one
by just saying private var
asteroidBehavior =
asteroidBehavior.
Behavior, all right, so
we've just created
an asteroid behavior.
But it won't do anything,
that behavior,
whatever we tell it teach
to do eventually, it won't
anything to the asteroid until
we add it to an animator.
Now when is it a good time to
add a behavior to an animator?
Well you really only
want animation to go on
when you're on screen.
Okay, if you're not on screen,
animating things probably,
99% of the time does
not make any sense.
So, kind of a cool place to
do it is in viewDidAppear.
So when my view appears, I am
going to tell my animator to,
mator, to add behavior,
my asteroid behavior.
Okay, now,
when do I wanna remove it?
Well, I wanna remove
it when I disappear.
So in, view will disappear.
No, that's not even close.
View will disappear.
super.view will disappear.
[SOUND] Animated.
Here I'm just gonna
say to my animator,
remove this behavior.
And as soon as I move
a behavior from an animator,
it will stop animating
that behavior, okay?
In other words that behavior
will no longer apply
to the animation
that's going on.
Now I can put it back and
it'll start animating again.
One thing that's
interesting to note though,
all the items that
are being animated,
if you take an animator
out of an animator,
they'll lose all their linear
velocity, they'll stop moving.
So if you add it back,
they'll all be stuck.
You'll have to repush them or
reestablish
their linear velocities or
something like that.
Okay, that's the only
bad part about stopping.
You can't really this is not
really pausing the animation,
it's stopping.
All forces stop on
things being animated.
And then when you add it back,
they all start
re-playing again.
But if the ship were
accelerating when
And you come back and
the ship keeps accelerating.
you removed it.
It will, those things will
still be accelerating.
So will be effective.
So now we've added
the asteroid behavior to
the animator.
What's the next step?
We gotta add the asteroids
to the behavior.
Okay, if you don't add
the asteroids to the behavior,
nothing's gonna happen.
And I'm actually gonna have my
asteroid field view do that,
cuz it's the thing that
creates the asteroids.
And so it kinda works for
the architecture of my app
if I only have it to deal
with the asteroids and I don't
actually have to deal with any
of the asteroids at all
in my view controller,
that's kinda cool.
So I'm gonna go back
over to my asteroid
field view right here, and I'm
gonna add a public var here.
Which is the asteroidBehavior
that I want to apply
to all of my asteroids.
So we'll have
an asteroidBehavior of course.
We'll have it be optional,
because maybe my asteroids
are just sitting there, not,
not behaving, no one's,
that sort of behavior,
they don't do anything,
they just sit there.
That's probably fine.
When someone sets this, okay?
Someone sets my behavior,
I want to remove
all my asteroids from any
previous behavior I had and
add them to the new behavior,
okay?
I don't wanna set this
asteroid behavior,
I don't want any old
behavior still be behaving.
So, I'm actually gonna go
through all of my asteroids
here for asteroid in
asteroids, oops, in asteroids.
And for each one, if I had
an old value that was not nil,
an old behavior, then I'm
gonna remove this asteroid.
And similarly, for
the new value,
the new asteroid
behavior that I have.
If that's not nil,
then I will add asteroid.
Okay, now what about this
little var right here,
asteroid?
Where are all my asteroids?
I don't have a var here for
my asteroids.
I actually waited to do
this instead of just putting
it in advance cuz I wanna show
you some kind of
a cool way to do this.
I'm gonna have a private
var asteroids.
It's gonna be an array
of asteroid view, and
it's gonna be calculated.
And the way I'm gonna
calculate it is,
I'm gonna return all
my subviews, Okay,
cuz all my subviews are all
these asteroids, but
maybe one day I'll add some
other kind of subview besides
an asteroid, I don't know,
space station, or something.
And so, I only want
my subviews that
are asteroid views.
So I'm gonna say,
subviews.flatMap.
Okay, now flatMap takes
a closure and if that closure
returns nill, it doesn't
add that to the thing.
To the return value here and
if it does doesn't return nil.
It does and so in other words
flatmap makes a new array.
With all of the things in
the first array but with this
closure executed on them and
it skips ones that are nil.
So, I'm just gonna
say $0 which is each
subview in the array
as an asteroid view.
Okay, and this will
return nill of course,
if I have a subview that's
not a asteroid view.
But all the other ones will
do that and that makes this
return value turn into
a array of asteroid views.
Okay, so just thought I'd
show you a flat map there,
kind of fun.
All right, so now we have
this asteroid everything.
The other thing we probably
want to do is when we
add a new asteroid.
If we have our
asteroidBehavior set,
let's go ahead and
add this asteroid to there.
So, in asteroidBehavior,
I'm going to add asteroid,
this asteroid.
So, you can set the asteroid
before or after
you add the asteroids, it'll
work either way with this.
So now, we need to set,
see this var right here?
We need to set that from
our controller, so that our
asteroid field view right here
knows what behavior to use.
So, we're gonna say here,
well we'll put it
even a little higher.
We'll say asteroid field.
Set your asteroid behavior
to our AsteroidBehavior.
And, again, it doesn't matter
if I do it before here, or
I could do it after here.
Either way,
it's going to work.
Okay, got that?
All right, now we're
all completely set up.
We have this behavior,
custom behavior,
which doesn't do anything yet.
All the asteroids have
been added to it, okay,
it's been added
to an animator.
All we need to do now is
implement our behavior and
however we implement behavior.
It's gonna start applying
to all off our asteroid.
So, I said the first thing
we want to is push them all.
So, let's go add
a pushing behavior to our
asteroid behavior.
So, heres our asteroid
behavior, right here.
Lets at a push behavior,
and I'm gonna do this push
behavior by creating a func
called pushAllAsteroids, okay.
And I'm gonna have an argument
to this pushAllAsteroids,
which tells how much you
want me to push them.
It's always gonna push them
in a random direction, but
you can say by how much.
And so,
I'll call it by magnitude and
I'll even let you specify
a range of magnitudes to push.
Because you don't want
to push all of them
the exact same amount.
So, we'll create a this is
gonna be a range of a rangle.
No a range of CG float and
we'll have a default.
How about the default
be 0..0.5 so between 0.
Which means don't
push them at all.
2.5 which means push
them a fair amount but
not really hard.
A one point o push is
a pretty good push.
And these are the kind,
I should probably have
a constant for this but these
are the kind of things you'll
play with these number until
you kind of get the feel.
For the animation
that you want.
How fast you want them in
the slide in or how hard for
something you want something
to be pushed or whatever.
Okay, so how am i gonna
push this asteroids?
I'm gonna do it
with push behavior.
So I'm gonna go through
each of my asteroids, okay?
And for everyone, I'm gonna
create a pusher, which is
gonna be a UI UIPushBehavior,
and the UIPushBehavior's
creator here is, here,
is this one, items.
So, a push can actually push
multiple items at once.
But I don't want that here,
cuz I wanna push all
20 asteroids, or
all my asteroids,
in different directions.
So, I don't wanna push them
all in the same direction.
So here I'm just gonna
have the array have
one thing in it,
And the mode can
be continuous,
which means I just keep
on pushing it forever.
So that's basically velocity,
push behavior that's
continuous is velocity.
Or it can be instantaneous,
which is one push.
And that's what I want here.
I just want to kinda
get them started.
But I'm not gonna keep
pushing my asteroids around,
I'm just gonna push them
around, and hopefully,
they're in outer space,
they'll just keep on moving,
right?
We'll see if that happens,
but hopefully it will.
And so, the pusher's magnitude
here is how hard you're
pushing it, and so
I'm gonna make the magnitude
be a random number inside
that, this range up here,
that's why I have this
CGFloat random in Range.
Okay, so that's what we do and
then the angle I'm gonna pick
is also gonna be a random
number CGFloat.random and
that's gonna be in a range
of zero to two pie, so they
can push in any angle all the
way round the arc of radius.
So now, I've set up my pusher,
I just need to get it to push.
And how do I get it to push?
Well, to get it
to push I have to
add it to a dynamic animator,
okay?
As soon as I had a,
any behavior to a dynamic
animator, it starts.
So here I just need to add it.
And how do I do that?
Well, here I'm creating a
subclass of UIDynamicAnimator.
the way we add behaviors
is we say addChildBehavior.
And so
Okay, and
that adds this pusher,
this one time instantaneous
push, to our behavior,
the asteroid behavior.
And of course the asteroid
behavior has been
added to a dynamic
animator and
that causes the push to
be animated as well.
So basically all
the animation gets propagated
down through our asteroid
behavior to all our children,
all our child behaviors.
And we're gonna
have quite a few.
Four or
five child behaviors here.
All right, so let's go ahead
and see if this did anything.
Wait, one thing we gotta
do first is call this.
We never actually called
pushAllAsteroids, so
let's do that.
Let's push them,
again when we first appear,
we'll give them a push.
So, we'll say push behavior.
And
asteroidBehavior.pushAllAster-
oids.
And
We don't really care that
much as you'll see soon.
But it's kinda nice to
give our asteroid some
kind of initial motion in
space, and you can see there,
we go, we pushed them.
Now, something bad
happened though.
They got pushed
out into oblivion.
We lost them all them.
And they're still going but
I think there is
one over there and
one way over there, we can't
see them obviously anywhere on
our view cuz we pushed
them all out of our view.
So that's a major
problem we need to fix.
It have these things
go all out of view.
So, we'll fix that.
The second thing, I dont
know if you noticed here but
they all just started to
slow down pretty quick.
Okay, they start
out very fast,
then they rapidly slow down.
Okay, and
it space naturally happen.
Now the normal physics
of the dynamic animator
a kind of like a table top by
default, which even know push
something there's some
friction there, right.
And so, things will slow down.
And this is not a table top,
this is outer space.
So the two things we need to
fix, is one, keep our things
from flying everywhere, and
two, make it more like outer
space, no friction,
things like that, okay?
And we're gonna do, fix each
of those things, which a,
with a different sub-behavior
of our asteroid behavior.
The first one of them
flying all over.
For now I'm gonna put a little
boundary around my entire
view, my reference view here,
so
the asteroids hit that
boundary and bounce back.
So they're all kept in here.
Now that's not gonna work for
my game, as you'll see,
because as you're flying
through space the asteroids
don't bounce back out of
some invisible wall and
come at you.
They are, the new ones
are always coming.
And I will talk about
how we're gonna do
that trick in a minute.
But first I just
want you to see how
collision behavior works.
So, I'm gonna add a boundary,
which is all the way around
this reference view, okay?
So how are we gonna do that?
So, let's go back to
our behavior, okay?
To do a collision boundary
like that we're just going to
create a private VAR
which is going to be a.
And it's going to be
a UICollisionBehavior Now
any time we add
a new behavior, we need to do
this add ChildBehavior thing.
And a good place to do that,
actually, is in init.
So I'm going to override init,
here.
Call my super init.
And then, I'm going to add
this ChildBehavior collider.
And that again means as soon
as I get added to an animator,
the collider gets
added to an animator.
It will animate as well.
The other thing we need to do
is add all of our asteroids to
this behavior.
Just because we
added ChildHehavior,
it doesn't mean it applies
to all of our items.
We might not want that.
We might not want
the collision effect.
Later, we're gonna find we
don't want our collider
actually to apply to
the asteroids for example.
Or to we don't want our
collisions to happen with
the ship.
Okay, that's how
we wanna do it.
So, how do we do this?
We do this by going down here
where we add a new asteroid.
Every time we add
a new asteroid,
we're gonna say collider.
addItem[asteroid).
And same thing down here
when we're gonna remove.
We're gonna say
collider.removeItem[asteroid).
Okay, so
don't forget those two steps.
In fact, I, let me move this
code up here next to the init
so you can see.
They kind of go together.
These two,
these three things right here.
Adding a ChildBehavior and
then adding the item.
We're gonna do that over and
over for
all of our sub-behaviors
that we're gonna create.
Okay, now we have this
collider but we have to
configure the collider to say
what do we collide against.
And remember I want
the outer bounds.
I want the asteroids to
collide with the outer bounds.
For fun, I'm also gonna make
the asteroids collide with
each other, okay,
to start here.
So let's see what
that look like.
I'm gonna do this
same trick here.
Private, private lazy var.
And I'm actually going to
initialize this collider using
a closure.
So to CollisionBehavior.
And it's gonna =,
whoops = a closure that I'm
going to execute, okay.
And inside of this closure,
I'm gonna do this so
I'm gonna let behavior = that.
And I'm gonna return
that behavior, okay.
So this is a way you can
initialize a var and
do some initialization
stuff here right in line.
Okay, so what do I want my
CollisionBehavior to do?
So I want it to have
a certain mode of collision,
so let's talk about that.
CollisionMode is
a var in behavior.
And there's three different
ways you can set this,
one is collides
with everything.
So everything means everything
collides with everything.
Boundaries, items
like asteroids,
they're all colliding
with each other.
That's what we're gonna do.
But the other options would
have been boundaries,
which means it only
collides with boundaries.
And we're gonna talk about
how to add boundaries,
bezier paths as boundaries.
Or you can have only the items
colliding with each other
like just the asteroids
colliding with each other, but
they don't collide
with any boundaries.
Well, here, I'm gonna have it
collide both with boundaries
and with the each other.
with the boundary.
Now, how about that boundary?
I want a boundary that's
all the way around
my reference view.
It turns out there's
a var to just do that
automatically called
translateReferenceBoundIntoBo-
undary.
If you set that to true,
it'll add a boundary.
Which is a rectangle around
your reference view.
Now we're later going to show
how we can put boundaries in
by specifying paths.
Like the ship, the shields
of the ship is a path.
But for now we'll just
do this simple one here.
Now, I don't have to do
anything anywhere else in
my code.
I can, since I've set up
this asteroid behavior
I can just keep adding
behaviors to it and
it'll just apply
to the asteroids.
I don't have to go back to my
controller and do anything.
Okay, my controller already
has created an animator and
added this behavior.
So there's nothing more to do.
So let's go see what
this looks like.
Now our asteroids that we know
won't fly off into oblivion,
at least.
Okay, there they are.
And you can see they're
bouncing off each other, and
they're hitting the walls, and
they're also slowing way,
way down.
Okay, that's that bad friction
thing going on there.
All right, so how are we
gonna fix the friction?
We want these things to just
kinda keep bouncing around and
not stop like this.
We want them to feel like
they're in outer space.
Well, to do friction we
actually need a different kind
of behavior which is called
the dynamic item behavior.
And a dynamic item behavior,
talked about it in the slides,
is kinda of a meta behavior.
It's gonna describe the
physics of how these things
work when other behaviors act
on them, like colliders, okay?
So when the collider hits,
we're gonna be
able to describe how bouncy
the hit is, for example.
And we get to say whether
there's friction, and
whether they slow down,
and things like that.
So let's create one of those,
private lazy var.
I'm gonna call mine physics,
because that's what it kind of
feels like, you're specifying
the physics of your
all your asteroid reviews.
And it's a UIDynamicItem
behavior.
Don't get confused
here between dynamic
item behavior and
dynamic behavior.
Okay, dynamic behavior
is the root of all,
it's the su, super
colossal of all behaviors.
This is a specific
kind of behavior.
Just like a collision
behavior is a behavior, so
is a dynamic item behavior,
okay.
The people confuse those
two cuz they're so
similar in name.
But I'm going to do the same
thing here, let behavior
= a UIDynamicItemBehavior
Behavior.
And I'm gonna return that
behavior out of this closure.
Everyone understand, right?
I got a closure here,
I'm returning this behavior
out of that enclo, clo, that
closure, which I'm executing.
And then to assigning
it to this.
And just doing it lazy.
All right, so
what kind of things can we set
in this physics like,
in this meta behavior?
Well, what are things
we want here?
Let's try the elasticity
have about.
So elasticity says how when
two things collide for
example, how much
energy does it lose.
If you have an elasticity
of one, that means
they don't lose any energy,
at least no linear energy.
They, if they spin, then they
might lose linear energy and
gain angular velocity, but
elasticity means that
they're bouncy, right?
Now an elasticity of two
would mean they gain energy.
So they bounce off.
Now they're going
faster coming out.
And a 0.5 would mean
they'd be slowing down.
So one, since we are gonna
allow our asteroids to spin,
our asteroids will kinda
generally slow down.
But over a much longer time
than they were before.
Cuz our elasticity before was,
I'm gonna,
I don't know what the default
is but it's very low.
Speaking of spinning,
let's make it so
that our asteroids can spin.
And we can just do
that here by saying
it allowsRotationTrue.
So that says when there's a
collision, the views can spin,
okay, just like
an asteroid would.
Of course we want that.
How about friction?
Let's set our friction to 0,
okay?
No friction.
across the tabletop,
they're in outer space.
And there's also a similar
one here called resistance,
which I'm also
gonna set to zero.
Resistance is how
much items resist
the forces being
applied to them.
So if you set a very
high resistance,
then they'll resist it a lot.
Now, why do you
want resistance?
Well, you might have a gravity
field or something like that,
where some things are getting
pulled fully by gravity but
other things are not.
Like they're a balloon or
something, I don't know.
They, they float more or
whatever.
So you'll be able to
control their resistance.
You can put them in
the same behavior,
like same gravity behavior,
same collision behavior.
But you can control how much
they resist, those things.
All right, so
we don't want any resistance,
we want when they collide,
full impact.
So this physics behavior,
just like the collider,
has to be added as a child,
and it has to be, and
the items all have
to be added to it.
So physics And
we need to addItem here.
Physic, oops, asteroids,
sorry, asteroid.
This is physics over here.
Physics, and same thing here.
Eh, physics.
You'll often forget to do
this stuff, right here.
You'll add nice behavior like,
you forgot to do this.
And you want to apply,
of course, because
until you add the items
unless it's a child
behavior and
then that behavior
won't affect anything.
All right.
So, let's see what this does,
see if this pictures
are problem by adding this
behavior.
Okay, yeah.
See, they're not slowing down,
I mean, they are actually, but
they're slowing down so slowly
you can't really tell and
they're all bouncing
at each other, and
spinning and some of them
are going quite fast actually.
Got it?
Okay, now this would not
be a good asteroid game,
because you, the ship would
be getting crushed in the,
this asteroid field.
But we're going to put
our ship in here anyway.
We're going to put our
ship right in the middle.
So, I can show you
how the shield work.
And our ship is supposed
to get battered here.
So, let's add our ship.
So, I'm going to go
back to our controller.
Here in same place where I
initialize my asteroidfield
and create my
asteroidfield right there.
I'm gonna create my
ship here as well.
How big is my ship
gonna be web?
I want my ship to kinda be a
good size relative to the size
of my view bound,
right, myself.view.
So, I set a constant for that,
which I think one fifth.
So, I gonna make my ship be
one fifth of the shorter side
Whichever side is shorter,
I'll make my ship one fifth
of my balance.
the size, so I'll say
let ship size equal my
view.bounds.size.minEdge Just
another one of the things I
added in my, core graphics
thing, so I'll take whatever
the minEdge is and I'm gonna
multiply it by a constant,
which is the
shipSizeToMinBoundsEdgeRatio.
And let's go take a look and
then what I set to,
here is my constant,
I set it yeah, to one fifth.
So, to one fifth.
So, the ship is one fifth
the size of the minimum age.
Which seems like
that's pretty good.
You know balanced size,
my ship might be a little
too big and I pass, so I might
wanna play with that but yeah,
we'll see So
I now got the ship size.
Now I just need to
create the ship.
And it's just a view.
So, let's go up here and
create a var for it,
just like we have for
our asteroid field.
Let's do var ship.
We'll call it
a spaceship view.
And we'll also make
that be implicitly
unwrapped and optional,
because we're gonna initialize
it right here at the start.
And so we'll say our ship
equals [SOUND]
spaceship view Frame.
We'll do a CGrect here.
Let's have our
ship be centered
on the asteroid field.
We're going to put it
in the asteroid fields.
Center.
Of course, we know the size.
Is the shipSize.
And actually,
I want it to be a square, so
I'm gonna use a different
CGRect thing that I have,
which is squareCenteredAt,
I think I called it.
If I typed that right,
yeah, squareCenteredAt.
So ship is gonna be a square,
centered at the asteroid
field's center, right in the
middle of the asteroid field.
And it's gonna be
the shipSize that we
calculated right there.
So, let's add This
ship to our subviews.
Now notice that I've added
the ship to my self.view as
a subview, so it's a sibling
of my asteroid field,
it's not a subview of
my asteroid field.
My asteroid field really,
the only subviews it has
is all those asteroids.
But I decided I'm gonna put my
ship at the same level there.
And what's it
complaining about here.
Sorry, see here at sorry,
yes, view.addSubview.
We've gotta add it
to our self.view.
We're in our controller
right now, not view, okay?
So there's our ship.
Let's go take a look at our
ship actually right now.
There's no collision's
gonna happen.
Our ship is not involved
in the asteroid behavior.
right?
We haven't added our ship
to the asteroid
behavior in any way.
So there's our ship,
it's pointing at zero,
which is off to the right, and
the asteroids are just flying.
They're behind it, because the
ship was added to the sub-view
later, so it's in front.
Right, we know that our
subviews are in order from
back to front.
Okay.
So, now we want these
asteroids to collide
with our ship's shield.
The ship's shield is just a
round circle around our ship,
and we want it to
collide there.
So, we're going to have to add
more to our collision behavior
code over here in behavior.
Because right now, all we're
doing is having everything
collide with everything, and
the reference bound is
our only bound here.
So, I'm going to do this
by adding another Func,
just give me a public func
called setBoundary and
it's gonna let you set
a UIBezierPath, [COUGH] as
a boundary and it's gonna
be able to have a name so
we can refer to it later.
You will see why we need
to be able to do that and
then another cool thing,
how about if we add a handler.
So that if there's a collision
with that boundary,
we call our handler for you.
Wouldn't that be cool to
use closures in that way?
So let's do that handler.
What's the type of
handler gonna be?
Well, it's just gonna be
takes a void, returns void,
in other words doesn't have
any arguments or whatever.
And I'm actually gonna
make it optional as well.
Som you don't have
to do a handler.
You can put a boundary, and
the collisions will
happen with it.
But if you don't
put a handler,
then no one ever
finds out about it.
Right.
I have too many parentheses
in here maybe, that one?
Yeah, all right?
So, we got that.
So,
how are we gonna implement
this setBoundary?
Well, first we've got to add
this boundary to the collider.
Right, we've got this
collider behavior up here.
We need to add this new
boundary, this BezierPath as
an area that is going
to collide again, and
that, against,
and that's easy.
Collider.addBoundary.
The boundaries, when you add
them, need an identifier.
Okay?
Which makes sense because when
the collide,
collision happens,
you gotta say which
boundary you collided with.
So, we'll use name for that.
But remember this has
to be an NScopying.
So, we gonna say as
in a string here,
cuz in a string minus
number are both
an escaping that we
can use right here.
And that works because
string can always be as
a string and back.
Okay it's special
the relationship between
those two case.
And okay we are gonna
add the path here.
Okay?
Now, the only
thing about this,
though, what if someone
sets the Boundary again?
Then we pretty much want
to remove the old one, so
I'm also gonna say
collider.removeBoundary,
the name as NSString to
get it out of there.
Not removeItem.
Remove boundary
with identifier.
Name as NNString.
Got that?
Okay, so, I'm going to
remove the boundary, and
I'm only going to
add the boundary,
actually, if you
specify a path.
So, I'm going to make
this path be optional.
And then we'll
unwrap it there.
I'm only gonna say if
the path does not equal nil,
then add the boundary back.
That way if you say,
set the boundary nil,
it will get of
the boundary of that name.
So it's a way of kind of
having one method to add and
remove boundaries.
Now what about this handler?
We've gotta somehow hold onto
this handler so that when
a collision happens later,
we can call this handler.
So whoever created this
boundary can find out
you had a collision there.
So, I'm going to create
a little private var here
called collision handlers and
it's going to be a dictionary.
And that dictionary's keys are
going to be strings and what
do you think the var or the
value of this is going to be?
How about a function?
Okay, so I'm just creating
a dictionary whose keys
are going to be
the names here, and
whose values are gonna
be the handlers.
Okay, and I know it taken you
guys a lot, some of you a lot
to un, really get comfortable
with this idea that functions
are just types.
It's no different then
a string right there, okay?
And so we can have
a dictionary full of them.
It's very, very nice and
easy to use.
So we wanna do the same thing
here to remove the old one.
So I'm gonna say my
collisionHandlers of this
[name] = nil.
So I'm removing any
old handler for this.
And when I add it in here,
there's a new path,
I'm just gonna say
collisionHandlers[name] =
the handler.
Okay, so now I'm keeping
track of those handlers for
each of these
named boundaries.
Right, these boundaries
have names, and
I'm keeping track
of the handler.
So how do I call this handler
when a collision occurs?
Well, we need to find
out about collision.
So here's how we find
out about collisions.
We do it with a delegate.
You see, it's the delegant
of our collision behavior.
So we're gonna go up
here to our behavior,
collision behavior, and say
that it's collisionDelegate.
It's not called delegate.
It's called collisionDelegate.
Equals, and
I'm gonna have it be self.
So this asteroid behavior
itself is going to get
the notification that
a collision occurred.
So that means I have to be
a UICollisionBehaviorDelegate
to do that.
All the methods in
there are optional.
So I successfully
implemented that delegate.
But, of course, I want to
implement one of the methods.
And so
let's look at some of them.
So I'm just typing
collision here so
I can see what they are.
You can see there's
four of them.
There's begin and end contact,
you see, begin and
end contact for
boundaries or items.
So I can find out if
the items are colliding or
I can find out if items are
colliding with the boundary.
And of course I want
the boundary collisions, and
I pretty much want the began.
So when the contact starts,
okay, impact first happens,
I wanna find out
about it then.
So I'm gonna pick this one
beganContactFor item with
boundary.
Let's look at the arguments
here more clearly so
you can see them.
All right, so this is the
collision delegate method that
gets sent when a item,
an AsteroidView,
impacts a boundary.
Like the ship's boundary, or
even the reference
bound's boundary.
And it even tells you at what
point in the reference view
the two things touched, okay?
Now, we could even have had
our handler take that CGPoint
Which is kinda nice.
as an argument.
We could've told
the person that,
but, eh, we kinda have
a dumb handler here.
It could be better, but we'll
leave it with what it is.
All right, so
what do wanna do here?
Here we wanna see
if first of all,
I wanna get the name
from that identifier.
So if I can let the name equal
that boundary identifier,
this thing right here.
And it's an NSCopying,
and it's also optional.
So I'm gonna say, as String.
So if I can get that
identifier as a string,
which it needs to be if I,
if it's a handler here.
The, there might be other
identifiers in there for
other boundaries
that you create.
But it's gotta be a string
if we're gonna do this.
And then also I'm gonna
let the handler equal our
collisionHandlers, sub
that name, okay?
So if I can do
those two things,
I can get the handler for
that collision.
And what am I gonna do here?
Call the handler.
All right, this is
a little bit sophisticated
implementation here.
I'm using closures and
all that stuff.
Hopefully you,
you're understanding it.
If you're not, you know, make
sure you follow up with Piazza
or with the TAs in office
hours or whatever.
But this is the kind of thing,
this is the kind of coding you
want to be able to
do in Swift, okay?
Using closures to cause
things like this to happen.
So this is the public
method right here that we
are going to use
in our controller.
We need to set a boundary,
which is the ship's shield.
And in the handler we're
gonna do whatever we do when
an asteroid gets our shape.
So let's go to that.
Let's go back to our
controller here.
Now, where do we wanna
set that boundary?
Now this is kind
of interesting.
You would think we
might wanna set
it here in initializeIfNeeded.
But it turns out we
can't do that, or
at least not only there.
And why is that?
That's because this
boundary we're ta,
setting it in the behavior,
it has to be in the reference
view coordinate system.
And that boundary is
going to change position
when we rotate our device,
okay?
You know that when you
rotate your device,
your bounds change and
the center is in
a different place.
Okay, coordinates of
it are different.
So that's why we can,
we need to reposition our ship
every time our bounds change.
So we'll do in
initializeIfNeeded.
But we're also gonna
have to do it in
viewDidLayoutSubviews, okay?
So let's create a private
func to do that.
We'll call it repositionShip,
okay?
This is every time
the ship changes position.
And we can only do this if
we have an asteroid field,
because we put the ship in the
middle of the asteroid field.
So if we have no
asteroid field,
we have no idea
where to put it.
So if the asteroid field
does not equal nil,
then we can
reposition the ship.
And we know that
the ship itself,
its center is
the asteroidField's center.
We don't even need that, it's
implicitly unwrapped, right?
So the asteroidField.center,
right?
So that's positioning
the ship, but
now we need to add this
boundary around the ship.
So we're gonna tell
our asteroidBehavior
to set a boundary.
Now, the boundary is
the boundary of the shield.
And I told you ship has
this nice method called
shieldBoundary, okay?
And shieldBoundary even takes
the coordinate
system you want.
So we want this to be
in our reference view,
which is the asteroidField.
So that's gonna give us back
a Bezier path that describes
the shield in
the asteroidField coordinate
system.
We can call this
whatever we want.
I have a constant for it.
I'm gonna call it
shipBoundaryName.
Oops, not shipSize, do they,
no, shipBoundaryName.
So that's
the shipBoundaryName.
And we'll use the trailing
closure syntax here.
Let's put this on here.
So let's go back here, and
you all know about that.
And it has no argument, so
we really don't need that.
Although I do wanna do
weak self here, okay?
Because this is probably not
going to be a problem where
somehow this animator
gets all rogue and
[LAUGH] starts animating with
my controller being gone.
But probably I don't
need weak self here,
almost certainly I don't.
I can almost certainly
do unowned self here.
But I'm gonna go ahead and
do it anyway just for fun.
And so we have weak self here.
We, we,
this is setting the boundary.
This our handler that
happens when it collides.
So what are we gonna do
when an asteroid hits us?
Well, I'm gonna have
auto shield activation.
So I'm going to say,
ship.shieldIsActive = true.
If we have a collision,
bam, I'm gonna do it.
However, I'm only gonna
activate that shield for
one second, okay?
So if you have
an asteroid hit you, yeah,
I'll put your shield up.
But it's going back down and
if another one hits you,
it's gonna go back up again.
So how am I gonna make
this shield go back to be
inactive in one second?
Well, I'm gonna use a timer.
Okay, scheduled, and
I have a constant for it.
It's called my
Shield.duration, and
it does not repeat.
And it does this block,
which is just going to
turn that thing back off.
We'll use trailing closure
syntax for this one too.
And so we're just going
to ship.shieldIsAc,
oops, IsActive = false, okay?
So here I'm just turning
this shield on and back off.
Now, of course, ship right
here is not defined.
It needs to be self.ship, so
I'm gonna say If I can let
ship equal self?.ship, because
ship itself is weak right
there, then I will do this.
Now, if I didn't
charge any fee for
activating your
ship's shields,
then the shields would just
constantly come on and
this wouldn't be
much of a game.
Okay, so
I'm going to charge you some,
some power of your
shield to do it.
So, I'm gonna say ship dot
ship level, minus equals,
and I have a constant for
that,
too, which is shield
activation cost, okay.
So, I'm going to
deplete your shield
every time I turn it on.
Everybody got this code?
This is super simple,
obviously if we had a real
game, we'd probably have
shield regeneration and
maybe the user would have to
turn their shield on when
they realize they
are about to crash into or
whatever but I'm just trying
to make this pretty simple and
straight forward here.
Okay the other thing
I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna have
auto resurrection.
So, if your ship
gets destroyed,
I'm gonna bring
you right back.
Okay, again cuz it's better
for our purposes here.
So, I'm just gonna say when
this shield gets turned back
off, if the ship's shield
level has dropped down
to zero, in other words
it's been destroyed.
Then, I'm gonna set the ship's
field level back to 100.
Okay, full shields, boom,
it comes back to life.
Now this reposition ship
obviously needs to happen here
in viewDidLayoutSubviews.
And I'm also gonna position
the ship right after I create
my ship up here, so
that the boundary gets
created right at the beginning
when it first initialized.
Now one thing about adding
this ship, is, well, we'll,
we'll see if it happens.
If it doesn't happen I'll come
back and do it, but there's a
little bit of a problem adding
this ship with this shield.
This might see, hopefully,
cross your fingers,
we'll see the problem here.
Now we didn't see it, but, so
our ship got destroyed
really quick here.
Why did our ship get
destroyed so fast?
Shouldn't get destroyed so
fast.
Hold on a second here.
Okay, if our shield is
up from a previous hit,
we won't let ourselves
be damaged again.
So here I'm gonna say If the
ship's shield is not active.
Okay, if the shield is
not currently active.
Then I'll do all this stuff.
But if the shield is
currently active.
Then I'll just ignore the hit.
Okay.
So when we turn that
shield on for a second,
we get a second's worth of
survival [LAUGH] in our ship.
Okay, so now we see, see how
when this shield comes on,
it kind of is thicker, is
bolder and then goes thinner?
And you can see it going
smaller and smaller and
then the ship explodes, right?
And then,
we auto resurrect, okay?
So again, this would not
be a very good game [LAUGH]
because we've got all these
asteroids kind of banging in.
Now one other thing that I
was hoping would happen.
But it didn't, so
I'll have to explain.
What could happen is when
we put our ship here,
what happens if there's
an asteroid inside the shield?
It's gonna be stock there
forever, bouncing around, and
Okay?
wrecked the ship.
So, for the purpose of my
game, I'm not going to allow
an asteroid to be created
where my ship is.
And that's why,
this ad asteroid up here.
Add asteroid counts.
It has another argument
which is exclusion zone.
Okay, the exclusion zone
is just an area where
don't put an asteroid here
because my ship is going to be
here basically.
And so,
what am I going to put there?
I'm gonna put
the ship dock invert.
The ship's bounds to
Gastroville, that's right.
Yes, okay, so sorry, I'm
using this convert to method,
the same one we used,
before in a previous demo.
I'm just converting
the ships balance,
its rectangle from its
coordinate system,
to the asteroid field's
coordinate system.
So that'll keep
us from getting
an asteroid crater
in the middle.
All right, so let's make our
game a little bit better,
because right now, the
asteroid is just killing us.
They're constantly
banging our shield.
So instead,
what we're going to do,
instead of having
the reference bounds collider
that's keeping all
the asteroids in,
we're going to let
the asteroids fly away.
But if they fly outside
of our asteroid field,
we're going to
pick them up and
move them around to
the other side, okay.
So, we're gonna create an
infinite space by doing wrap
around okay, I don't think
that's how the universe
actually works,
although we don't know.
But that's how our universe
is gonna work, okay.
Anytime something goes off
one side we're gonna wrap it
around to the other side.
And anytime it goes off
the top we'll wrap it around
the bottom,
kinda like table view does.
Now we will only have 20
asteroids in our field but
we'd constantly
be reusing them.
And the other thing I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna make
my asteroid field much bigger,
that way the user won't notice
that I'm doing this wrap
around thing, okay.
So the two things will,
it's a good, easy,
quick simulation of having
an infinite asteroid field.
So, how are we
gonna make it so
these things wrap around,
okay?
I don't wanna,
it's just math to do that,
so I don't wanna type
too much of it in.
So, I actually
have a little pre
typed in thing here to
show you that, recapture.
So here it is right here.
Okay, this is all the code
that does that recapturing,
recapturing.
The basis of it is a timer.
So every half a second or
so, I'm just gonna look and
find all of the asteroids
that are outside and
move them around
to the other side.
Okay, very, very simple.
So, add this timer and
look that you can see
this code right here.
It's just looking for
ones that are outside.
It's using mod basically,
to, modulo, to move them
back to the other side, either
horizontally or vertically.
And notice here,
very importantly though,
when I move them, I tell
the animator that I move them.
Because if I don't,
let's say I have an asteroid,
flies off the field right
here and I'm moving back.
The next time your
animator ticks,
it's gonna move it
back over here.
You see?
Because the animator he's
got a hold of that asteroid.
So, if I'm gonna move
the asteroid over here,
I have to let
the animator know.
So that's why we have
this line right here,
updateItem(usingCurrentState),
which tells the animator,
here's the new position of
this thing, keep animating it,
from here, okay?
Understand that very important
line of code right there?
I'm also keeping count of the
recaptures, because it might
actually be a good score for
my asteroid game.
Because the faster I go,
the more recapturing is going
to be happening, of course,
the more risk I'm taking
of smashing into something,
too, so
it's kinda good risk reward.
Maybe I could use recapture
count as part of or
all of my scoring mechanism or
whatever.
So, I have this start
recapturing wayward asterisks
that starts the timer.
And then,
stop which stops the timer.
So, when should I stop and
start this timer that's doing
this wrap around business?
Well obviously,
if I add an asteroid.
I need to start recapturing,
okay?
Because once an asteroid
enters the field,
we've got to start capturing
otherwise, it will get loose.
And similarly,
when I remove an asteroid,
if I remove the last asteroid,
so if asteroids was empty,
then I would want to
stop recapturing.
But that's not all, okay.
There's one other time that
we want to stop this timer.
That's if the animation stops,
okay.
If the animator stops
animating his asteroids off
in the universe,
then we stop recapturing them.
We don't want our
timer running then.
So how do we find out that
our animator stopped?
Well, this is his method that
is implemented in the super
class here, our super
class UI dynamic behavior
called willMove to and
it tells you when you've moved
to a new dynamic animator
including when you've moved
out of all dynamic
animators by moving to nil.
Dynamic animators.
So, let's go down here and
put that, maybe right here.
So it's called willMove to,
you can see it it right there.
And I'm gonna call super,
because I inherit it.
I don't know that my
superclass actually does
anything, but I don't
wanna take any chances.
So here,
what am I gonna do in here.
Well, if the dynamic animature
that I was added to is nil.
That means that
animation stopped.
So, I'm gonna stop recapturing
wayward asteroids, however,
if I was added to a dynamic
animator tha's not nil.
Now, I want to
start recapturing
as long as I have at
least one asteroid.
So, I'm gonna say
asteroid is not empty.
Is empty, look at that, hm,
that asteroids is empty.
If, that's why.
If asteroid's not empty,
then I'm going to
start recapturing.
Okay, so do you see how
if my behavior's added to
an animator and moved from
an animator, boom, I'm gonna
start and stop my timer that
does the recapture as well.
So, you got to think about
these things when these
timers are going.
You don't want the timers
running wild, okay.
You got to think about when
appropriate time to start and
stop them is.
Okay, now that we are
recapturing, I don't need this
collision boundary here that
is the reference now, so
I'm gonna comment that out.
I'm also going to stop having
the asteroids collide
with each other.
I'm only gonna have it collide
it with the ship's shield.
So, I'm gonna change this from
everything to boundaries.
Okay, so it's only going
to collide with boundaries,
the asteroid's only going
to collide with the ship,
basically.
The other thing I'm gonna do,
is make the asteroid
field really big.
This is going to make
the asteroids larger too,
which I think will
look better as well.
And so, I'm gonna do
that just by taking,
see where I asteroid
field right here.
You can see the sizes
[INAUDIBLE] bounce that size.
I've got a constant for
how much bigger to make it, so
I'm going to multiply this
by constant.asteroid field
magnitude, okay?
And asteroid field magnitude,
let's look and
see what I set it to, ten.
So, ten times larger
than our view.
That's how big our asteroid
field is gonna be.
Now, do I, why don't I
make it 100 or 1,000?
Okay, well it's not free
to make views that large.
Views have backing stores for
drawing things efficiently,
you wouldn't want it to be
infinitely large like that.
You wanna pick a reasonable
size for efficiency.
Ten times is fine, okay.
100 times?
1,000 times?
No, you wouldn't want
it to go 1,000 times.
Okay, so
now let's see if that worked.
Okay, so now here we
are in outer space.
That is really big.
Here come some asteroids.
They're just kind of,
they got pushed so
they're just wandering around.
This is much more
manageable as a game.
More likely that we could
manuever through these things.
But to maneuver,
of course, our ship needs
some engines, okay?
It needs to be able to move.
Now, we're gonna
have our ship move
just like a real spaceship.
How does a real
spaceship move, okay?
It fires its engines, and
what happens to it when
it fires its engines?
It accelerates, and
it keeps accelerating as long
as its engines are firing.
As soon as its engines turn
off, what happens to it then?
No longer accelerates but
it keeps its velocity
cuz it's in outer space.
Okay, so
there's nothing to stop it,
so it just keeps going.
But it's doesn't decelerate,
nor does it keep accelerating.
It goes no acceleration but
its velocity stays the same.
So, we're gonna do
exact same thing here.
So, how do we do acceleration?
Like that in behaviors.
We use a gravity
behavior because gravity
is acceleration
due to gravity,
due due to the Earth's pull,
right, pulling things down.
They're accelerating at 9.8
meters per second squared, and
we can have the same
kind of behavior here.
And our gravity behavior
is great because we can
have it pointed
in any direction.
So which direction
are we gonna have
our gravity behavior point?
The, yes, the opposite
direction of the ship, okay.
And that's gonna cause all
the asteroids to move as if
the ship were going here.
Because we don't actually
want our ship to move.
We want the asteroids to move.
So we're just gonna
apply gravity in
the opposite direction
the ship is pointing.
Simple as that, and that's
gonna cause acceleration.
And we're gonna start
accelerating and
those asteroids
are gonna start moving.
If we stop accelerating,
they're gonna keep on moving
because there's no friction in
outer space.
So if we want them
to slow down,
we're gonna have to turn
our ship around and
fire our engines the other
direction, okay?
So that's how this
is gonna work.
Okay, so
let's see if we can do that,
add a gravity behavior
to our behavior.
So we're gonna go
back to behavior.
Here it is, we got collider,
we got physics,
we're gonna add another one,
this is going to be a lazy var
I'm gonna call
this acceleration,
it's not really gravity, okay,
it's acceleration through
our engines here.
And it's gonna be
a UIGravityBehavior, and we'll
also initialize it
with a closure And
inside here we will say, let
behavior equal a UIGravity,
I keep typing in graphics
there, hm, surprising,
the term behavior.
Okay, and what do we need
to do to initialize this
GravityBehavior to act
like acceleration?
Well, when you create
a GravityBehavior, by default,
the gravity is 1.0
that's a thousand
points per second squared,
in the down direction, okay?
And so, we don't want that,
we want gravity to start out
zero, cause we're in outer
space, we're just floating,
we're not accelerating,
our engines are not going.
So, we're gonna have our
behavior.magnitude be zero.
Now I'm, I could make this
private and add API like I did
for my collider,
where I had set boundary.
But I'm go ahead, gonna go
ahead and leave this public.
And what that
essentially does,
when you leave something
public like an outlet
in your controller, or
something like that,
it exports this entire
API of UIGravityBehavior
into the API of yours, because
you're making this public, so
now people can do
anything they want.
To that acceleration
bar right there.
The grabby behavior only
has a couple of methods or
a couple of bars magnitude and
angle,
basically it also has vector
which is basically the angle.
So it's not so bad.
We're not exporting
that much API.
But we also want to be careful
when we make a bar public that
we intend to let
people do this, okay?
Which we do.
We're gonna allow
people to do that.
So, when we add
a new behavior,
what do we need to do?
Right here.
Okay, don't forget these.
So, let's go here again.
Child behavior for
the acceleration.
And also down here we're gonna
add all of our asteroids so
they're affected by
the acceleration.
And we've got to remove
items when they get removed.
Okay, don't forget that
part or it won't work.
Okay, so that's it.
Now we've got gravity, let's
go back to our controller and
get our engines to fire.
Now, how are we gonna
fire our engines?
We clearly need a gesture
to fire our engines.
So, I'm gonna use a gesture
called a long press, okay,
a long press is a press
that you hold down.
And as long as you hold
it down it keeps firing.
So it's a continues gesture
like a pan gesture or
something like that.
But you don't, it just,
you press and hold, okay?
Very, very similar to
a pan gesture actually.
But the long press
will be configured for
other things, how long to
wait until you recognize it,
which I am actually
going to set to zero so
it instantly recognizes
my finger going down.
You can also have long press
do things like if you move it,
it stops working.
And of course we want
our long press to keep
following it around keep
just a pan gesture.
But you can make it so
a long press if you move it
too far up now it stops firing
so that's the difference.
I just wanted to
show it to you so
you can see a pan gesture,
what it looks like.
So let's go back to our
storyboard here and
add that pan gesture.
I'm gonna add it in
the storyboard rather than
in code.
So here's my controller right
here, I'm gonna go down and
find it by searching for
gesture.
If you go down these things at
the bottom there's Tap, Pinch,
Rotation, Swipe.
Here it is, Long Press,
I'm gonna drag it out,
I'm gonna apply it
to my self.view.
So my self.view is going
to handle this gesture.
Okay, my controller is
gonna get it, sorry,
self.view is going to
recognize this gesture and
my controller is going
to handle the gesture by
Causing our ship to
burn its engines and
cause that
acceleration increase.
And remember, when we drop,
drag this in here,
it adds up here, I can click
on it, I can even inspect it.
Here's where I can say things
like the minimum duration is
zero or the tolerance
of how many points
you wanna allow it to get to
move before it stops firing.
The person jerks their
finger away or whatever.
You can do all
this right here.
And I'm just gonna
have this thing.
I'm gonna control drag it to
cause an action to happen.
Let's put it,
let's put it right here.
So we'll control
drag over to here.
It's gonna do an action.
It's gonna have
the LongPressGesture as
the argument.
We'll call this burn cuz
we're gonna burn our
engines here, okay?
So what's gonna happen here
is, my finger goes down,
I'm gonna turn the ship
towards my finger, and
turn on the engines.
And when I let go,
I'll turn off the engines.
Leave this ship in whatever
direction it was, and
turn it off, and
it can start drifting.
Okay, press the finger down,
ship's gonna quickly turn,
and you know,
if I were doing a real app,
I'd probably have that
turn be animated, but
I'm gonna have
a jerk down there,
but you guys know how
to do view animation.
You could easily have that
rotation be animated.
And that's how
it's gonna work.
So you press and hold,
and it'll accelerate
in whatever direction you
wanna do, wanna do there.
All right, so let's go
back to our controller and
implement this burn.
So here is our
burn right here.
So how's the burn gonna work?
Well, I'm gonna switch
on the sender.state.
That's the recognizer state.
And right from when it began,
and also every time it changed
I'm going to turn the ship
towards the finger, and
believe it or not, I can do
that in one line of code.
Okay, what did I
do wrong there?
Maybe just not enough of,
yeah.
Okay so
how am I gonna do that?
I'm gonna say ship.direction,
and
I want to set this to where
my finger is relative to
the center of the ship as an
angle, that 0 to 2 pi angle.
So the first thing I'm gonna
do is I have added in my
core graphics stuff a way
to subtract two points and
get a vector between
the two points, so
you just use minus to do it.
So I'm gonna say this is the,
make sure I use the right
variable names here, we do,
yes, okay, so this is
the sender's location in
our self.view, right,
this is our controller.
Minus the ship's centers.
So that gives me a CG vector
vector between those two, and
vector, I added
a method called angle
which turns that vector
into a zero two pi angle.
So you see how I can
make this really cool.
One line of code if I have
these old CG extensions.
So that's something
to think about when
you are writing
your code as well.
And then of course I wanna
burn too, I wanna turn
on my engines when this
figure has turned out.
So I'm gonna need a private
func burn that does that.
I'm also gonna need
a private func endBurn.
Because when I lift my
finger up, it needs to stop,
which is in the case
that it ended.
endBurn, okay?
Otherwise we'll just ignore,
okay?
So that's it.
That's my entire burn,
super simple.
So what happens when we burn?
Well, we need to set that
acceleration gravity behavior
to be the opposite
direction of my ship.
Also I want to tell my ship
that its engines are firing.
Okay, this is just
a graphics thing so
that it draws that little
flame coming out the back.
That's all that does.
And so now I'm gonna say
that my asteroid behaviors,
acceleration.
[SOUND] Angle equals my
ship's direction minus what?
Pi, right?
Zero to two pi is
all the way round,
so pi is half way
around that circle.
And then my asteroid
behavior magnitude.
So for
the magnitude of the burn,
this is something that
we would need to.
Sorry.
Acceleration.
This is something we
need to play with
to kind of get the right one.
I have a constant for it so
that I can kinda work
on the constant.
You know,
I was home developing my
app I called
Burn Acceleration,
I think it's what is
burn acceleration?
Okay, .07,
points per second per second.
That's a not
really light burn.
But, you know,
as you hold that finger down,
that thing's gonna start going
faster and faster, and faster,
and faster, cuz you're
constantly accelerating, okay?
It's not just that
you're going fast.
You're accelerating
going faster and faster,
the longer you hold
that finger down.
Now the end burn is to just
tell the ship that the engines
are no longer firing.
And we'll make the asteroid
behavior's acceleration
magnitude back to zero.
So we stopped accelerating.
And we'll leave the ship
pointing whichever
way it's pointing.
Everyone cool with this little
bit of code right here?
So that's all we need to
do to get this ship moving.
All right, so here we go.
I'm going to start
accelerating
up towards this
guy in the top.
See, see how he's coming
down to me, no, you be.
Okay, I'll keep accelerating.
Now you're gonna start to see
the asteroids really rip by me
faster and faster and faster
in the down direction there.
See that?
Now if I wanna slow them down,
I got to turn my ship around
and slow down here, okay, see?
I'm accelerating the other,
too late,
I got destroyed
before I did that.
But it still keeps
slowing down.
Slow down, slow down,
slow down.
Okay, now I'm starting to go
the other direction, okay?
Finally caught up with that
one and now they start going
the other way, so I'm
continuing to accelerate here.
I'm destroyed again, okay?
Does everyone see
the way that works?
Now if you were actually
playing the actual game,
you wouldn't be doing this
massive acceleration.
If you're doing sh, little
tiny move, move, tiny move.
Look for the, things coming,
little more trying to go
another direction, etc.
I've got time for
one more thing.
I think, I'll do one real
quick one, which is if
you notice if I hold down this
thing and start accelerating,
some of the asteroids
are going super fast.
I mean just like so
fast you can barely see them,
they just blink going across.
This is another problem we
gotta fix is not letting our
asteroids be stopped and
caught in the middle.
But that super duper fast
asteroids, we don't want that,
because at some
point they go so
fast that the user
can't even see them, so
they're kind of useless.
They're not even on there.
So what if we put a speed
limit on our asteroids?
How would we put a speed limit
on our asteroids, because
we can infinitely accelerate
our shift faster and faster,
and faster, so how could
we put a speed limit?
Well, the way we're going do a
speed limit is we're going to
cap the linear accelerate,
the linear velocity
rather of the items.
And if you remember
from the slides,
this dynamic item
behavior right here,
it knows what the linear
velocity is of all its items,
and it can, you can set the
linear velocity of its items.
So, in init here,
those are init,
I'm actually going to
set a sped limit here.
Okay, so
this little piece of code
sets a speed limit
on all the items.
And how does this thing work,
okay?
First of all,
I'm gonna have to have a var,
which is the speedLimit,
which is a CGFloat, and
I'm gonna set it to 300
points per second, okay?
All these, the linearVelocity
is your points per second.
And the way this works is it
just gets the linearVelocity
for an item using this
linearVelocity for method.
Then it calculates the excess
velocity as a negative
number, okay?
By subtracting
the speed limit,
subtracting the velocity
from the speed limit.
Caps it out at zero, so
it's always a negative number.
And then just adds that
negative number back in as
a linear velocity.
That's always, anytime
an asteroid tries to go faster
than the speed limit,
it slows it back down by
adding enough linear velocity,
negative linear velocity
to slow it down.
And, we did all this, by the
way, with this action thing.
Remember the action var
where we can execute
a block of code every
time that it acts?
So the physics are acting
all the time because
you know the physics is
always being in effect.
So now if I accelerate,
no matter, even if I keep this
engine down full speed, you
can see these things, that's
as fast as they right there.
They've kind reached
there speed limit,
which does appear to be
about 300 points per second.
This screen,
I don't know, it's maybe
a thousand points wide.
Takes about 3 seconds, or
a little less than
that to go across.
Okay, so
this action allows to do it.
Now, this is executed a lot,
because this action's
happening a lot.
So, we want this code
to be quite efficient.
I might even go so
far in here, as to not call
addLinearVelocity if these
two numbers are both zero.
I'm not sure whether
addLinearVelocity
does anything if
those are both zero.
But I want this little
thing to be so fast that
I don't wanna take any chances
there, and I have to do this.
I can't get linearVelocity
otherwise and
I have to do this small
little tiny calculations, so
I'm not worried about those,
but this one maybe
I'll make optional.
Okay, so that's it.
That's it for
dynamic animation.
Hopefully, hey, this was kind
of fun, feel free to take it
and add some features
to it if you want.
But hopefully you've
learned all the things
we need to do there.
And make sure hopefully
all of you submit your
proposals and all that.
And make sure you're getting
started on that final project.
Don't wait til
the last minute.
Use that crossword puddle,
puzzle mentality where let
things ruminate, okay?
See ya next time.
>> For more please visit
us at stanford.edu.