[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, well welcome to
Stanford CS193P Developing
Applications for
iOS winter of 2017.
This is Lecture number 15 and
our only topic
today is segues.
This is the segues lecture.
You've learned show segues and
show detail segues, which
work in navigation controllers
and split view controllers and
now we're gonna learn all the
rest of the kinds of segues
that you can use to
build your application.
So let's start
with mode segue.
So now a modal segue
is interesting.
One, you,
when you segue modally,
you take an MVC that
you're segueing to.
And it takes over
the entire screen, okay?
That's why it's called modal,
because you're in a mode
[LAUGH] where you can only
interact with that MVC.
There's no back button.
There's no tab
bar to click on.
There's no way to do anything
else in the app except for
what that MVC is doing.
Why would you ever
want to do this?
Well, sometimes you get to
a point in your application
where you need some
information from your user and
you just can't
proceed without it.
So, my example here is, let's
say I'm in a contacts app,
like the contacts app on your
phone and you get to a point
here where you're looking
through contacts and
you say, "well I want
to add a contact".
Alright, so you're going
to press this little +
button in upper
right hand corner.
When you do that,
a whole new MVC,
the add contact MVC slides
up from the button and
you notice there's no back
button there because I'm
not in the navigation pushed
and instead of a back button,
this one happens to have
a cancel button right here.
But there's nothing I can do
now with this application,
except for
what's on this screen.
So, I could fill out
the field to add a contact,
I could hit cancel or
done, that's all I can do.
And it's perfectly
fine to have a modal
MVC that brings up
another modal MVC.
In fact, this one does.
I'm adding a new
contact here and
I'm going to add a photo for
my contact.
So I'm gonna click this add
photo button, right here, and
when I do, another MVC,
presumably the camera, or
the photo library, or
the photo choosing MVC,
comes up on top.
And again, I can't do anything
now until I've dealt with this
and, presumably I
could take a photo,
that would be one way
to get out of this.
Or I could hit cancel so let's
go ahead and hit cancel in
this one, when we do that we
go back to the previous model
one and here if we hit cancel
on this one we are going to go
back to the original
one that we had right.
So it is two order model
viewer control is it kinda
takes over your app for
a little bit now,
you gotta think a little bit
about modal view controllers.
They're so easy to put up,
that they can be
abused a little bit.
Users tend to be slightly
disconcerted by modal MVCs.
Because they get comfortable
with their app and
they know where the tabs are.
And they know how
to go backwards and
forwards in navigation
controllers.
And then, all of a sudden, all
they can do is this one thing.
Now, sometimes it
makes perfect sense.
Like add contacts of course
that the user understands I'm
adding a contact that
I can click over and
do something else.
Well there are some users
who might say why can I
click over do some of
the things right now?
I need to do that to add
these contacts or whatever.
So, I tried to stay away from
modal view controllers as much
as possible but things in
navigation controllers and
tab button controllers,
and things like that but
there are times, when it's
absolutely, necessary.
So how do you set one of
these modal segways up?
Super easy.
You just control-drag.
And when you control-drag,
instead of saying show or
detail, you're going to
say present modally.
Now, normally,
as with any segway,
you're going to be segwaying
from like a bar button item or
just a regular button, or a
row in a tableview, but if for
some reason you want to
put something up module
from something else
basically from code.
You don't forget about
this method that actually
in a previous lecture called
perform segue with identify.
we're talk about,
You can set up a segue in your
story board by just control
dragging from the little
view controller icon at
the top of your scene
that little yellow thing,
it's at the very top part of
any scene in your story board.
In control drag from that,
to any other MVC,
set it to be present modal,
and then inspect that segue.
Give it an identifier, and
then call this
method in your code.
It will cause that
segue to happen, and
that MVC will appear modally.
Also, if you happen to have
a view controller in your
hand like you have
a local variable or
something that has
a view controller in it,
which by the way when
would that ever happen?
Have we seen that happen?
I don't think we have yet.
But there are various iOS
API that will give you back
a view controller.
Like on Wednesday we're
gonna talk about alerts and
action sheets.
They will give you an MVC
which is basically an alert
that you're gonna put
up on the screen.
Also if you want to take
a picture with the camera,
you're gonna get this UI image
picker controller which is
an MVC and
you're gonna put it up.
And the way you put that up,
okay,
anytime you have an MVC
in your hand, in a VAR,
Not in the storyboard but
in it might be something you
created out of the storyboard
but it's in your in a bar.
You just do present.
So these are both new
controller methods up
here these yellow things.
And present just takes the
view controller you want to
present, whether
you wanna animate
it appearing on screen
which you usually do.
A and
then a completion handler.
When animations done it'll
call a completion handler.
Often we just ignore that.
That's why it defaults
to nil there, okay.
Now, when you are causing
this modal thing
to appear, when it appears,
it can actually appear
in different forms.
One way is, it can cover
the entire screen,
which you're going
to always see in
train trade collections where
it tours on like compact.
Okay, so that's like iPhone,
all right,
or master maybe of my pad.
In a horizontally compact
environment it's going
to kind of cover drop
the whole space.
But in other places you
might want it to appear
as a Popover, okay?
Or you might even want it
to appear as kind of a form
sheet, a smaller than
the huge iPad screen.
So when you setup your segue,
you can go and inspect it and
you can set how you want
it to appear, okay?
And you can just take a look
of those prime out, page and
form sheet and see what they
look like, and see which one.
that's what it's gonna look
like when it, it gets there.
You like there, so
In horizontally compact
environments, okay,
they aren't really
narrow environments,
it's always by default going
to adapt to full screen,
no matter what, you put in
there, but I'm gonna show you,
hopefully, if we have time in
the demo, how you can override
that adapting that behavior,
that automatic adapting
behavior preparing for
a modal segue, it's
exactly the same as any other
segue you've ever seen, right?
You just check the identifier,
see if the destination does
the thing you're looking for,
and then prepare it.
What about hearing
back from a Modal MVC?
So you put a Modal MVC up like
that contacts thing and it
collects all the information
for the new contact.
How do you communicate back?
Here's the new contact, okay?
So, there's a couple
of things there.
One, you know, that new
contact thing might just be
creating that contact
in a database.
And, and
you don't need to do anything.
You just dismiss the modal
view controller.
When it comes back, the other
view controller is looking in
the same database, and
it sees it appear.
It's probably using a fetch
results controller or
something like that, and
it sees it as it appears and
magically just works, but
sometimes you might be
creating something
where you do need to
communicate back and you're
gonna use an unwind segway for
that, and I'm gonna talk about
unwind in a few slides here.
But that's how you're going to
communicate back from a modal
view controller.
How do you get the modal
view controller
to go way like when you
hit the cancel button?
The answer is that
the presenting view controller
the view controller that puts
it up okay the things you said
way from that thing is
responsible for dismissing it.
And it does it with these
methods dismiss animated,
okay and that when you say
dismiss to NBC it means
Dismiss any view
controller I've put up.
That's what this means, okay?
Dismiss ones I've put up.
And, the good news is, okay,
a lot of times you'd wanna do
this in the cancel button of a
thing that was presented, but
of course, you can't
send this to yourself.
But luckily,
every view controller knows
who presented it.
So, it can just get its
presenting view controller.
There's a, bar called
presenting view controller,
and it can send dismiss to its
presenting view controller.
You'll see that in
the demo as well.
Online segues by the way,
which again I'm going to talk
about in a minute,
they automatically dismiss.
So, you do not have to call
dismiss if you unwind.
To communicate
information back.
Now, not only can you control
what the modal view control
is going to look
like when it's up,
whether it's full screen or
whatever, but
you can also control how
it animates to come up.
And it's the same thing we saw
with the other one, you can
flip to have it appear, it
can cross this all in there,
you can slide up from the
bottom that's coverVertical is
the default, and
you can even partialCurl,
it will kind of lift it up
like a piece of paper and
see the new one in behind.
In all cases though,
no matter how animates on,
no matter how are chose, it's
modal only that new MVC can be
interactive with, okay, the
other MVC is like the one I
presented it,
are kind temporarily disable.
All right, let's talk
about that unwind segue.
This unwinding,
is the only segue in iOS that
does not create a new MVC.
Okay?
Show segue, new MVC.
Popover, new MVC.
But unwind, does not,
because in unwind,
you're segueing back to some
MVC that already exist.
That has presented you.
Okay?
Now, what's it good for
this unwind, is it's good for
communicating back
from a modal.
It's also good if you have
a navigation controller with
a whole bunch of things
on the stack, and
you want to jump
back more than one.
You want to do more than one
back button's worth, you can
jump back three levels, you
can unwind back up your stack,
because, though, when you
have a navigation controller,
all the MVCs, higher on the
stack are considered to have
presented you by pushing
you on the stack, okay?
Which they did, they segued to
you with a show, or whatever.
So, that's what unwind
is mostly good for.
How does it work?
Well, you don't control
drag from the button, or
whatever you want to do the
unwind, to the MVC you want.
Instead, you're
gonna Ctrl+drag
to this little orange
button at the top.
You've probably seen
this button and
said, mm, what is that thing?
It has a tooltip that
says Exit, and, indeed,
that's what you do.
When you Ctrl+drag
to this thing,
you're creating a segue that
is going to exit this MVC.
Okay.
Now, how do you decide where
you are going to go when
you exit.
Well, you are going
to do that,
because you create a special
method in another MVC.
And whenever you create this
special method in any MVC
it gets added to a list
inside of X code, and, so
when you control drag to exit
that list is going to appear.
And you can see I only have
one of them here
called go back.
Now, I'm Ctrl+dragging from
a table view raw, so I've got
the accessory one, and the
main table view raw one there.
But go back,
there's the only one.
So, when I choose this go
back, I'm basically saying,
that I wanna segue to some
MVC that presented me,
it implements the go
back method, okay?
That's how unwind work.
Now, let's look at kinda
how the code behind all
this works.
So, in the presenter, the one
you're gonna unwind to,
you have to create a method.
And this method has to
have two important things.
One, it has to be
marked @IBAction.
And two it argument and
it can only have one argument,
it must have one argument, and
that argument must be of
type UI storyboard segue,
because you're going to be
segueing to this thing.
Okay, so that's in the view
controller you're going
to unwind to,
that you're segueing to.
So, the code for this
kinda looks like this, and
to prepare.
Of the presenter, so
the presented I mean.
The prepare,
of the thing that's going
to be doing the unwind,
because it's going to be
segueing, it gets to prepare.
So, it has normal prepare,
you can check its identifier.
And when you're in prepare,
the segue's destination it's
gonna be the presenter,
the view controller
you're gonna unwind to.
So, this code goes in
the presented view controller,
the modal view controller,
whatever,
that you're gonna unwind from.
Then back in the presenter
you have code that looks like
this, the special method with
the at sign app, action,
ID action and
the UI storyboard segue.
And inside there,
very interestingly,
you're gonna look at the
segue's source you know that
were used to looking a segue
destination that's the view
controller we are segueing to.
Segue source is the source
of the segue, so
that's the MVC we're
segueing from, so in
an unwind situation for in the
go back method, this go back
method, just go back method
goes inside the presenter
right there.
The source of the segue
is the modal one.
And when you do unwind,
you will automatically
get dismissed.
See how I disappeared there.
I'll get dismissed, and
the presenter will have this
go back special method called,
So, this,
this is how unwind plays out.
okay?
It's all about that special
method and the presenter.
All right.
Another segue is
the Popover segue.
I'm sure you've all seen this.
Here's a Popover, this
Popover is presenting an MVC,
which is some kind of
search for appointment
MVC there in some calendar
app, or something like that.
And, so that's the MVC
that's being presented.
Now, when you notice when
this is being presented.
It's in this little white box
and there's a little triangle.
See the little tiny
little triangle there?
It's pointing to the UI
element that cause the popover
to come up.
So, that's usually a bar
button item, or button, but
you can actually point to any
rectangle in any view, okay.
So, for example, if you
had an iBooks like app and
you have text, and you
double click on a word, and
you hit define it could
bring up a popover with
a little arrow is pointing at
the word you are defining,
you see?, so it can point
to anything you want there.
And notice also that the rest
of the UI is kinda grayed out
a little bit right the stuff
that is not the MVC that is
being presented in
the popovers kinda grayed out,
in fact if you click there you
will dismiss the popover, so
this is also a modal,
a popover is also a modal.
It only, you can only interact
with what's in that popover.
If you try to click on
anything else, it's gonna just
miss the popover, and end
exit the modal state, okay?
You've probably noticed this
from using various iPad apps,
and by the way, the popover,
mostly iPad only, but
not always, you can actually
do popovers on the iPhone,
I'll talk a little bit
about that as well.
So yeah, popover, just like
modal, you control drag,
you're just gonna set its type
to be popover instead of,
present modal.
When you're preparing for
a popover,
there's a few extra
things you can do, okay.
So, all of these
presentations,
anytime you go modal, or you
even push in the navigation
controller, these are all
managed by a class called
a UI Presentation Controller,
it controls
the presentation of an MVC.
Now, we're not gonna have time
to talk about that, you can
actually build your own
presentation in folders that
present MVCs, and
other ways that you want.
Pretty rare to do it, but you
see it sometimes in apps, or
things slide out in
a certain way, or whatever.
But, in the popover case,
we're just gonna
talk about the,
this, presentation control
a little bit, because there's
a sub class of it called UI
PopoverPresentationController.
And it has a few interesting
bars in it, like, what arrow,
what direction is the arrow
from the popover allowed to
point, okay?
The system automatically
figures out where to bring
the popover up, but it will
try to make the arrow point in
one of the directions that you
allow, also this is where this
popover presentation
controller is a thing where
you specify the rectangle and
view that they are should
point at, if it's not pointing
in a bar button icon, or
a button, or
something like that.
And where do you
configure all this
UIPopoverPresentationContro-
ller stuff?
You do it in your prepare,
when you prepare for
a popover segue,
you're going to do that,
so, the code looks
kind of like this.
Here's a typical prepare for
segue that is preparing for
a popover segue,
it looks the same,
all the green is the same
as any other segue.
But then there's the yellow
that's different
I'm creating this
local variable.
I'm calling it PPC, so
that it fits on my slide,
but that's not a good
variable name.
PPC equals VC which is
the View Controller that I'm
segueing to give me it's
popover presentation
controller.
When I get that popover
presentation controller, and
you can go look at
the documentation for it, but
one of the things it can do is
permitted arrow directions is.
Will let you set the arrow
directions to right, left,
right, up, down or here I've
set it to any, which means
any, I'll let the arrow point
in any direction, all right?
In addition to doing things
like arrow directions,
this popover presentation
controller also has
a delegate.
Now why does it
need a delegate?
Well the delegate is used
to control this adaptation
behavior.
Now the popover, when you have
a popover, you'd like to have
your storyboard just
have a popover so
that when it works on
an iPad it's nice.
It's in a popover but
when you're on iPhone,
especially when you're in
a horizontally compact
environment you don't
want to use a popover.
There's usually
not enough room,
it's just too crowded to put
a popover in there, instead,
you wanna do this full screen.
And as I said before,
the system will automatically
adapt to the fact that you're
in a horizontally
compact environment, and
it will make it full
screen instead.
But via this delegate,
this pop over presentation for
a delegate, you can
control that adaptation.
Behavior you can prevent it,
you can modify it, so
let's talk a little bit
about how that works.
So this adaptation to the size
classes let's just look at
the code right off the bat.
This delegate method of
the pop over presentation
controller is called adaptive
presentation style for
controller trait collection.
And, what this is
basically asking is,
I'm about to present this
controller, the argument
there, in an environment
with this trait collection.
Remember trait collections are
like horizontal size class,
vertical size class.
And, it's asking you to return
what kind of adaptation
you want to do?
So, you can return none,
and it will not adapt,
it'll just do it
like a popover.
This how you can get a popover
on your iPhone just implement
this delegate method and
return none, okay?
.None, if you do
that it won't adapt.
Now you could return
other things in here like
.fullScreen or .overfullScreen
and by doing so
you control how the popover's
going to look and
adapt to different
trade collections.
Okay, hopefully,
we'll have time for
that in the demo maybe not,
but we'll see.
The other thing you can do,
which is kinda cool when
it adapts,
is I might have a popover, and
since popovers don't
have cancel buttons.
They don't need
cancel buttons,
cuz I can touch anywhere
outside the popover, and
it cancels it.
Okay, so I don't need
a cancel button, but on a,
when it adapts to full
screen modal on an iPhone,
I do need a cancel button cuz
I can't click anywhere else.
It's taken over my
entire screen, so
I want to put a cancel button.
So to put a cancel button up
there, maybe I want to put it
in a navigation controller so
that I can fit a cancel button
at the top,
a bar button item, right?
I mean, I could put the cancel
button somewhere inside my
view controller and then just
take it out when I'm on iPad,
iPhone, or whatever.
But maybe what I wanna do is
have it be in the navigation
bar of a navigation
controller.
But again,
only when I'm adapting and
so this will let you that.
This one called
Presentation Controller,
View Controller for
adaptive presentation style,
is saying, what view
controller should I use
when I adapt to this
presentation style?
Okay, and that presentation
style over full screen or
pop over or full screen.
And so here is where you
might want to say I'm gonna
return a navigation controller
with the controller that
would normally disappear
in a pop over inside of it
as it's root view controller.
Okay, so this is kind of
a cool way to do substitute,
another, like, usually
a navigation controller,
another MVC that you'll
wrap around the MVC you're
trying to present.
So the return values
of this is actually
another ViewController.
Okay, so it's kinda fun
controlling that adaption
stuff, there's another
important issue about popovers
by the way, which is size.
Now, by default,
a Popover comes in size
that kind of is like
an iPhone in portrait, that's
kind of it's default size.
And if it doesn't really know
what size the stuff is inside,
that's the best it can do.
But you can control their
size, make it a lot better,
by having the MVC that's being
presented, implement, or
set, this var called
preferred content size.
And that just says,
this is the size I want to be
in a popover, basically or
in any environment, really.
But this is my preferred
size to be and
so, again if we have time can
do this in our demo as well.
You want to return
here the smallest size
that you look good in and then
when your popover comes up,
it'll use this size.
If you don't set this size,
you're gonna kind of
get this default size,
it depends on
whether in portrait,
landscape, iPad, whatever.
It's gonna give you
a somewhat standardized size.
Okay the last segue we're
going to talk about here is
embed segues, these are really
cool, really powerful.
Segues is basically a segue
where you put another aVCs
self.view it's top of a view
inside another view hierarchy,
so this embedding view
controllers inside another
view controllers.
Okay really cool thing
to be able to do and
Xcode makes this super easy,
you're just gonna go down
to your object palate.
And look for
container view and
drag that container view out,
it looks just like a view.
You're gonna put auto layout
on it, wherever you want and
itself.view is gonna appear
embedded in the view hierarchy
of the thing you
dragged it into.
It's really quite
a normal segue,
it seems weird cuz it's like
you're embedding this thing
but, it's a fairly
normal seque in there.
You can name it,
you get to prepare for
seque and all that stuff.
You can see here,
the little gray thing
next to this container,
that's the view
appearing inside the big
light blue view
hierarchy on the left.
And on the right is just
an entire NVC that you get to
configure any class you want,
any UI you wanna put in there.
And that's all just gonna
appear inside that box on
the blue side, okay?
One thing to be really
careful about embed segues,
it's no different
than any other segue,
in that when it happens,.
When the prepare happens, none
of the outlets are set In that
MBC that you're embedded okay?
So a lot of times people
they're embedding this other
MBC and they want to be
setting all kinds of outlet
in the thing
they're embedding.
But you can't because none of
those outlets have been set,
you're in prepare,
you're really early.
So almost always what we do
here is we grab the entire MBC
and prepare and hold on to it.
And then later in our view did
load when all valve is loaded
then do we start
talking MBC and
tell it to you know set
its outlets or whatever.
So 90% of the time
in the prepare for
an embed segue we grab on to
the MVC that we're embedding
okay which is just going to be
the segue's destination right?
That's the seg that's
the MBC we're segueing to.
Now I'm gonna do all demo
the rest of the way here, so
I'm gonna give you a little
what's coming up here.
So on Wednesday i'm gonna
be talking about alerts and
action seats sheets and
also notifications and
the application life cycle.
So the application life
cycle's all those methods in.
Next week, on Monday is
the Accessibility lecture.
Also Monday,
slides are due if you want to
participate in
the alternate final.
You have to submit
them by Monday,
if you don't submit
them by Monday, sorry,
you can't do
the alternate final.
But then that's
the only thing you do,
you don't have to sign up or
anything.
Just submit your
slides by Monday and
then Wednesday will be
the alternate final.
So, the demo I'm gonna do
right now is we're gonna take
FaceIt and
we're going to add all four
of those segue Ways to it.
Okay, all the I just
talked about we're gonna
put them all in there
in one little app here.
So, let's go over to faces,
there's faces.
All right, so
you guys remember faces,
very simple little app.
It had this little emotions
view controller and
we had three emotions,
sad, happy, and worried.
And when we clicked on it,
it would show a face
that showed that emotion.
So, I'm gonna actually before
I dive into these segues,
kind of enhance this
whole app slightly.
remember when we did our face
view controller way back when?
One thing is,
And we wanted to do squinting,
but we couldn't do squinting.
Remember why?
Because our face view only
could do eyes open or
eyes closed.
So we didn't really have
an option to do squinting,
so we just kinda had this,
okay,
well, we'll just
say that is your.
Okay, we had the punt,
essentially.
So, I'm gonna make it, so
we don't have to punt.
What I'm gonna do is,
remember we did that blinking
face view controller?
I'm gonna make squinting
be blinking, okay?
Squinting and blinking
aren't the same thing,
but kind of like
repeatedly squinting.
So, we're gonna make it so
that works, so
how are we gonna do that?
We no longer have
to punt here, so
we'll just not do anything if
someone says squinting, and
you remember that all of our
blinking code is in this
subclass here blinking
a face view controller.
So, we'll go ahead and make
our update UI overridable and
we'll go to our blinking face
view controller here and
override it, so I'm just
gonna override update UI.
Of course I wanna call funk or
a funk update UI,
and of course I wanna call
my supers update UI, so that
the mouth and other stuff and
the eyes themselves can all.
then I'm gonna say that
my blinking, whether or
Be set.
But
not I'm blinking,
is equal to our model,
which is our expressions.
Eyes.
If those are equal
to squinting.
So, if we're squinting,
then I'm gonna be blinking.
Everybody see
what I did there?
So that's it, I just [LAUGH]
upgraded blanking face for
now if you set your model
to have squinting, as your,
your controller,
as part of your
model,then it will blink.
Now, we made this
blink view controller
kind of a demo thing.
I made it every time it
appears it starts blinking.
Every time it disappears
it stops blinking.
I don't really want that now.
Now, I want it to blink
when it's squinting and
not otherwise but
I also still only want it to
blink when I'm on screen.
I don't want my timer blinking
when I'm not even up here.
So, I'm gonna change this
blinking thing here to can
So, let's add a new
private var up here,
blink.
can blink start out as false.
And so here if I appear,
I'll say I can blink and
even say blink if needed
at this point because maybe
someone set us to blinking
while we weren't there and
when we disappear I'm gonna
say can blink was false so
I'm not allowed to blink.
And then, in blink if needed
I'll just say If I'm blinking,
and I can blink, then I'll
go ahead and do my blinking.
One other little thing that
I want to do here is to not,
if I'm in the middle of
a blink, okay, this timer,
and I get another
request to blink,
I don't want to
start another timer.
Okay, so I'm gonna have
another private var var here
which I'm gonna call in
a blink which is whether I'm
in the middle of a blink,
let's start that as false.
And, so I'll also check it
here and we're not in a blink.
So, then I'll just set
a blank here to true and
then when we get out the other
side down here I'll set in
a blank to false.
So, all I did was upgrade
my blank view controller,
so be able to be controlled
by it's model rather then
being a demo thing.
Everybody cool with
what I did there?
Minor little upgrade.
Now the next thing
I wanna do is.
What we're gonna do for
our demo segues is, we're
gonna, if you remember in the.
Self question mark here.
If you remember in
our storyboard here.
We're kind of fixed to these
three different emotions,
that's all we have.
Well, I'm gonna make it so
that we can hit an add button,
and add another emotion.
Okay, as many
emotions as we want,
that's what we're gonna do.
So, we're gonna have a modal
segue to that theme,
we'll unwind to bring it back.
We'll make it
work on pop over,
we'll embed the little
blinking face view.
We're gonna do all kinds
of segue stuff here.
But first we have to convert
this to something that we can
add more to.
So, we can't have this
three buttons like this,
basically not going to work.
So, we need a different kind.
And what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna use, there's not much
code in this emotions
view controller as it is.
It just got this.
Little dictionary of
the three things, and
then it does prepare.
So, I'll keep as much
code as I can here.
So, but what I'm gonna
do is make it a table
ViewController.
Okay, so I'm just gonna turn
this emotions thing into a
table ViewController, cuz it's
real easy to add more rows.
So, I'm just gonna say, this
is a UITableViewController
instead and
I'm gonna have to change
my model a little bit here,
from being a dictionary.
I'm just gonna have it be
an array of tuples, where this
name of the emotion, and then
the expression are in a tuple.
And we'll have it in
an array like that, so
I'm just gonna replace this
whole thing with an array.
Of tuples but otherwise
it's the same exact data.
It's just this it's
an array of tuples or
one thing is the name
like sad, happy and
the other is the expression,
the eyes and mouth whatever.
Since I've also
made this a var, so
that we can add more of
them to it over time.
Okay, now, we of course,
this broke our prepare, but
we'll fix that in a second.
Let's go back to our
storyboard and add this thing.
So, I'm gonna make
a table view, so
let's go over here to
utilities windows, and
grab ourselves a table
view controller, and
put it out here.
Here's our table view.
Of course I wanna set this
identity to be this emotions
view controller which I can
do because I changed it to be
And then, raise it to make
it back to being th root
a table view.
view controller of this
navigation controller.
Look that up, and remember we
had these three segues that
would segue from those three
separate buttons over here.
Well, I still am
gonna need the segue,
cuz I gotta show the emotion.
So, I'm just gonna Ctrl
drag over to here, and
create a new segue.
I'm gonna split through here,
so it's gonna be show detail.
And we'll call this one
right here, this segue.
How about show emotion?
That's what it does, right?
It shows an emotion
when you click on it.
And, we'll wanna configure
this table view,
as well right here.
We'll have the cells
be just basic.
One piece of text in there,
that's be like happy or
sad, or whatever.
And we'll have reused
identifier would be like
emotion cell.
Let's say.
Okay, everybody
cool with all that?
Maybe we'll even put the title
we have this title if you
remember in motions the name
of that table right there.
So that's all that we
need to do to fix our UI.
So, we just need to fix our
motions view controller to be
a table view
controller now and
set this old, kind of
thing that it was before.
So, let's go ahead and
fix this navigation first.
Remember in that case we
were using the identifier of
the segue to figure out
whether we were sad,
happy or whatever.
In this case we're just
gonna look at the row and
index it into our nice,
new model up here.
So, we can get rid of this let
identifier equals identifier.
And clearly, we're not getting
the expression using that
dictionary anymore.
So, everyone
remembers table view?
We just wanna get the cell, so
we're gonna let the cell equal
the sender as a UI
table view cell.
And then, we wanna get
the index path of that cell so
we know which row it is.
So, we're gonna say
let index path.
Equal the table view.
Index, path for the cell.
Okay, so long as we're able
to get that indexPath out of
there, then setting
the expression
in our faceViewController
is really easy.
It's just going to be our
model, emotionalFaces
indexPath.row and here,
we want the expression, right?
We want this part
of the tuple.
Okay, similarly for saving
the title, we're not coming
from a button anymore, we're
coming from table view row.
So we want to do the same
thing but we want the name,
cut to this topol.
Okay, that's all we
have to do there,
that was easy to convert,
everybody cool?
So, now we've got
navigation working.
What's the most important
thing we need to do in a table
view to get it working?
We need to implement its
UITableViewDataSource, right?
Get the data in the table.
Super simple on this ca, case
we haven't seen numberofrows
and section,
that's just going to return
our emotional faces
of their account.
However many of these
emotional faces that we have
up here and then we need
cell for row and index path.
That's also easy, we'll
get the cell by dequeing,
dequeueReusableCell(with
identifyer.
We called it emotion cell, I
think, there's the index class
and we would have the cells
text label text equal
the emotion faces name
right index path row.
The name that's the name and
puppies are whatever and
when we return this, so better
if we just converge this to
your table view was easy hope
all of you your super familiar
with table view.
After all this so
let's go ahead and run and
make sure that we've got
our new upgraded version of
this emotions thing working
well, we didn't forget
some identifier somewhere or
something like that.
Okay, here we go here's
our app, here's our three
things in our table view,
that's looking good so far.
Let's click on one that
looks sad that looks happy,
okay, we've converted
our thing nicely, so
now we're gonna dive
into these segues.
The first we're gonna do
is add a button up here
which is gonna do a modal
segue to bring up
an emotion editing gear
controller, something that
lets us create a new one
of these emotions, okay?
So it's gonna have to let us
specify the name like sad,
happy or worried and
this is gonna have to list
best by the mouth and
the eyes, okay?
And that's all it's gonna do,
all right,
so, how do we do that?
Let's go back to
our story board and
we need to drag out the story
board that is going to be
this mo- modal
view controller.
didn't get a chance to do
this earlier in the quarter,
Just because I
I'm gonna make the UI for this
thing be a static table view.
Right, we've done
dynamic table views, but
we haven't done a static one.
So, let's go ahead and
do a static one, so
I'm gonna drag
out a table view.
Here it is, right here and,
I'm going to make it static,
so I'm gonna click on
the table view in here, and
change it from being content
dynamic to content static.
By the way, didn't I really
talk about this, I should of,
I suppose.
But, how do you define how
many rows there are in
a static table, okay?
You're gonna hold control
shift and click on the table,
so that you can drill
down to what you want.
You don't want the controller,
you don't want the table view,
you want the section okay,
because, in a static table you
could have multiple sections.
You wanna be able to
edit a certain section,
you click on that,
now it's selected.
And so in the Inspector
Table View section,
you see rows, and I can
change this to be 4 rows.
Now, why do I need 4 rows?
Well, I need the name, I need
the eyes, I need the mouth and
also I'm gonna have one row
which is a a preview of what
the face is gonna look like,
okay?
So as you can see, as you're
choosing your eyes and mouth,
what you are actually doing,
so
that's why you need four rows.
You can also put headers and
footers in here, but
I actually am going to
leave this in plain style.
And not have any headers and
footers cuz they kind of,
doesn't need any headers and
footers.
All these four
rows go together.
Okay, so we don't need to do
that, we of course are going
to need a subclass of UI
table view controller
to control this MVC, so let's
go ahead and create that.
The subclass of
UI Tableview controller.
Now this is an interesting
naming thing,
right here,
I'm gonna call this my
ExpressionEditorViewControl-
ler.
Notice I'm not calling it my
ExpressionEditorTableViewCont-
roller.
This is purely and art of
programming thing I tend to
not name my static table views
with the word table in there.
And the reason for that is I'm
mostly using static table here
just to help me layout the UI.
I'm not using it's table
viewness very much.
Okay, like I would to be
with dynamic rose so,
I tend to not but
the word table it's up to you.
You can certainly called
a expression editor table view
if you wanted
I like my expression editor
view controller but do you
understand why I'm calling
expression editor, right?
Because it's going to
edit an expression,
a facial expression here.
We'll put it in
the same place,
we'd put everything else,
here it is,
I'm gonna clean out all
this stuff right here.
I don't need any of this,
table view data source stuff,
because this is a static cell.
I'm not gonna allow deletion,
or anything like that,
we're not gonna be Doing
navigation out of it, so
we have this nice empty
expression editor.
And let's make sure that in
our story board that we go and
change the identity of this
guy to be this expression
editor otherwise won't be able
to wire up any outlets or
any things like that.
Okay, let's start,
before we build our UI for
this, let's just put
a cancel button in here and
get this modal segue going,
so let's do the modal segue.
We're gonna modal segue
from this emotions,
this is where all our emotions
are, sad, happy, etc.
I'm gonna put a little bar
button item in there, so
I'm gonna search for
bar button item there it is,
I'm gonna drag it up here.
When I inspect it, there's
actually some pre-canned bar
button items for common things
you want to do like add,
which is what we're gonna do,
cancel, redo,
all these things.
You can pick these and
they'll have standard icon,
standard words and So in here
we are adding an emotion so
I'm gonna hit add,
happens to be a plus sign.
And I'm just going to ctrl
drag from that to my new
editing view controller and
I'm not gonna do show or
show detail,
I'm gonna do present modally.
Okay that's going to take
over the whole screen and
put this MBC up and
allow me to add a new
emotion or whatever in here.
Now, how do we
get out of this?
If either run this right now,
we'll see that it
works in a manner of speaking
but it really kind of kills my
whole app, my app would be
dead it seems like do that,
let's go here this
is working fine.
I click on this plus, this
thing comes up, I'm dead now.
There's nothing I can do,
I can't get out of here.
This has taken over my app and
I haven't provided any way
to get out of it, okay?
So let's start by
adding a cancel button,
we're just gonna make it so
we can cancel out of this.
I'm gonna put it as a bar
button item in a navigation
controller so
I'm gonna pick this thing and
say embed in
navigation controller.
Okay, so I put this in
the navigation controller, so
now I can put up on top
of here a cancel button.
I'm going to put
it on the left,
it's another bar button item.
There happens to be a standard
one for that as well; cancel
and how do I make this
cancel button work?
How do I make it
actually cancel?
Well, this is where I do
the dismiss, so, let's wire
this up, target action to a
method that does the dismiss.
So, let's go into
automatic mode, here,
we've got our new expression
editor view controller.
I'm gonna control drag from
the cancel button over here.
Do an action okay, borrow but
an items in the argument and
I'm gonna call this cancel.
Of course, and
it's going to cancel.
And in here,
I need to dismiss.
But remember, I can't send
dismiss to myself, dismiss is
a view controller thing but
I can't dismiss myself.
I have to send it to my
presenting view controller.
So all view controllers know
who presented them, if any.
It could be nil, okay,
you might not have been
presented by another one.
I'm just gonna ask my
presenting view controller,
please dismiss whoever you've
presented, which is me.
And yes,
please do it animated.
And I don't need to find out
when it's finished dismissing,
so I'll just leave that off.
So now, if we run and
we go here and hit the plus,
Okay?
comes up here is
our table view.
We haven't done a UI yet but
if we cancel we goes back
into dismisses us, okay?
So we're in good shape.
So now let's go ahead and
do RUY,
let's go back to our
storyboard here.
And add RUI for these four
things, again we want the name
like sad happy whatever,
we want a little preview face,
and then we want the eyes and
the mouth.
So I'm just gonna start
dragging this stuff out and
we'll start working on making
it look good over time.
So for the name obviously
I'll need a text field so
I'm just gonna drag that out
and notice all these cells
are of type if you look
at the cell types here,
they're all custom cells.
Because I'm gonna be putting
custom UI in each of them.
We're gonna configure
that in a second.
What about here in our
little face view thing.
What are we gonna do
to show our face?
Well, I'm gonna start by
doing a face view ui view.
Yeah, let's put a generic
UI view in here.
I'll even put some nice auto
layout in here on this one,
is that it, yeah,
and we'll do reset to
suggested constraints,
check out constraints to
make sure it looks good.
Yeah, that looks good to me.
We'll inspect the identify and
make it be a face view so
we get a nice face in there.
So that's a good face.
So we have text field face.
What about for eyes and mouth?
How are we gonna set
our eyes and mouth?
I'm gonna use something
that something that
I haven't shown you yet,
which is a segmented control.
So segmented control
looks like this.
Okay, we'll drag one in here,
drag one in here as well.
And a segmented control lets
you choose from a number of
items up to maybe four or five
like a fixed number of items.
So that's perfect for
our eyes and
mouth cuz we have three
kinds of eyes positions and
five kinds of, of mouth.
And when you inspect
it right here,
you can say how many
different choices you want.
So for eyes we want three
segments, and here for
the mouth we're
gonna need five.
Okay, right frown, smile,
smirk, grin,
neutral, whatever.
And then you can
just edit these,
you just double-click on them.
So here let's say eyes open
here we'll say eyes closed
and, of course, our favorite
one which is squinting.
And then down here
we'll have frown and
smirk and oops sorry, neutral.
And what to grin I think,
then we add smile.
Okay, so there's our UI.
So we want to make some of
these things look a little
better like this text field
right here there's quite a few
things we want to set
about this text field.
One thing is we really
don't need a little border.
I zoom way in so
you can see here.
We don't really need
this border around.
It's in a text field row, so
that's kind of
it's own border.
So we're gonna go down
here and say border off so
it's not gonna
have any border.
Also I want the font to
be quite a bit larger,
let's say 24 point
would be good.
We'll have it be centered,
the text will be centered.
There's no reason to have
it left or right aligned.
Let's use place holder text,
that's really cool.
I'm gonna put name in here
as the Placeholder text.
That way I don't need to label
on the left that says name,
this is the name
of this emotion.
I'll just put this
placeholder there,
it'll be obvious to users.
That's the name.
And so they'll just click
there, and start typing.
And, also, for the keyboard,
I'm gonna have it
autocapitalize every word.
So that if you say sad it
will be capital S-A-D.
It will just look nicer in
my other table I think.
And then finally, what
about the auto layout here?
Where do we want
this to appear?
Well I think we just want
this thing to be centered in
there so I am going to pick
centered horizontally and
centered vertically I just
control dragged to this row.
And so, that's good enough.
You notice that it's yellow,
right?
Why is it yellow?
Because my constraints don't
match what's on screen.
So, I can fix that in
my document outline.
Indeed, here's that yellow.
I go up here, I click on this,
I'll use update frames here to
misplace it and moves
name into the right spot.
Okay, we already have our auto
layout and everything for
the face view.
How about this guy down here?
Let's us zoom in again and
look.
What I'm actually going to put
another constraint on here to
show you a little more
sophisticated constraints,
which is do I ever want
to allow this to spill of
the edges?
ta-table view so narrow that
it wouldn't even fit these?
And the answer is no way.
I would never want the table
view to be that narrow.
I always want it to be wide
enough to at least fit
all these buttons.
So I'm gonna CTRL + drag
from this right edge
over to this to do
the trailing space.
Okay.
So great to this eye beam
right here that you're
very similar with.
We can click on it.
Where is it?
There it is.
But I don't actually
want it to be 75.
I want it to be zero,
all the way over the edge.
But I don't actually don't
want it to be equal to zero.
Because then that means that
edge is always gonna be pinned
over there and that's gonna
stretch my control out and
I do want the secondary
control to be, you know,
fit into its text, but I don't
wanna be stuck over here.
So what I'm gonna do is make
it to be greater than or
equal to zero.
So we have not seen this
kind of constraint,
where you're not setting
it equal to something,
you're setting it
greater than equal.
what I'm saying is, the
distance between this edge and
And that's what,
right here must be
at least zero, so
it can't be negative, it can't
have pushed off the edge.
You see that?
That's gonna keep my table
view big enough, to do this.
And now, of course,
I need to do the same thing
on the other side of this.
I'll Ctrl+drag over here,
leading space.
And we'll click on this one
and we'll say 0 as well, and
we want this to be
greater than or equal.
So I'm just guaranteeing
that that thing is gonna be,
greater than or equal to.
Okay, now it's let's double
check all of our things here.
So we've got the trailing
space and leading space.
So this one also I probably
want in the middle, so
I'm gonna Ctrl+drag.
Okay, and say I want
horizontally and vertically.
Okay, so it's not where
it's supposed to be so
I can update its frame right
here and it looks good.
It's where it's
supposed to be.
I'm guaranteed that it's
never going to spill out over
the edges because I put
that side constraint in.
Let's do the exam same thing
with this one right here.
CTRL + drag.
Center it vertically.
Center it horizontally.
CTRL + drag to the edge.
This the trailing space.
We're going here.
We want it to be
greater than or
equal to zero, and
the same thing over here.
This the leading
edge will come out,
we want that to be greater
than or equal to zero.
Okay, get that right,
did I say greater
than equal to there?
Yes I did.
Okay, this one also,
not positioned properly,
no problem, we go over here.
Update frames, looking good.
Okay, a lot of layout issues.
All right, here's our UI here,
looking pretty good.
Let's go ahead and
run this and
just see what our UI
looks like, see if we.
Got everything where we
wanted, things are centered,
things are the right size,
all that business.
Okay so we'll go over here,
bring it up,
looking pretty good.
The only thing is, that face,
I'd like that face to
be as big as possible.
Look how the eyes are so
little they're almost
like solid eyes.
Really I'd like that
row in the table
to be a square since
my face is a circle.
I'd like it to be a square.
So how can I make
that a square?
Hopefully all of you know this
from your homework assignment.
How to control
the height of something.
I'm just gonna go into
my code right here for
my expression editor.
that row I'm gonna have the
table view's height for row.
And for
Okay?
I'm gonna say if the index
path we're talking about,
row equals 1 cuz that's
the second one down,
that's where my face is,
I'm kind of hard wiring this,
we could probably
use constants,
all that stuff in here.
Then, I'm gonna return the
table views bounds.size.width.
So I'm going make the height
equal to the width.
That way it'll be a square,
otherwise I'm gonna
return our superclasses,
cuz we're overriding
this function, right?
So TableView,
heightForRowAt, and
the TableView is our TableView
and the height is at
this index path that it's
asking us for right here.
Okay?
So, everybody got that?
So let's run, and see if
it makes that thing square.
Should make that face square.
All right, let's go back here.
sure enough we've got a nice
big square face here.
Click, and
Okay, so this is excellent.
We got our UI exactly
the way we want it.
Now we just need to
hook up our outlets and
actions to this thing.
We're gonna need outlets to
these two segmented controls
And an outlet to this name,
so we can get the name.
right here.
And build an expression out of
the settings of this switch.
And then obviously,
we're gonna need to be able to
set our face view to reflect
that as well.
So let's go do that.
Go back to our
storyboard here.
That, this up,
let's close that, all right.
Zoom in a little bit here.
Okay, so let's create outlets
for these two things and for
this name.
So Ctrl-drag over here.
Call that our nameTextField,
we'll control drag from
this guy down here, we'll call
this our eyeControl, and we'll
drag from this one,
call that our mouthControl.
Okay, so we got our nice,
outlets there.
Let's go ahead and think about
the model of this control,
what does it do?
It's an editor.
It edits an expression,
a named expression actually.
So it clearly has something
which is the name, okay?
So we'll make the name,
we'll have that be
our nameTextField.
Text, and if we don't
have a nameTextField yet,
like we're preloaded, we'll
just return a empty string.
Okay, so that's the name part.
And of course,
we have an expression as well,
that's gonna be
FacialExpression.
And we'll return by creating
a FacialExpression, and
here is its constructor, we'll
make it a little easier to see
when we're an arrow
here like this.
Okay, so
how are we gonna set the eyes?
We're gonna look at
our eye control and
see what the eyes are.
How do we set the mouth?
We're gonna look at
our mouth control.
So to make this easy,
I'm gonna make a little
private var here.
Actually a let.
I'm gonna call this my
eyeChoices, okay, these
are the three choices in my
set menu control view there,
it's just going to be a little
array that has facial, oops,
Z, equals an array with
FacialExpression.Eyes,
and we've got open, closed,
and squinting, those
are the Three different things
in our segmented control.
So now to make this I's
thing I can just return here
my i choices.
And the index I'm gonna
use is my eye control.
And the way you get which of
the segments is controlled is
picked in a segmented
control is with the method in
segmented control called
selected segment index.
Selected segment index.
And of course our eye
control might not be set yet,
in which case we'll default
to just doing segment 0.
Okay?
Does everybody see what we're,
what we're doing there?
To do that?
And same thing with the mouth.
We'll have some
mouth choices here.
These are
facialExpression.mouth.
What have we got here, frown.
We've got smirk,
we've got neutral,
we've got grin and
we've got smile.
Do the same thing here,
we'll say mouthChoices.
Okay?
So mouthControl this time,
selectedSegment Index.
And again we'll default to 0.
So everyone see how we've
created our facial expression
from our UI?
This is essentially our model,
it's a read only model.
You could imagine designing
this to not be read only,
where you might want to have
this editor start with some
expression you set.
But we're just gonna do
this to make it easy.
Read only.
And one other thing we want
to do is whenever these
are changed over here,
well, for
now every time someone clicks
on one of these we're just
gonna print on the console
what our expression is.
So let's create a little
target action from this guy,
control drag.
We'll call it
updateface cuz that's
what we're gonna need to do
is update this face up here.
We don't need any
arguments to it.
Okay so this update face is
gonna have to change this face
to reflect the eyes and stuff,
but for now I'm just gonna say
print our name equals
our expression.
So like sad equals,
you know frown plus
closed eyes or whatever.
Okay, and we'll have this
one do the exact same thing.
To the same action,
everybody cool?
So we just actions to make
our, our thing work here.
So let's go run, see if our
UI is basically working.
It's, it needs to be hooked
up to the rest of our app but
still we wanna make sure it's
it's functioning property,
properly.
Let's add, we'll call this,
here's a interesting thing.
So, let's go here.
See when I click on these
it selected this row.
I didn't want this row
to be selected like in
a table view sense.
I just wanted it to edit
this name right here so
that's not good, so
we'll have to fix that.
But let's go ahead and
put in a test name.
We'll say test, return.
Return doesn't get
rid of the keyboard.
So that's bad, bad UI.
Because now it's
really hard to get to
these things down here.
I can get to them,
because this is a scroll view.
Table view is a scroll view.
But it's still kinda bad UI.
So we gotta fix that as well.
So let's pick eyes closed and
see if our console is
saying anything and
sure it's saying test equals
eyes closed mouth frown.
That looks right eyes
closed mouth frown.
Let's say squinting grin.
Squinting grin.
Okay so it looks like
our UI is working but
it's got these two problems.
So let's fix the problem where
it's selecting this row in
the table view sense when
we click in there and
let's fix the problem
where a return key is not
resigning first responder and.
And making
the keyboard go away.
So both of those
are easy to do.
We can do that most of
this in a story board.
So let's go back to our story
board full screen here.
So the way to make it, so it
doesn't select rows in here,
is just- Select our
table view and if you,
when you do your inspector
on a table view, you'll see
there's selection down here
in the table view selector.
We want to change that to
no selection that means
rows are not selected
in our table view.
You almost always want this
in a static table view.
Rarely are you selecting the
rows in a table It it stack
table, sometimes you might be
but rarely are you doing that.
And the other problem was
our text field right here,
we wanted it to do
resign first responder.
So I'm gonna show you a little
trick here which is how we can
wire this text field up to our
view controller as a delegate
without any code.
Okay, so do the wiring up,
I'm just gonna control drag
from my text field up
to my view controller.
Remember this little yellow
thing at the top represents
my view controller.
So I'm gonna control
drag right there and
when I do, look,
I can hook up outlets.
I'm gonna hook up this text
field's delegate right there,
so now this view
controller is the delegate
of this text field.
Now we still have to go back
here and make it be a UI
text field delegate and
of course
we still want to implement
our text field should return.
Not should clear,
text field should return And
we're just gonna have the text
field resignFirstResponder.
Responds to [LAUGH]
resignFirstResponder and
return true.
I just want to just use that
as a trick to show you you can
Okay, so
control drag to set outwards
of things as well if you want.
So we fixed our two
problems right there.
So our UI should be
looking good now.
There it is, go here.
Okay, let's try the text
again, let's say Test, and
Return.
Design's first responder and
notice when I clicked on test
it didn't click this row,
when I click down here,
it's not clicking this row.
Even if I click on
the edges of it
Is still not selecting it.
Okay, what about the face?
We gotta get that face, so
it's updating,
based on what's going on here.
Now, we've offered the option
of squinting right here, so
really, what class
needs to be in here?
What's the only class
that does squinting?
It's that blinking face
view controller, right?
So we need to put
an NBC in here, okay?
Blinking face view
controller is an NBC,
we can't use face view, which
is what I have in here now.
Face view doesn't know
how to do squinting, so
we need to put an NBC.
So this is where we're
going to do an embedded
view controller, so let's do
the embedded view controller.
Okay, we're gonna go here,
we hit,
right now we have it's
face view inside here.
So we're just gonna get
rid of that face view,
we don't want that.
Oops, I dela deleted
the entire row, sorry.
Is that my face
view right there?
Yeah, so
we'll delete the face view and
instead of having a face view,
I'm gonna go over here and
look for a container view.
Container, there it is,
container view, I'm gonna drag
this container view in here.
I'm gonna do the exact same
thing as I did before.
I'm gonna use my bl let's,
zoom in a little so
I can see it a little better.
I'm gonna use my da dash blue
lines to place this thing
where I want.
I'm still going to do reset to
constraint, I'm going to check
that make sure that this
is all hooked up right.
It appears to be
hooked up right,
look what also appeared,
it's kind of hidden,
it's kind of afraid,
there it is, right here.
Okay, when we created this
in it also created this
new NBC right here.
Okay, this is the MVC whose
self.view is going to appear
right here, and all the auto
layout constraints are gonna
apply to it and everything so
it's gonna be fit in there and
everything.
So what do we want this to be?
Wel, we want it
to be a blinking,
face view controller.
So I'm gonna go here,
go to identity, Fir-,
I'm gonna select this.
Go to identity and say
blinking face view controller.
Of course, I have to still
build the UI of this thing and
of course it has
a face view in it.
So I'm gonna again try and
copy and paste,
it didn't work last time I
did it but we'll try again.
Paste, there we go.
Okay and so we're gonna
make it fit perfectly
in here as usual,
ahead and reset.
Adjust constraints and of
course, this phase view right
here needs to be wired up as
an outlet of this blinking
face view controller and
how am I gonna do that?
Same way I did that text
field delegate, so,
we'll control drag now from
the view controller to this
face view and wire it up.
We don't have to
bring up the code,
in a side by side window,
especially this is a pain for
blinking view controller.
Because, the, it's a subclass
of it, a superclass,
rather that we're hooking
up to, etc, okay?
So I built this embedded view,
I've created the MVC is
actually the way I want and
so now if we run.
We should have that blinking
view controller embedded
inside of this
into that row and
of course it should be square.
And all those things just
as if it were the regular
face view I'm sure
that here it is.
Okay now, how do make it so
when we change these things,
it changes this?
Well, this is just
a segue right here, so
in our prepare for segue,
we're gonna grab onto that
blinking view controller.
And then every time things
change, we'll just tell
the blinking view controller
what its expression is, so
let's give this thing a name.
We'll call this our EmbedFace,
segue right here, and let's
go back to our editor and it's
the thing we're segueing from.
So it's the thing that gets to
prepare, so let's go prepare
for segue, and
inside this prepare for segue.
All we really need to do
is grab onto that Face view
controller, so let's create
a little private var,
which we'll call our
faceViewController.
It's going to be of type
linkingFaceViewController and
it's not set initially, so
we'll have it be an optional.
And here I'm just gonna say
if the segue.destination
view controller is, actually
we'll even say if let.
Let's say if let Controller
we didn't mean to do that,
actually I can do an even
easier way to do it.
Let's just say face view
controller equals the segue's
destination as a blinking
view controller and
if it's not a blinking view
controller and won't work.
Then of course we probably
want to check our identifier
here so we'll say if
the segue's identifier =,
what did I call it?
Embed Face.
Then we'll do this.
Okay?
So all I did here,
when I'm preparing,
is just grab onto
that view controller, so now
I have the view controller.
So for example,
when updateFace happens, okay?
Instead of printing
out on the console,
I can just say that
my faceViewController
expression equals my
expression, right?
My expression is this thing
right here, cool with that?
Let's go see that.
Okay, so we go here,
we add eyes closed,
looking good and
the frown there, grin.
Notice that it started out
with the wrong face though,
so probably,
when I grab that face view
controller right here,
probably want to update it
right away with my expression.
Whatever expression
I have now.
In other words, as soon as
that embedded segue gets
embedded, I wanna have it
update with my my face, but
it's working, and it even
works for squinting, okay?
So we got squinting
even happening in here.
All right, we got this
awesome system here,
this awesome MVC for
editing and
emotion right with the
emotion's name and its face.
So how do we communicate
what we just edited back?
And that's through unwinding
ao let's go ahead and
create an unwind segue back
to our presenter okay.
And let's move this thing so
we can see this whole thing,
what we're doing here.
So we're going to create an
unwind from a done button in
this, and it's going to
unwind back to this guy.
And when it unwinds we'll
communicate the expression and
the name of the expression
that was chosen here in this
editor.
Now what's the first thing
we want to do in unwind?
We need to create that magic
method to unwind to, that's
always the first thing you're
gonna do when you unwind.
So that's over here in this
EmotionsViewController, so
let's go over to the
EmotionsViewController, and
create that magic method,
put it right here at the top.
Okay, it's gotta
be an IBAction.
Okay, just a function, we can
call it anything we want.
I'll call this,
addEmotionalFace, because
that's what it's gonna do,
it's gonna add an emotional
face to this array right here.
And I'll say from segue
UIStoryBoardSegue, and this
satisfies the second thing we
have to do which it has
one and only one argument.
And hit the storyboard segue
and inside here, we will use
the segue information to get
the expression that we chose.
So, now let's go back
to our storyboard.
And wire up that,
unwind which we do right here.
So I'm gonna add a done
button right here.
Click down here, this is
bar button, there it is.
Okay, I wanted
a standard one again,
this is the done button.
See all these standard
ones we had add for
the other one, cancel for the
other one, done for this one.
So we have done and
I'm just gonna control drag,
over there?
No, up here.
Okay, so this exit button.
look what appeared there,
add emotional face from.
When I let go,
Notice that it puts
the little from
that was the external
name on the end of it.
It's kind of a backwards
compatibility with objective c
there and so, I click that
I want that connection and
now it's made that segue.
Now where is that segue?
If I zoom out am I
gonna be able to see
that on my storyboard?
No, you don't see it, so
where are things that you
can't see in your storyboard?
Where do you go to find them?
Yeah, the document
outline here,
so let's go to the document
outline and sure enough,
Look at that, unwind segue
to add emotional faces,
right here.
we could give this segue.
A name, maybe we could call it
add emotion because that's
what it does, right?
It calls this add
emotional face so
it kind of add emotion segue.
Now we could transfer
our information kind of
either way, either in
the prepare in this guy.
But I usually like to do it
in this guy because this is
the guy who I would have to
create some public API to add
an emotional face or
something.
So I'm just gonna have this
guy and his special method.
He's going to ask the editor
there what is your expression
and name and it's gonna
add it to his model here.
All right, so
we're gonna say if we can let
the editor, basically
we'll call it editor.
If we can let the editor
equal the segue is what?
The source,
it's the source of the segue,
we're segueing from
the editor to this guy.
So this as
a ExpressionEditorViewCOntrol-
ler, so
if I'm able to get the editor,
then I'm just gonna
say EmotionalFaces.
Not kGuard [LAUGH]
EmotionalFaces, append, and
I wanna append a tuple,
and the tuple is
gonna have the editor's name,
and the editor's expression.
That's it!
To unwind?
Super simple, all right.
So, here's, we got worried.
We got happy, we got sad.
Let's add another one,
let's go, I don't know.
Now let's go, okay, this face
looks like contentment to me,
he looks content so
we're going to call
this one content.
Content, content,
there it is, okay?
So we've got this named
content, eyes closed, grin,
I'm going to hit done right
here, it's going to unwind and
add that, hopefully,
and it didn't show.
Anyone have an idea why
it didn't show there?
Because we appended
it to our model, but
we never told
the tableview to update.
Okay, so this is a common
thing you'll do, you'll update
your model and you're like,
my tableview doesn't work.
And we just need to
do tableview here,
reload data cuz it to call of
its UI table view data
source methods again.
Hopefully you experience that,
maybe in your
homework assignment.
You're used to this
particular forgetfulness but
here we go, try again.
Okay, we'll do content again,
I liked content, content,
Tent there it is and content
was what did I say, green.
Eyes closed yes looks content,
done, there's content.
We click on it,
we've got content,
we've got worried,
we've got happy.
Whoops, happy, okay?
Everybody understand
that unwinding?
Everyone understand the modal?
Lets go take a look
at this on iPad,
lets see what it
looks like here.
Okay, let's make
this a lot smaller,
is that the smallest
we can make it?
No, four, here we go.
Okay, so
here it is on iPad well,
lets go to landscape here,
make sure it's working.
Sad, happy, worried,
lets add another one, woah!
Big face, now, this is the
kind of UI that in your final
project you're going to
get dinged on the UI
part of the rubric,
because this is a horrible UI.
Look at the tiny,
little things at the bottom,
gigantic face this
is a classic,
my app works on iPad and
iPhone, okay?
Because I just
clicked the button that
said do iPad, okay?
Sometimes we have to do more
to make things work on both
platforms and in this case,
clearly this is bad UI.
it's an opportunity to make
points on your rubric and your
And in fact,
final project by implementing
an iPad specific idiom.
In this case that's what we
wanna do this clearly wants to
be in a pop over.
When we click this little
plus we want this a little
to appear right here in
that little pop over, so
what do we need to do that?
Is could be simpler, we gonna
go back to our story bore here
and we're gonna
change this segue,
which is currently our
modal segue, right?
The modal segway from
emotions right here
over to this editor from being
modal to being a popover.
Now we know that it
automatically is going to
adapt to being like modal
full screen on the iPhone.
So by changing it to popover
it's gonna work now on
both platforms but
we're going to see a little
bit of problems here.
All right, so, let's try it,
plus, nice, okay.
Maybe not seeing this very
well because of the high
resolution being
scaled way down but
it's picked a reasonable size,
it's a little bigger than
it needs to be,
it's a reasonable size.
But there's actually one thing
that's wrong with this UI
which is this cancel
button right here.
Okay on in a pop over you
don't have cancel buttons
because watch if I click
over here it canceled it, so
I don't need this cancel
button right here.
I need it on iPhone but
I don't need it on iPad, so
let's add a little bit of
code to take this cancel
button out.
If we're actually
in a pop over,
and the way I'm going to tell
I'm in a pop over is I'm going
to look at my pop over
presentation controller.
And see if my arrow is
pointing any way, and if my
arrow is pointing somewhere
I must be in a pop over.
If i don't have an arrow then
I'm probably over full screen.
Okay so let's go ahead and
do that.
Let's go back here
to our editor and
in our editor, I'm gonna do
this in view will appear.
Nice late in the game time to
do it, so view will appear,
super view will appear.
I'm just gonna say in here, if
I can If I can, and here I'll
make it wide so that I have
pick good variable names here.
If I can let
popoverPresentationController
= my navigationControllers
popoverPresentationController.
Now, why am I giving that
navigationControllers
popoverPresentationController?
Cuz it's actually
the highest level MVC
that's in the popover, okay?
Also, that cancel button
is in the
navigationController, right?
It's part of
the navigation items for
the navigationController,
so if I'm not in
a navigationController,
this whole thing is
kinda useless anyway.
So here I'm gonna say if the
popoverPresentationControll-
er's arrowDirection equals
unknown, or well let's say if
it doesn't equal unknown,
so it points somewhere.
Then I must be in a popover,
so I'm gonna remove
from my navigation items,
my left bar button item.
Okay, remember navigation item
is what controls, what bar
buttons appear when you are in
a navigation controller.
Okay, so here we go,
we click, no cancel button
which is good and we'll run
it on iPhone in a second and
we'll make sure the cancel
button is still there.
Okay, what's another
problem here though?
Well the problem is this
is a little too big,
it's kind of got this extra
space down here at the bottom
that we don't want, okay?
And, in fact, if I go this
way, and I slide this out and
bring this up, now it's
a little too small, so
it's either a little
too small or too big.
That's because it doesn't know
how big this thing is, so
it's just picking kind
of standard sizes.
For these particular
orientations, so
let's teach this MBC, this
editor MBC, how big it is.
And we're gonna do that by
adding up all the heights
of all the rows and seeing
which row is the widest.
By doing that, we'll be able
to see how big this section
in the table view is,
we'll do that, and
view will appear also.
I'm gonna say here,
var size = tableView., well,
it'd really be nice if I had
a method called minimumSize
forSection: 0, okay, if it
could just tell me the size.
And unfortunately, tableView
doesn't have a thing like that
but luckily for you I have
such a thing right here
as an extension today will
view and we don't have time
to type it all in such
like quick typed it.
But you can see as pretty easy
it's just goes through all
the rows in the section that
you ask and it gets the cell
at that row or even creates a
cell at that row if necessary.
And then it uses this really
cool method here, system
layout, size fitting, UI
layout, fitting compress size.
This guy right here
uses auto layout
to say what's the smallest
this thing can be, okay?
So this is a really
cool little function
that you can do in UI view.
By the way, notice I'm sending
that to the content view of
each cell.
We didn't talk about
content view but
each table view cell has a
content view that's where all
the contents really are.
And that's the thing you want
to ask to apply all the auto
layout rules to see
if it will fit.
So then here I'm just getting
the one that's has that's
the widest okay
maxing the width and
here I'm adding the heights
of the rows okay?
Height for row is just
the height of the row by
asking the delegate here.
Okay, so good, so we got
the size this is the size,
but actually we got a little
trickiness to do here because
we've got that
square face view.
I still want it to be square
even when I shrink it down.
So I'm going to take
the size's height and remove
the height that it got for
that
index path that the little
face is at, that's row 1.
Section 0, so
I'm gonna remove that and
I'm gonna add back
the width of the tableView.
Actually the width of
the tableView I calculated,
which is size, okay?
So I've just added
it's square, so
it's square in
the new smaller size.
Hopefully everybody understand
what I did there, it looks
like I'm missing something
here yes the parenthesis.
Set it as our prefered content
size equals that size.
So this prefered content
size remember is the thing
that tells the system
this is how big this MVC
should be when it's
in a pop over.
So let's see if that worked,
all right?
So let's just slide it
out here and click.
Perfect size right there,
right?
Let's do it in landscape,
click, perfect size, okay?
So that's how you get your
pop overs to fit their size
exactly, you've gotta figure
out what their size is.
Okay, that might be
a little work but
once you figure out what their
size especially using that
nice system fitting thing,
you can do that.
So last thing I wanna do
is go back to iPhone and
see what damage we've
over there by doing this
clicking this pop
over business in.
Okay, so
here's our iPhone version, so
still working here,
plus it's still adapting.
It not, it didn't show it in a
popover even though we changed
this segue to be a popover
on all platforms.
It does that adaptive behavior
to make this happen, okay,
it's still working fine,
though.
Call this happy.
Works like a charm,
let's take a look over here.
Okay?
This is landscape mode on the
phone, this is pretty good,
I'm sure, woah!
Big forehead guy.
Okay, now again
you could argue
well this is just the way it
makes it be but this is bad.
This is bad UI, I mean
really if you had an app and
you bought it and it did
this you'd be like what the?
Who wrote that?
Now this is a strange
situation where on an iPhone I
actually think this
would look a ton better
as a pop over, wouldn't it?
Because the pop over
is nice minimum size,
so if we had this thing where
you clicked on this plus.
And it made a nice little pop
over here wow that'd be just
really cool in landscape mode.
So how can I make it stop
adapting cuz that's, well
the problem here is when I hit
plus it's adapting to the fact
that it's on a compact width.
All right, and it's turning
it to full screen, so
I don't want that, I want
it to still be pop over.
So let's use those that
delegate method thing
I was talking about to
make it stop doing that.
So that delegate stuff
happens in the prepare for
this segway, that prepare
happens over here in
the emotions view controllers.
We already have a prepare for
that,
just preparing
a different segue,
it's the segue that
actually shows the face.
So here I'm just
gonna say else,
because I'm not talking
about that segue,
I'm gonna talking about
a different one else if
the segues destination
is the editor,
expression editor,
view controller, okay?
Then I wanna Prep my
popoverPresentationController
so I'm the delegate.
So I'm gonna say,
if I can let the
popoverPresentationController,
= segue, Destinations popover
presentation controller.
Remember that the presentation
controller is always
on the thing being presented,
it's controlling
the presentation itself.
Not the thing that's
presenting, but
the thing presented.
So now I'm just gonna
tell this popover
presentation controller to set
delegate to be myself, okay?
And then of course I
have to go up here and
say I'm a UI popover.
Presentation controller
delegates.
All the methods are optional,
so
I am nicely implementing that.
But I'm going to
implement the one,
which is this adaption,
adaptive behavior thing.
It's called adaptive
presentation style for
view controller,
trait collection.
Right here,
well maybe arguments
a little easier to see.
Okay, so this is the thing
where it's asking the pop over
presentation manager,
hey do you wanna control
the adapting behavior?
Right, how it adapts,
and I do.
And what is it
that I wanna do?
Well, when it's in
landscape mode in iPhone,
I want it to be pop over.
So basically what is
the traitCollection
of the iPhone in
landscape mode?
It's vertically compact.
It's the only case that's
vertically compact.
No other device has
So I'm gonna, just gonna say
if the traitCollection, okay,
cuz that's passed along to me
here as an argument, if I,
I'm gonna say if it
verticalSizeClass = compact,
then what's the adaptation
mode I want?
.none, do not adapt.
Just be your normal
pop over self.
However, if
the traitCollection
horizontalSizeClass is
compact, I do want to adapt.
In fact, I wanna adapt
to overFullScreen.
By the way, overFullScreen
means full screen and
don't show the view
controller behind it,
over, what you call,
full screen,
just .FullScreen is go
over the whole screen.
But let the one that I'm
on top of show through, and
usually if we do that one, we
blur, we put a blur background
or something like that,
you might check out UI visual
effects, if you wanna do
that in your final project.
UI visual effects great
way to do a blur.
Otherwise I'm
gonna return none,
because otherwise I'm regular
width or height or something.
I'm on an iPad
basically probably or
maybe I'm on an iPhone 6+ or
something like that.
iPhone 7+ but I don't wanna
adapt in those cases either.
All right, so this will
control the adapted behavior.
But one thing I have
here is destination,
we don't want destination
because the destination
of this segue is a UI
navigation controller okay?
We want here this destination
view controller that we
calculated by looking inside
the navigation controller, so
this is destination
view controller.
Okay so now let's run this.
Oops,
>> No segue dot.
>> No segue dot, yeah.
Okay, there we go.
So we've got our destination
view controller B in this
expression, then we're going
to become the pop-over
presentation for
those delegates.
And we'll implement this
adapted behavior where we
don't do it, in the case where
we're vertically compact.
So here this one,
is vertically regular, so
it's not doing that.
But in here,
we're vertically compact, so
this shows up as a pop-over.
Right?
long today.
And I will, see you Wednesday.
>> For more, please visit
us at Stanford.edu.