[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
Developing Applications for
iOS, Winter 2017.
This is lecture number 16.
We have some miscellaneous
topics today, all of which I
think might be interesting to
you for your final projects.
We're gonna talk
about alerts and
alert's cousin: action sheet.
We'll talk about
notifications,
that's the radio station
model from our MVC.
We'll talk about
the application lifecycle: we
already talked about
the lifecycle of view,
but now we're gonna talk
about the lifecycle of
the whole application.
And finally I'm gonna
talk about persistence.
How do we store stuff so
that when our app
launches it finds it and
of course you already know
a couple ways of doing that.
So I'm just gonna show
you a couple others.
Let's start with this alerts
and action sheets business.
These are "pop up and
ask the user a question"
kind of user interfaces.
They're both just MVCs,
alert and action sheet is just
an MVC, and they're always
presented modally or in
a popover, which as we learned
last time is basically modal.
So alerts pop up in
the middle of the screen,
they usually ask questions
with only two answers.
Like yes or no, OK and Cancel.
It is okay to have an alert I
guess with just an OK button.
Usually you wanna maybe think
of if there's a better way to
present that information
to the user than putting up
And then we start talking
about having three answers
an alert.
in alert.
(A) you might wanna think
about an action sheet,
which I'll talk
about in a second.
And (B) you just might wanna
think about how am I getting
the user in the situation
where I'm asking them
an emergency question,
and there's three
different answers or
even more than three, that
would really be interesting.
So, alerts are quite
disruptive to the UI.
The user is happily using
their user interface and
then bam, the whole screen
goes grey and there's this
little box in the middle and
it's giving them some alert.
I saw a class forum post about
using alert, and there was
a great suggestion there from
one of the TAs which is,
this is something you wanna
read the Apple human interface
guidelines about using alerts,
when to use them,
what to say in alert,
things like that.
And in fact, I recommend
all of you read the human
interface guidelines
from Apple in general, so
I'm gonna post that on the
class forum, the link to that.
And I'm actually going
to hold you to it in
the UI part of the rubric
in your final project.
So pay some close attention
to that, Apple's done
a really good job of analyzing
all the uses of the various UI
elements and kind of what
works well, what doesn't work
so well, and what's consistent
between different things so.
An alert can ask the user for
a little bit of text.
This has been abused to
make like login screens out of
alerts and things like that.
It's pretty rare in my
experience that you actually
wanna ask for text in
an alert, but I'll show you in
the demo today how to do it,
but it's pretty unusual.
And then there's
action sheets,
now an action sheet does not
gray out the whole screen and
appear in a little box,
instead on an iPhone it
slides up from the bottom.
And on an iPad,
it's always gonna pop over.
Now, an action sheet,
I like to think of as
a branching decision
user interface element.
So a user has gotten to some
point in the UI where you
simply can't really
proceed without knowing
what the user wants to do.
So for an example: maybe you
want to include an image in
something.
A contact, and
it's the profile image, or
something like that.
And do you want that image
to come from the camera,
where it's gonna take
a picture right now?
Or from the photo library,
past photos you've taken?
Or maybe from some collection
view of clip art or something,
avatars or whatever that you
provide, so you've kind of got
to go in one of these three
directions so an active sheet
might slide up from the bottom
and say you know add photo,
how do you wanna do it and
you get these choices.
And usually there's Cancel
also which is I didn't mean to
do that so cancel.
Action usually have
more then two answers.
It wouldn't be wrong
necessarily to have an action
sheet with only
two answers but
it just rarely does that
circumstance arise.
So what do these two
things look like?
This is what an action sheet
looks like on an iPhone.
You see how it slides up from
the bottom there and it has
some choices in it and this
is what an alert looks like.
It takes over
the whole screen.
This one happens to have
a little text field in it,
with two choices there.
So let's talk about the API.
To make these work because
it's the exact same API,
in fact it's the same MBC
that does both of them.
This is the API to create
this view controller,
it's called a UI
alert controller, and
it just has a title, which
is that thing at the top,
you see where it says
redeploy Cassini.
In the picture on the left
there, that's the title.
And then message is just
a short informational message
telling you what the heck
is going on right now.
And then preferred
style right there,
if you set that to action
sheet you get an action sheet.
If you set it to .alert you're
going to get an alert and
I'll show you that.
So the API for these is
basically identical except for
this one little preferred
style thing right there.
So once you've created your
alert, you wanna add buttons.
Now adding buttons to your
alert or action sheet,
is done with add action.
And the argument to add action
is a UI alert action object.
And UIAlertAction is
created with a title.
So that's the title
of the button.
A style, and we'll talk
about what all the styles,
the button styles are.
And then a handler.
Now, this handler is just
a closure that you provide.
This is the handler that's
gonna get executed if that
button is pressed, so
that's the model for
alerts, it couldn't
be simpler.
So let's look in example one,
we got Orbit Saturn right
there, see the title
is Orbit Saturn.
The style,
this style is called .default.
So the default style, the text
is gonna not be red, okay,
it's gonna be whatever color
you've got going on in
your app there, usually blue.
And then in my closure here,
this orbits Saturn, so
I'm gonna just go into
orbit around Saturn.
That's Cassini's mission by
the way, to go to orbit around
Saturn, so it's just going to
do it, if I click that button.
And let's add another button,
this one's explore Titan,
a moon out there.
This is a little bit outside,
well it's inside Cassini's
mission but
before we divert it,
we wanna make sure we're
gonna log in for example.
So here in my closure
you see I've logged in,
made sure I'm logged in
before I go to type.
But it's the same
kind of thing,
a default button right there.
All right, so we've got
those two default buttons,
the blue ones.
How about that closeup
of sun button.
Now if Cassini closed
up to the sun,
it will be destroyed cuz
it doesn't have enough
propulsion to escape
the sun gravity well there.
So I made the style of this
button be .destructive,
instead of .default.
And so .destructive in an
action sheet is gonna turn in
turn up red okay just so
that the user knows "
this one is probably something
I should be carefully with".
And anytime you have
a destructive action in your
closure, you are probably
going to want to confirm that
this really want do to
that destructive action.
In this case, for example I'm
gonna make them log in again
or something like that.
So that's destructive, and
then finally we've got the
cancel button at the bottom,
that's another type of button
called Cancel style and
you can see that it looks
a little different right,
it's kinda separated
from the other buttons.
It's not destructive in
fact it's the opposite of
destructive, it gets
you out of the problem.
Of this action sheet,
to go back to wherever
you were before,
you're not really gonna
redeploy Cassini.
And, but
it is separated down there.
It kind of gives it just
a little bit of a highlight.
So I've added all my actions,
I've got my buttons, and
now I want to make this action
sheet appear on screen.
And I do that with
the normal method that
we talked about before,
which is present.
Remember, present is a view
controller method that just
presents the new controller
using whatever modal
presentation style is set in
that view controller which by
default is modal.
So the action sheet
slides at the bottom and
it's being modally presented.
So that looks good
on the iPhone but
what about on the iPad.
It would look terrible if
that huge, if the thing was
all the way the width of
the iPad and came up.
Or if it was just tiny even in
the middle it was just look
out of place right there.
So of course on an iPad we put
this action sheet in a pop
And whatever button causes us
to have to do this branching
over.
decision, that's the button
that we're gonna have
the little arrow point to.
So how do we make that work?
we're presenting this alert
using the modal style.
Because right now,
So it would come up
modal on the iPad and
it would look terrible.
So instead,
we just have to go and
change our action sheet
MVC here to have a modal
presentation style
of pop over.
That means it's gonna still
present modal but pop over.
Pop over is
basically modal but
different kind of
presentation style.
And of course,
when it pops up,
we want the little arrow
to point at the redeploy
button in my bar
button item there.
And so we're gonna do that
with that same pop over
presentation controller that
we set the delegate of last
time so we could
control the adaptation.
Remember that from the demo?
And so we're gonna use that
same popover presentation
controller, and this time
we're gonna set its bar
button item to be the redeploy
bar button item, and
the presentation popover
presentation controller is
smart enough to know "I'm
gonna make my little arrow
point at that".
And as I said before with
the presentation controller,
you could also have the little
arrow point at an arbitrary
rect in a view or at a button.
That's it.
Now, what happens if we put
this code in there, this alert
modes, modal presentation
popover and we try and
run, (by the way it should be
lower-case p popover there).
And we now try to run
it back on the iPhone,
what's it gonna
look like there?
It's gonna look exactly
the same as it used to.
And why is that?
Adaptation, right?
It's gonna adapt to the fact
that in this case we have
a horizontally
compact environment.
And it's not going to
put it in a popover.
So that's an automatic
adaptation,
same thing we had before.
So it'll look fine.
So if you have an app
that's universal,
you'll obviously put
this little popover code
in right there and it'll look
fine on your other device.
So that's the action sheet,
what about alert?
Same thing exactly, basically
we're just gonna say that
the preferred style is
alert in this case.
Here I'm gonna add
a cancel button there.
I'm gonna add a login button.
And I'm also gonna add
a text field to this one,
so here's how I add
a new text field.
I just say to the MVC,
the alert MVC, addTextField.
Notice there's a little
closure there that I can
include to configure
that text field.
Set the placeholder text.
Actually, this looks like
a password, so I'll probably
want secure text turned on
in there, things like that.
Probably would wanna use
trailing closure syntax there
instead of using
the whole thing, but
I just wanted you to
see the argument,
it's called
a configuration handler,
cuz that's what it does.
It configures the text field.
You can add more than one
text field if you want.
And then, the way you get
the text out in your action,
this is sort of the login
button's action right there.
I'm gonna get the alert and
ask for its text fields,
which is an array
of text fields,
cuz I said you can have
more than one text field.
I'm gonna get the first
one out of there,
cuz I only have one.
I could do at sub-zero and
sub-one, whatever,
depending on how many I have.
And, then I'm gonna get
the text out of it.
So now I have the text
to other text, and so
it's really easy.
So let's have
the TextField work.
Again with alert style we
just present it modally.
Now, in this case,
we don't present this in
a popover on the iPad.
So, it looks exactly the same
as on the iPhone, a little box
in the middle, which is okay,
it actually looks okay there.
So, nothing special in
doing the alert case.
So that's it, that's
alerts and action sheets.
I have a little demo.
FaceIt here.
Show you what this looks like.
Code this up.
Here we are in FaceIt,
where we were before.
And watch what I'm
gonna do here.
So here I'm pressing
my add button here to
do this nice editor MVC.
What happens here
if I just hit done?
No.
It didn't work.
That's weird.
I'll try again.
Let's try something like grin.
Squinting.
Done.
I just made this work.
What's going on.
Well, actually,
this did work because look,
it added one right here.
It's just the name was blank.
I went up here, I hit done and
I didn't put a name.
So it comes back,
this is really bad UI,
because it "worked".
But this is clear now what the
user intends, for there to be
blank lines there they can't
even tell the difference
between when there's
something there or not.
So really what we'd like is,
when we click done right here,
we would like to put
up an alert if you
didn't give a name.
And maybe we'll even
put a text field in and
let you type the name
right there in the alert.
Which is a little questionable
UI but it's good for demo.
So that's what we're gonna do.
So we're gonna have this
done button right here,
put up an alert if
the name field is empty.
So how do we do that?
Let's go over here to our
editor MVC, the code here for
our editor.
Remember this code right here.
Pretty simple.
And what I'm gonna do, I wanna
prevent that unwind segue,
that done unwind segue,
I wanna prevent it from
happening if
the name is empty.
So how do I prevent a segue?
What's the method that I add?
I hear whispers of it,
yes I think I hear it.
Should perform segue,
remember that one,
should perform segue so should
perform segue with identifier.
I'm gonna implement that.
And I'm just gonna say if
the identifier is my unwind.
Does anyone remember
what our identifier was?
Let's go look it up so
we can remind ourselves
how we find it.
So, the it was,
the unwind out of here.
Now, of course, we don't get
to see our unwind segues
as these little arrow lines.
We had to go look in our
document outline over here.
And click on this MVC and look
at the bottom right there,
unwind segment, segue add
Emotion, we called it.
When we click on inspector,
we'll see it, and
we call it Add Emotion, that's
the identifier for that segue.
So now we know what
our segue's called,
let's check it here.
So if the identifier
is Add Emotion, and
if our name isEmpty,
then we wanna return false.
We do not want to allow to
segue to happen if that's
empty, otherwise,
what are we gonna return?
Well, some people would
mistakenly say return true.
But you don't want to
return true there,
you want to return super
should perform segue.
Because you wanna give your
super class a chance to,
it might have some segues, and
you wanna give it a chance.
To see if it want to allow
this particular identifier.
So don't forget that, when
you're overriding these things
don't return true there give
your super class chance.
So let's run this just to see
what this did, we haven't done
any alert here obviously we're
just preventing that done.
Let's see even that
works there we go.
Add, I'm not putting a name
in here, done and turn off.
It didn't unwind, see but this
would also be terrible UI.
The user would think no,
delete this app,
it doesn't work.
This is a broken app,
I'm clicking this button here.
It's not doing anything,
forget it.
So you never wanna have a UI
like that where you press
a button and
it just does nothing,
that's really bad UI so
do never do that.
Instead we want to do
an alert, so I'm gonna create
a little function to put
all this alert stuff in,
private funk we'll call
it handle unnamed face.
And in there we'll do
our alert business so
I'm just gonna do it up here,
I'm gonna handle
this UnnamedFace.
When I'm still gonna prevent
this segway because I cannot
do the segway when
this name's empty.
So I'm still gonna
return false but I'm
gonna handle this UnnamedFace
along the way here.
So here's handle unnamed face,
I want an alert easy alert
= UIAlertController.
Here's the argumnet down here,
title.
Let's have the title be
something like Invalid Face
and the message, there's a lot
of good stuff in the human
interface guidelines
about message here.
You don't want to scold
your user with these alert
messages.
We want to be nice to them,
so we just want
to kind of explain nicely
what's going on like.
We'll just have a face
must have a name or
something like that, maybe
even that's a little harsh.
But, we'll say, we don't want
it to be too long but by
the same token we don't it to
be, you know, terse and mean.
So we're kind of somewhere
in the middle, so
we'll say "a face
must have a name".
And of course the style here,
what is it?
Is it action sheet?
No, it's Alert style, so
I've created an alert.
This is a view controller this
is returning, if I look at
the type of alert right here,
it's an alert controller,
which is a UI view
controller sub class.
So I've got this nice thing,
let's just actually present
this and see what happens.
Let's go present
Alert Animated.
True, and we don't even
need a completion handler,
we rarely need that completion
handler by the way.
You know, it just tells you,
I've finished presenting this
thing, if you want to
do something you could.
Let's go back here.
Go here, again, I'm not
putting the name in, done.
Well it's better.
My app is still
completely broken though,
because whoa, I got this
modal view controller up,
and there's no way
to get rid of it.
So my app is completely dead.
The only way to
get out of this,
is to literally kill the app.
So we don't want that.
We never wanna have an alert
with no buttons, obviously.
So let's could give it
a button, go over here.
To our alert, say
alert.addAction remember is
how we do that, and
it's got a UIAlertAction and
let's look at the arguments
here for AlertAction.
We got a title, so, I'm just
gonna put an OK button.
I just got finished telling
you that you really don't
wanna have alerts that'd
only have one button.
But this is a demo, so
I'm just showing you
how to add a button.
Here's an OK button.
The style on this
one is a default,
it's just a default button,
it's not destructive, or
anything like that.
One could argue this
should almost be a cancel.
You're gonna see that I'm not
gonna make it like a cancel
appear in a second and
then the handler, we're not
doing anything when we click
OK, so now let's run it again.
Oops, got a parenthesis there.
All right, let's run again.
So here we go, we add,
not putting a name, hit done,
comes up invalid face.
A face must have a name,
now I'm back here.
This probably is
minimally okay, right?
This is probably fine, the
user would immediately know,
I gotta give it a name and
they go up here and
give it a name and
all would be well.
But in order to show you text
fields in alert, how about
when this comes up If give
give them a text field.
And let them enter a name, so
they don't have to go back,
enter a name, and click Done.
They can just type the name
right here, and click OK.
So how do we do that,
well one thing in our alert,
is that we would want
to add a text field.
And in configuration handler
we could figure this
to do whatever we want,
we'll just say we won't have
a configuration handler here.
And then in our add action,
when the user click OK,
I'm gonna look in
that text field,
get the text out of it and
put it in my name field.
Remember that this handler
gives you the action itself,
the same alert action.
It's kind of like if you had
a delegate method, you'd get
the thing that's delegating
same kind of thing here.
This action here would be
passed to you in the handler,
we don't need it though,
I'm just going to say that
my self.name/text field.
Its text equals the alerts
text fields, text fields,
text, actually I guess that's
all I needed to do there.
Text field is an array.
So let's grab the first one
out of there and get its text.
So this is fine except for
look we're presenting this
thing before we add the text
field so that's not good.
So let's put this down
here and try again.
All right, go here,
we're done.
Now I have a text
field in here,
we'll say Foo is the name we
want, and we click Okay and
it puts Foo in their name
text field, excellent.
However we're still
making them go back and
click done again, right?
Because now I can hit done and
it works, got this in here.
But it would be really
nice if I go into this
unnamed situation, and
I typed something here, and
I click okay, if it would
just do done automatically.
So does anyone remember how
we perform a segue from code?
Cuz that's what we need to do,
we need to perform that
unwind from our code.
I'm gonna do it right here
in my action handler,
I'm just gonna say
self.performSegue.
Exactly what you would
think and the identifier?
It's that add emotion,
which is the unwind segue and
the sender.
I don't really care
who the sender is,
I don't look at
that in my prepare,
I don't need it for
any reason.
That's all that's
required there.
It's a good chance for
me to show you perform segue,
segueing from code.
All done, here we go here.
Let's do our favorite one
which is contentment right
there, so
I didn't put the name in here.
Done, face must have a name,
I'll say content.
We click Okay, it comes back.
Here it is,
everybody understand "alert"?
Alert's pretty straightforward
to implement, action sheet is
pretty much exactly the same
way, no text fields.
Obviously, in an action sheet,
but
you just add more
actions in that case.
All right, back to our slides.
The next thing we're gonna
talk about Is notifications.
Notifications are the radio
station in that MVC
talk I gave right at
the beginning of the quarter.
This is how we can,
essentially,
broadcast information blindly
to other objects in our
application and have them tune
in if they're interested.
So how do we do this?
The key to making
notifications work is this
class called
NotificationCenter.
So there is a default
NotificationCenter,
which you get by accessing
the static bar called default
on NotificationCenter.
So you have
NotificationCenter.default
gives you this default
notification center.
And so you can do two things
once you have a default
notification center?
You can sign up to listen
to radio broadcast or
you can broadcast.
Now who that you
things you can do,
super simple API really they
do nice job with this one.
So first let's talk about
how you sign up to listen,
you wanna listen to
a certain radio station.
It's done with this method
that you send to the default
notification center
called add observer.
So add observer means
I'm listening to
this radio station.
And has three arguments,
the first one for
name is the name of
the radio station.
Now the type of that is
NSNotification.name.
And I'm gonna talk about
that in a second, but
that's just the name of radio
station you what to listen to.
The second argument
is object: Any?
That's basically, in a sense,
the sender, the broadcaster.
If you're only listen,
interested in a radio
station that's broadcast from
a certain object, then you
can put something there.
If you put nil there, it means
anybody broadcasting on that
radio station, I'm interested.
So it's just a way
of narrowing down.
The radio stations are kind
of weird in that you can have
multiple people broadcasting
on the same station.
It's not like a real radio
station where it's only one
radio station.
And then a third
argument is a queue,
(it's actually four arguments,
I guess).
The third argument is
a queue that you're gonna run
this closure on.
The fourth argument
is a closure.
So you sign up for
this radio station and
when there are broadcasts
this closure get to executed.
And that queue is
what queue that closure
get to execute it on.
If you say nil,
by the way, for
that queue you get executed
on the same queue that
the radio station broadcaster
is broadcasting on, but
very often here you're
gonna be doing UI stuff.
In which case, you wanna put
operation.mainqueue here.
Operation.main, I think is,
is what it was called.
Cuz you obviously need
to be on main queue
to do any UI work.
So inside this closure,
you can see there's one
argument which
is notification.
That is the broadcast packet,
if you wanna think of it
that was broadcast, and
inside there there's a couple
of things but the really
important thing is something
called the user info.
See that
notification.userInfo.
That's a dictionary
that the broadcaster
can put any information
they want for
people who are listening
to this radio station.
We'll have some examples to
see what kind of stuff people
put in their user info.
So that's it,
super straightforward.
This is how you listen
to a radio station.
So let's see, before I
show you an example of it,
let's talk about
NSNotification.Name.
Its types like this
which is really nice and
swift in iOS 10
they really typed
all of the things used to be
just string, have been type so
you know what type of thing
you're looking for here.
NSNotification.Name, what's
really cool about that,
is if you go look at
the documentation,
for NSNotification.Name,
you'll see all
of the radio stations that
iOS will broadcast on.
And there's a lot of them.
But it's a great way to
quickly learn what radio
stations there
are built into IOS.
They're all static vars, these
names of the radio stations
are static vars in
NSNOtification.Name.
Now you can create your own
NSNotification.Name, because
it's perfectly legal to create
your own radio station, and
broadcast if you want.
You just do that with
the string initializer for
the type NSNotification.Name.
NSNotification.Name, hopefully
by now you're familiar after
reading your reading
assignments and
stuff, it's just
a nested class, name,
it's a instruct or something
inside NSNotification.
That's why it's
NSNotification.Name.
So I'll talk about
broadcasting in a second.
But first I wanna show you
an example of listening.
So here's a radio station,
a system radio station called
UIContentSizeCategoryDidCha-
nge,
you see it there
under the forName.
And this if you go into your
settings app on your phone and
go under accessibility you'll
see that there is a text size
setting, looks like the thing
on the right there,
where you can set
the size of your text.
So when you get old like
me you can make the text
a little bit bigger and
still see without having
any reading glasses.
When your young like you you
can make it really small so
you can get more
text on screen.
So, when that changes
though all the apps
find out about it and each of
them then locally broadcast on
this radio station.
Now, radio stations
are only used for
broadcasting inside your app.
So the communication from
iOS the operating system
to the apps that this changed
is happening some other way.
You don't know what it is,
it's behind the scenes,
you don't care.
But when an app finds out
that this slider has changed,
it locally broadcasts on this
radio station UI content size
category did change.
Because those little, that
slider actually has, like,
detant marks on there,
and it's not just, like,
the point size or the font.
It's small, medium,
large, extra large,
extra extra large.
So, as you slide
that thing across.
So if I want to hear
about that change,
now why would I want to
hear that this is changing?
I don't need to hear it
from my fonts because
I'm being a good
programmer and
I'm using the text
styles in my UI.
Remember when we
went to the UI and
we set the text style
to be like body font or
headline font, or caption
font, remember when we were
doing the little
Tweet Twitter client there?
So those will automatically
get updated when this changes.
But what if I have
something else an icon or
some other image that really
wants to size itself depending
on the surrounding text.
If the text gets really small
maybe the icon wants to
if the text gets really big
the icon wants to get bigger.
get smaller,
So I might want to find out,
so I find out by signing
up to listen to this radio
station with addObserver.
And here I'm saying I'm only
interested if the UI
application object sends it.
I can probably put nil there
actually cuz I don't care who
sends this I know it's going
to be the application object,
but I don't really care.
And I am going to execute this
on the main queue because
I am going to do UI things for
sure, in reaction to that
size category changing.
And then inside my closure I
look at the notification and
in the dictionary there I'm
looking for the key called
UIContentSizeCategoryNewValue-
Key.
And I found out about that
by looking in
the documentation under
NSNotification.Name.UIContent-
SizeCategoryDidChange.
And when I looked at that
particular radio station.
It said in the documentation,
hey, you can use
UIContentSizeCategoryNewValu-
eKey to get out of the
dictionary the size category.
In other words the position
of that slider.
And so an example what the
value might be of that would
be UIContentSizeCategorySmall.
So now I found out, and
I'll find out every
time that changes.
I'll get a broadcast and
it'll tell me.
Now, I didn't really
talk about this, but
notice that addObserver,
that notification,
default notification center
method, it returned something.
This thing observer, which is
of type NS object protocol.
Basically it's a cookie.
You don't what it is,
you don't know what type
it is, all you use it for,
is later when you're no longer
interested in hearing about
this, you remove
this observer.
That's, that's saying to
the notification center,
I don't wanna hear about this
radio station anymore, so
don't send me
anymore broadcasts.
Now it's really
important to do that.
So usually we're going to
do something UI-oriented
like this.
And then in view
will disappear,
we're gonna remove observer
because it makes no sense to
listen to this radio station
and adjust our icon sizes and
stuff when we're
not on screen.
Now of course, this might
happen while we're off screen.
So perhaps in our view did
appear, or view will appear,
we might want to adjust
our icon sizes based on
this content size category.
Which you can get that
from the UI application,
you can just ask it what
it is and it will tell you,
you don't have to, have to get
a radio station notification,
to find out what it is.
That's an example of
listening to a radio station.
Now what about sending on
a radio station, broadcasting.
That's super simple, as well.
You get that default
notification center, and
you're gonna use
the method post.
Post takes the name of
the radio station to post on,
which again, you can invent
your own if you want.
The object, that's the sender,
in case people might only be
interested in this being
broadcast from certain people.
Usually, this would be self,
that you would put there.
And then there's
the user info.
That's that dictionary that
you get to pass to them.
So, that's the same user
info they're gonna get.
So, as soon as you
execute this post
all listeners, all people
who did addObserver, who
are listening on, for their
closure to execute on the same
queue as your posting this
on will immediately execute.
All the other ones, so
if you're posting this
off the main queue for
example and you're observers
are all on the main queue.
Their closures will just
be put on the queue,
they'll be put on
the main queue, and
they'll execute the next
opportunity that they have.
So that's it, posting and
posting to broadcasts on
the radio station, by the way
radio station that's just
something I made up,
nobody calls it that,
you're not gonna see
that in the docs,
it's just a analogy for
what's going on here.
That's notifications.
There's another kind of
radio station model thing,
which I'm not talking about,
which is key value observing.
And you might wanna look
up in the docs as well.
That's a way that you can
sign up to find out if a var
on some other object changes.
So, take a look at that if you
might be interested in that.
The next topic here is
the application life cycle.
You know how we have
a view life cycle,
we have an application one too
and you get to find out as
your application goes
through its life cycle.
So first let me talk about the
states that your application
can be in.
It can be in really one
of five conditions.
One is the top not running.
So that's, user has never,
not run your app,
obviously you're not running.
Your code,
there's no code executing in
any way related to your app.
No one's touched on
your icon or anything.
Then there's two
foreground states
after your app starts running.
One is called
the inactive state.
In the inactive state,
you don't get any events.
You can't draw any UI.
You're just kind of like
preparing to, to really run.
You're not active.
You're not being
shown on screen.
The user's not
interacting with you.
The other one the other
foreground state is active,
now this is the normal
state where you're getting
touch events, you're drawing
on screen, you're interacting
user perceives you as
an active application.
Then there's also
the background state.
Now the background state
is even less running than
the foreground inactive state,
in the background state you're
clearly not on screen and not
only are you not on screen and
interacting you're barely
running in the background and
your lifetime
there is limited.
You're probably not gonna run
for more than 30 seconds.
This is a transitory
state between
being in the foreground and
going to the next state
I'm gonna talk about,
which is to be suspended.
So, if you're suspended,
no code in your
application is running.
You're still in memory, but
you're just sitting
there not running.
You get no cycles.
Now, one thing you have to be,
you have to kind of understand
about how this life cycle
works is that you transition
through these states
in an orderly fashion.
So when you launch,
you go from not running,
to this foreground
inactive state, to active.
You always transition through
inactive to get to active.
When some other app is
switched to, someone launches
another app and you're the you
were the active app, you go
from active back to inactive
in the foreground briefly,
then around down to background
for up to 30 seconds or
so and then you get suspended
where you don't run at all.
So you always transition
through that flow to go
from you're the active
app to somebody else's
the other deactive app.
Now when you're in
suspended state and
you get killed for
whatever reason.
You go straight to killed and
no code of yours runs from
the time you're suspended,
to the time you get killed.
Why do you get killed?
Well, maybe the user
killed you, explicitly.
Maybe you started using
too much memory and
the system killed you.
Maybe the phone's battery
died, it got re-booted, for
some reason, whatever.
So when you're in
the suspended state,
you kind of have to be
ready to just be killed.
So you wouldn't want to
have any unsaved data, or
anything else going
on in that state,
that's why you get
the background state,
to kinda get ready for that.
Now, at each of these arrows,
these orange arrows,
you get a message sent to
your application delegate.
So far, we've only
used the application
delegate to have our little
core data stuff in there.
But there's a bunch
of methods in there.
You've seen them every time
you look and you had delegate.
And we're gonna talk about
what they all do and
when they're all called.
So the first one in your app
delegate is called application
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions.
There's also
a willFinishLaunchingWithOpti-
ons.
And it gives you
this dictionary.
And the dictionary,
the keys are
UIApplicationLaunchOptionsKey,
which you can look in the
documentation for that symbol.
And you'll find all the
various things that can appear
in this dictionary.
And the values depend
on what the key is.
By the way, all of these
app delegate methods,
you can also get by listening
to this radio stations.
So the radio station for
this one is the
UIApplicationDidFinishLauching
radio station and it's
notification .name.that If you
listen to that you'll get,
and you do add observer,
you'll get your closer called
when did launch finish
launching happens, so you
don't have to put it in your
app delegate you could put it
in other places other code.
What happens here in this
DidFinishLaunchWithOptions
what why does it get
called things like that,
why do you have
this dictionary?
Well, obviously when you
normally launch, this gets
called, the dictionary
doesn't have anything in it.
Because you just got
launch normally,
the user clicked on
your icon and launched.
But there are a lot
of other ways for
you to get launch
to buy the system.
And when those
other ways happen,
then you're gonna have this
dictionary to tell you why,
and give you
the information you need.
So one thing, for example,
is if your application opens
a certain kind of document,
let's say you're a PDF viewer
and you know how to open PDF
files and you've registered
that with the system.
Then if someone in some other
app says, open this PDF,
the system's gonna launch you.
And when it launches you,
in the dictionary right there
is gonna be that
URL with some key.
It's telling you to open it.
And so that's an example,
another one is,
you have set up, you can
set up with core location.
I didn't get to talk about
core location this quarter,
but you can set up a core
location mechanism, whereby,
if you go by someplace in
the world, the dry cleaner,
just the canonical example,
when you walk by the dry
cleaner, your app will launch.
So you could set it up and
if that happens again,
this dictionary will say,
hey I launched you because you
went to one of your
registered locations and
here it is when you worked.
You can also do it for
continuing activities.
I don't know if you guys
know about this feature,
it's kind of a nice feature.
You start browsing something
on your phone, and
then you switch
over to your iPad.
You can continue browsing
from exactly where you were.
So you might get
launched to do that,
to continue doing
what you were doing.
If you get a push
notification,
we didn't really talk about
notifications much except for
in the cloud kit section,
I hope you,
how many of you saw the cloud
kit Friday section?
It's only a few of you, it's
worth going back and looking
at just to see notifications
and push notifications.
But if you get a push
notification sent to you and
your app's not running,
it may get launched
to handle that thing.
Or if you have some Bluetooth
device that you connect with,
it, it gets in range and
it gets launched.
So there's a lot
of reasons your
application might
get launched.
And when it does,
that dictionary's going
to have the information
related to that
particular launch.
Now I'm gonna warn you of
something, when you're doing
your final project,
you're gonna be searching on
the Internet all the time
to find ways to do things.
And you might run across
really old posts, which you
can often tell because they're
in Objective C versus Swift.
But if you ever
see a post where
someone in their application
did finish launching with
options is like saying UI
split view controller init,
or navigation init.
And they're building their
UI in code right there,
that's pre-story board code,
we do that stuff in
the story board now.
The times that we build any
UI in application did finish
launching, 0.001% of the time.
So I just wanna make sure you
don't get confused by that.
So this little delegate method
is sent with that arrow
right there.
You see the arrow
that's down there?
So that's the arrow where
you go from not running
into being inactive.
So you're running,
you can do stuff, but
you're not on screen.
So in
ApplicationDidFinishLaunching
with options, you could
be building your UI, but
you can't put it
on screen yet.
I mean,
it won't appear on screen
cuz you're still inactive.
Now I wanna talk briefly
about an opposite
arrow there that can go
into the inactive state.
You can get into inactive
from running, but
you can also get inactive
when you were running.
And things happen, like you
switch to another app, other
things can happen that cause
you to go back to the inactive
state, where you no
longer can do UI.
This transition, which is the
WillResignActive transition,
you want to think of
that as the pause button.
This is where your
app wants to pause.
So if we were doing
an asteroids app,
I'd want to stop all
of my asteroids,
remember what their
velocities were.
And be in a pause state.
And then I'll show
you what I'm gonna
unpause in a second here.
Then bring it all back.
So this is pause, I like to
think of this one as pause,
you're going from being
the active app where your UI's
working to this
inactive state.
You're still in
the foreground.
Now what causes
this to happen?
A phone call comes in,
when a phone call comes in,
your app kind of is
in the background.
It's, you can't do any UI,
it gets no events because the
person's talking on the phone.
But as soon as their
phone call ends,
you go back to being
the active state,
you never went into
the background.
You just were
foreground inactive.
Or you'll pass
through this arrow
on your way to the background.
Someone did click on
another app, and so
you're transitioning back
here, still wanna pause.
And then you're gonna go to
the background, gonna clean up
some more cuz you might
get terminated later.
But here, you still,
i's worth pausing as you pass
through here, so tha's
what the resign state is.
This other arrow going
in the other direction,
this is when your app
really starts up.
So this is when your
UI is available.
Here's where you
wanna unpause.
If you have paused,
then here's where you unpause,
is in this DidBecomeActive.
Because you're gonna pass
through this on your way back
from being in the background
or when the phone call ends,
then you're gonna go active.
So this is the unpause.
Now you only unpause
obviously if you're paused.
You never paused,
then there's no unpause here.
This little arrow
down in the corner,
this is
the DidEnterBackground state,
this is where you wanna
batten down the hatches.
You wanna save any
unsaved information,
you've already
paused probably,
because you went up through
the active, can't get there
from active, unless you went
through the inactive pause.
See how the arrows go there,
so
here's where you
wanna save things.
You wanna get yourself in
the state, you got about 30
seconds to do it where
you could be killed and
usually would lose any data or
anything.
This is also a good
place maybe to
save your state a little bit,
so if you did get killed and
you got run again,
you could start up
exactly where you were.
And there's actually
certain infrastructure in
UI application, which
I'll mention in a second,
to do that.
So this is the batten down
the hatches area right here,
the transition.
When you come back out
of the background, so
you were in the background or
suspended, when you come back
out, you're gonna get this
ApplicationWillEnterForegro-
und.
So, that's the thing that
says, you will, back up,
this is where you can unbatten
down the hatches if you
wanna open some files
that you had closed or
something like that,
you can do that here.
Have you got that?
So these are the transitions
you make through the lifetime
of your application.
The ApplicationDelegate is
involved in a lot of other
things as well besides
just the lifecycle.
For example, state
restoration, this is the thing
I was telling you be, just
moments ago, where you can
save your state, so that when
you launch again, yo're in
exactly the same state on
the same view controller.
Maybe even your first
responder is the same blinking
cursor and the same
text field or whatever,
you can save all that,
there's a whole mechanism for
doing that.
You can take a look
at it if you want,
might be a good thing to get a
rubric point out of in there.
Also data protection, so
the data on your phone
is protected by default when
you're in the locked state.
Your phone is locked.
Then all the phone,
data on it is encrypted, so
even if someone broke into
the phone somehow and
got the data out
of the static ram.
It would all be encrypted,
so it'll be useless anyway.
So the AppDelegate
can tell you when
data becomes unencrypted and
available for use.
In other words, unlock, the
screen has been unlocked, or
when it goes back
to being locked.
You can open URLs
in other apps.
There's a method, I think you
wanted the extra credit items.
Or maybe we've even made it as
part of the required
task of one.
So you probably know
how to do that.
This is the other way around.
This is someone's asking you
to open a URL in AppDelegate.
So this is: you'll
get this message,
your AppDelegate saying, hey,
this, some other app wants you
to open this URL, and
you can go do it.
Similar to if you
got launched,
if you didn't get
launched to it,
because if you got
it's gonna be in that
dictionary, but otherwise,
you'll get this method.
And there's also
a whole mechanism for
background fetching.
Sometimes you might have an
app, it's a social media app.
And you wanna have up
to date information for
the user at all times, so that
if they launch, they're seeing
the latest posts on your
Facebook page, or whatever.
And to do that, you can set
up this background fetching.
Now, the background fetching
is not happening once a minute
or anything like that.
It's happening, you know,
occasionally in
the background, and
if you try to do too much,
the system,
will get upset at you and stop
doing, scheduling you so much.
But what happens here in the
background fetching is, you
move from the suspended state
into the background state for
30 seconds or less, usually.
And you go you get to go
fetch on the network or
get your latest information,
and
then you go back to suspended.
So that way if you go
suspended background,
foreground active really
quick, you got the data.
There's a few other things,
but that's mostly what
the ApplicationDelegate
is all about.
Now application delegate of
course has to be a delegate
of some object.
And it's a delegate
of UI application.
So UI application is a class
there's only a single instance
that you ever
have in your app.
You get it by saying
UIApplication.shared and
it manages all
the global behavior.
Which sounds like, wow this
is really important object.
But actually it's
not that important.
You almost never interact with
UIApplication, because it
delegates all the interesting
things to its app delegates.
But there are a few
things that you can do in
UIApplication.
For example, here's where you
can open URL in another app
you can register to receive
push notifications here.
Push notifications
your app will not get
unless you call this
registerForRemoteNotifications
in UIApplication.
By the way, notifications,
push notifications and
local notifications have been
unified in iOS 10 to this UN
notifications framework.
A local notification, a push
notification you probably know
what this is that's when
some server send you
some information like in
the cloud kit case where it's
telling you hey some data
changed in your data base.
But local notification
are kind of cool as well.
You can set up local
notification that will fire at
a certain time.
That's how a calendar app
reminds you when you have
a particular appointment or
rather it's using local
notifications and you schedule
them for a certain time.
I think you can also do local
notifications for location
changes, and you get near
the dry cleaner or whatever.
So local notifications,
put push notifications
are unified in iOS 10 and
it's not part of UIApplication
it's this other framework.
Unfortunately I didn't
have time to go over that.
By the way also local
notifications is different
from NSnotification,
or just notification.
Notification is that
radio station thing,
local notification, and push
notification are the, this
other mechanism for notifying
the user which is actually
completely different not
related to each other at all.
In application you can also
set the fetching interval for
that background fetching
thing I talked about.
If you get into
the background and
you need more time, because
30 seconds is not enough.
Something is blocking or
you need to get something from
the network and
you want some more time.
You can ask for more time by
asking the UI application
object to begin
a background task.
Now, again,
you can't abuse this.
If you keep asking for
more and more time, and
you're trying to run for
ten minutes,
eventually the system's
gonna say, that's enough.
This is for, just exceptional
circumstances where,
"argh, I need another
minute please".
Can I have some more time?
And it'll give it to you as
long as you don't abuse it.
The little spinner in the
upper left hand corner of your
device, okay, that spins.
Have you ever seen that thing
spinning when you're doing
something on the network?
You can control that,
you can turn it on and
off with this bool
in UIApplication.
You can also find out a lot of
information like remember that
category sizer, the little
slider text size slider.
You can find out what
the preferred content slide
category currently is.
You can find out how much
time you got remaining
on your background,
sitting in the background.
You can also find
which state you're in,
foreground inactive,
foreground active background.
You can find out which of
those states you're in.
So you're application's
a little bit of a clearing
house for that kind of
global information.
So that's it for
UIApplication.
Info.plist, we've
already seen Info.plist.
Info.plist is really like
a raw data file that's storing
a lot of your
application's settings.
We saw the one where
we had HTTP URLs and
we want it to allow
those unsecure ones,
remember that the app
transport security.
We actually went and
edited our Info.plist.
You can see it looks like
this when you click on it.
This is a property
list editor right here.
So on the left hand side
you're gonna have strings and
dictionaries and arrays.
Things that property lists
are allowed to have.
And on the right
you're gonna have
the values that are in there.
This is really
backing an XML file,
this property list that
stores an XML file.
You can actually
right-click on it and
edit it as an XML file.
I strongly recommend
against this because
you can break this so easily.
And then now the app won't be
able to read this info.plist
anymore, so I recommend
against doing that.
But usually all
these settings,
you edit them in the project
settings, right.
You're not going
to the Info.plist.
But it doesn't
happen to be one or
at least I've never found
one for that app transport
security, but maybe they want
it intentionally obscure
because they want your app
to be secure in that way.
But you've seen many,
many settings here,
like do we allow a portrait
upside down, and
things like that, these are
all stored in the Info.plist.
So this settings UI that
you see is pretty much
an editor also on
Info.plist for
a lot of the things
that you see there.
Another thing that you'll
see in your settings
are capabilities.
They're a number of features,
couple dozen maybe, that
require an external server.
Some external resource
like iCloud or
like CloudKit, requires some
server that's storing all that
data out there or Game Center.
Is has all the servers so
people can get together and
play games and
things like that.
When you have that kind of
thing where you essentially
need your app to be
authenticated so
that it it the server you're
talking to knows it's you.
Then you're going to have to
go to the capabilities tab in
the project settings and
turn it on.
And turning it on, basically
means update my entitlements
so that I'm entitled to
do this particular thing.
So, see some of the examples
up there besides iCloud and
Game Center at the top,
you have Apple Pay,
In App Purchases, obviously
these things require servers
and people connecting
to them and things.
Even the background
fetching modes and
things like that require some
entitlement if you're gonna be
doing fetching while
in the background.
So, check these out, this is
a cool thing just to see what
features there are out there.
Again, maybe way to
get add some breadth,
some of them are not that
difficult to implement,
simple versions of anyway.
But, you have to turn these
on just to enable them.
My last topic here
today is persistence.
So persistence just means
making data stay on the disk
when after your app
is killed or dies.
You already know about two
really important ones.
User defaults which is tiny
little pieces of data,
preferences kind of data.
And has to be in
PropertyLIst format.
And then there's Core Data,
which is kind of the opposite.
Monster relational database
can have huge data in there.
It's really for
a data centric applications,
applications where the data
is what is all about.
So, I'm not gonna
talk about those.
You know about those.
I'm going to talk about
these last three briefly.
Archiving.
So archiving is a way of
storing an object graph that
is not a property
list on disk.
Your storyboard is archived.
Take all those views
archives them to disk.
So, I talked about that.
SQLite, we all
know what SQL is,
its relation on
database technology.
iOS comes with kind of a light
version of SQL at which
you don't usually ever use
cuz you're using Core Data.
Core Data's actually built
on top of SQLite which
you don't have to
access SQL directly.
And finally,
you can make things persist by
putting them in
the Unix file system.
iOS, put Unix underneath, so
you can put things
in that file system.
We'll talk about
how to do that.
So, let's talk about
archiving thing.
Do not get the idea that
this is a good way to
have an arbitrary object
graph that you have, and
store it on disc.
Because archiving
requires the involvement
of all the objects that
want to be archived.
Each of them has to implement
these two methods up here
in code which essentially
takes your object and
converts it into a dictionary.
Not quite that, but
that's 90% of what it is.
So converts to dictionary.
And then it also has to
implement this initializer,
any object that wants to be
archived has to implement
this initializer.
Which essentially gives you
back that dictionary and
tells you to create
your objects from it.
Now this is kind of special,
this mechanism because
the system is smart enough to
know when you put an object
in your dictionary.
And someone else in
the same object graph
puts that object in there
if that's the same object.
So it's not gonna ask that
object to reconstitute itself
twice it's only gonna
ask to do it once and
then it's gonna make
pointers to it.
So this is how the storyboard
can work, if you think about
the storyboard,
it's got a view hierarchy.
All those views are pointing
to other views in their
subviews but
they're also pointing
back to their superviews.
And obviously you only want
one copy of every view in
that hierarchy.
So UI view implements this
coding protocol that has this
methods in it.
And that's why view can be
archived and all the sub cost
of UI view that come
with iOS like label and
button they also
implement this.
And that's why the storyboard
could be archived.
But in the end if you
start having an arbitrary
you try to implement this in
code and UI for all of thems.
object graph, and
It starts to be more work
than for example, just
making a core data database,
to store that data in.
Or converting it to
a property list and
using user defaults if
it's a small thing.
So this people here listen and
they're like, that's cool,
yeah I've got a big
object graph of data and
I'm just gonna put it
on this using this.
Well it's a little more
involved than you might think.
And it also, you have to know
what you're doing here to make
sure you get those back
pointers properly set up and
things like that.
SQLite, so
this is SQL in a single file,
one gigantic file
the entire SQL database.
It's not a network thing it's
purely just a local file.
SQLite is an Open Source
project, comes with iOS.
It's not really good for
everything.
I wouldn't store huge
things in there.
It's not really built for
that I'll probably put huge
things in the file system.
Even core data when you
create something big like
attribute NSData there's
a switch in there.
You can turn on which is store
this in the external file not
actually in the data base.
And that's usually worth
filling if the object is gonna
be fairly large.
The API to use in SQLite
directly looks like c.
Not surprisingly it's not
object oriented in any way
it's just classic single SQL
call there's functions that
you pass SQL language
to basically.
And it executes it and even
though core data uses it you
don't see it from
core data directly.
You know, there's a new
probably use SQL is
if you had some existing
database or something.
The file system,
now the file system is
something that I would imagine
some of you might want to
use in your final project.
And your access to the Unix
filesystem that underlies
your application is
a little bit limited.
And so the way that you access
it is generally be used four
steps.
First you're gonna get a URL
into the Unix filesystem and
there are about
20 preset points
in the Unix filesystem
that you can get a URL to.
And once you've got that URL,
then you can create
directories there.
Create files there by taking
your URL and adding path
components to it to describe
directories and files.
Then you write to the files,
you're usually doing this
with the data object.
Or there's some property lists
methods that can write out
to a file.
And then finally you're gonna
manage all those files with
a class called a file manager.
So the file manager
lets you copy files and
remove files and
list files and directories.
And all the things you can
do with a file system,
you do with a file manager.
So these are the main aspects
of accessing the file system.
So let's look at each
of these things.
It's a Unix filesystem it
starts at root of course it's
protected, there's
permissions.
So you can't go writing files
into system directories or
even reading a lot of
the system directories.
And you certainly
can't see other apps
what they're doing over there.
That's completely
off limits there.
In fact,
you can only write and
read inside what's called
your application's sandbox.
So sandbox is this totally
segregated part of the file
system.
do things.
And now why do we
have a sandbox?
It might seem obvious
to you for some things.
For example security
is a big one.
We don't want other apps to be
able to reach into your app
and damage you.
That would be really bad.
So we gotta have security for
that.
There's privacy, we wouldn't
want those other apps to
be able to look inside you and
see your private data either.
But another interesting reason
that you wouldn't maybe
think of is clean up.
If someone deletes your app
from their phone entirely they
want everything this app has
ever created to be gone.
And by having the sandbox, and
that's the only place you can
write, when you delete, it
deletes your entire sandbox.
So anything you've
ever created is gone.
So you don't have to worry
about people writing
things into system
directories and all of that.
Which happens all over
the place on the Mac for
example, you're home directory
slash library has got
all kinds of junk in there.
They don't have the same
concept there of everything
being isolated like
you have in iOS.
So it's actually a cool
feature have the sandbox.
Now inside the sandbox there
are certain directories that
you can get URL too,
I can says about 20 of them.
So for example, there's
the application directory
that's where your
applications binary is.
You can only read and In there
read only, you cannot write
to your own application no
self modifying code allowed,
in IOS.
This is also where you
might have things JPEG's or
other things if you don't
use the image assets things.
You can actually
just drag JPEG's or
whatever directory
into your project.
And they'll appear in you
application bundle you
can look at the directly.
We rarely do that, by the way.
But other URL's that you
can look in there that
are kinda cool.
There's the documents
directory, that's a big one.
That's where you're gonna
put user created data
that the user cares about.
What the user perceives
as their documents.
Even if you don't have a
document oriented application
the user considers that as
like that's their data.
That's what they entered.
Now you're app might store
that on the network.
So maybe
Or your app is just not the
kind of app that has data like
that, fine.
But if it does
the documents directory is
your primary place you're
gonna store stuff.
But sometimes the user
creates things and
you're really just cashing it.
So for example,
let's go back to our
Twitter client, Smashtag.
In Smashtag we
downloaded images and
maybe we wanted to
keep the images that
were associated with
the image tab local.
That way I'm local even
though I'm not connected
to the network.
But those aren't really user
data their just something I
wanna cache.
I just want to keep them
local so for ease of use.
But as things go
out of recent,
I'd probably clear them out.
And if that cache directory
got completely cleared out it
would be fine I'd just
reload them all again.
So the caches
directory is a place
to put stuff that you
can easily get again.
Images and
stuff that you're caching.
And there's a bunch
of other directories.
I don't have time to
talk about all of them,
unfortunately.
So how do we get our URL
to one of these special
directories like
the document structure or
the caches directory,
things like that?
We're gonna use this
another default,
just like we had in in this
notification center.default.
Now we have
FileManager.default.
So the FileManager is
the thing that lets you
manage the entire file system,
and
it has a default one
that you can use.
And it has a method
called URLs for
directory in domainMask, okay.
That's this method
you see right here.
And it gives you
an array of URLs.
In iOS, there's only
ever one URL in there.
The reason this is an array on
desktop machines like the Mac,
sometimes you'll have like
a library directory that has
one for the user,
one on the network so
there's multiple of them.
But in iOS all things
are inside the sandbox so
the only domain, that's why
the user domain mask there is
user domain mask.
So there's only ever one URL.
So there's only one URL for
your documents directory.
One URL for
your caches directory.
your documentation directory.
One URL for your application,
okay, just one.
Just the one in the sandbox.
So you specify which
directory you want with that
argument therefore directory.
And that has to be a type
FileManager.SearchPathDirect-
ory.
So again, look that up
in the documentation and
you'll see the various
directories in your sandbox
that you can look at.
There's about 20 of them.
And if you are the document
director for example,
you say .documentDirectory
right there.
And it will give you back an
array where there is only one
thing in there.
document directory
in your sandbox.
Make sense?
So that's how we get in.
Once we get in, we want to
create directories in there,
create files, whatever.
We, or access files.
We do those by using these
appending methods in URL.
So we have that URL and
we send a message to the URL.
Like give me a new URL by
URL appendingPathComponent
whatever the name of my
directory or the name of
the file that I want or by
appending path extension, so
.jpeg, or something like that,
so I can get my jpeg file.
So by doing that I
build a path, the URL,
to the file I want.
So that's how I navigate
around in my sand box.
So now I have the URL and
I can do a lot of
things with that URL.
I'll show you in a moment how
you can write files out and
things like that but you can
also find out about things URL
like is this a file?
Or is it a directory?
Or is it on the network for
example?
Cuz you have a URL
that someone gives you,
maybe it's a network URL.
Http, colon, slash,
slash, something.
Well that's not a file URL so
is file, file URL right there,
we tell you that it's
in the file system.
A really powerful method in
URL is resourceValues for
keys.
So resource values for keys
you give it an array of keys
that are attributes of files,
these keys are attributes of
files, like the files size, or
the files creation date,
or whatever.
And it will return you a
dictionary with those keys and
the values for the file, for
the URL that you're
pointing to.
So that's how you can find
out the size of the file,
where the creationDate or
whether isDirectory.
Things like that.
Notice the listing throws so
be careful here.
You have to do this in a try.
How about writing files
out to the file system.
Well mostly we do
this with a data.
If you have for
example a UI image and
you wanna store on
your screen, or
whatever that you downloaded
from the internet, and
you wanna store that
into the file system,
there's actually a cool
function called, I think,
UI image jpeg representation
or something like that.
And you give it a UI image,
and it will return a data.
And a data will have
the data of the jpeg image.
That you can store.
And then you can
say write to url.
So this is a data method here
write to URL atomically.
And then we'll write
it out to that URL.
So you have to build yourself
URL like get in the sandbox
directory, and then depending
whatever name you want to it.
Then you say write to URL,
atomically just means it'll
safely, it'll write it
to a temp file first and
then swap it in so
if you ran out of disk space
while writing it or something
it wouldn't corrupt if a file
that was already there for
example.
Now, to get the data object
back you just use the same
initializer you used when
we did some hashtag or
the lecture before that,
what we said data init,
contents of URL.
Now in that case,
if the URL was a network URL
and it blocked the main queue,
here that URL could
be a file system URL.
And it wouldn't block
the main queue.
Loading files up super fast.
So you don't really need
to do that in a separate
thread unless maybe it
was a gigantic file.
But even then, maybe you
could do that, yeah question.
When would you not wanna
do atomically right here?
It's hard for me to even think
of an example with that.
Maybe it's a really
huge file and
you don't wanna create
two copies of it.
The safe copy and
then over, and so
you've got an existing copy
of a huge file, let's say.
And you don't wanna
create another copy of it
as a safe copy before
you move it in, so,
that you might say
atomically no so,
it just destroys your old one
right off of that, I mean,
I'm really stretching to
think of good example,
you almost always
want true to there.
So, that's how you read and
write files with data,
very common way to do that.
Once you've written out files,
you want to be able to go
through your file system and
like look at what files are in
certain directories or
things like that.
Maybe you've got
caches out there and
you want to see what's in
your cache or whatever.
And that's what
FileManager's for.
It has dozens of methods for
doing that like,
createDirectory( at url, which
will create a directory for
you so
you can put files in there.
And it also has a bunch,
it has a delegate.
And a bunch of shoulds.
Should I allow
creating this file?
Things like that.
The FileManager by the way is
thread safe in the same way
that an NSManagedObjectContext
is thread safe.
In other words, if you create
the FileManager on a certain
thread then it's always thread
safe to use it in that thread,
in that same queue.
If you create a FileManager
on a different one,
that one's safe to
use in its queue and
they will work
together as well.
Just don't try to use
a FileManager created in one
thread over on
a different thread.
That is not thread safe.
It's just like how
NSManagedObjectContext is
thread safe.
That is it for this lecture so
the coming up we have
is accessibility is our
next lecture on Monday and
also your slides are due for
the alternate final there.
Do not forget that.
I put it in red.
How many people,
A few of you, so make sure
you get your slides in.
Wednesday will be
the alternate final itself.
Your final project is due
the Sunday after that,
the Sunday the 19th of March,
at midnight.
That is it.
I will see you all on Monday.
>> For more please visit
us at www.stanford.edu