[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Okay, welcome to Stanford
CS193P, Winter of 2017.
This is Developing
iOS Applications,
this is lecture number 17,
I said.
Yes, and
we have a guest lecturer today
who's gonna talk to us
about accessibility.
His name is Skylar Peterson.
Why don't you come up here,
Skylar?
It's all yours.
Thank you very much.
All righty.
Good afternoon, everybody.
As he said,
my name is Skylar Peterson.
I am a member of
Apple's Accessibility team.
If you don't know exactly
what I mean by that,
then don't worry.
It's what I'm here to
talk to you about today.
I first wanna thank Paul for
inviting us here
to speak today.
Hopefully you'll find what I
have to say meaningful in some
way, and choose to apply it to
your own work in the future.
So before we get started,
let me tell you just
a little bit about myself.
I actually graduated
from Stanford in 2014.
I studied computer science,
and
my concentration was in HCI.
I took this class
while I was here, and
it's actually one of the
reasons that I fell in love
with iOS as a platform and why
I'm in the job I'm in today,
so thank you for that as well.
After I graduated I spent
a year and a half working at
an enterprise software
company called Citrix,
where I worked on two
different iOS applications.
And then a little
over a year ago,
I made the jump to the
Accessibility team at Apple,
where I focus mainly on iOS.
there's a couple things that
I'd like to cover with you.
So for today,
First of all,
what exactly do we mean
when we say accessibility?
And once you understand that,
how do you take the tools that
we've created for you and
apply them to your own work
to make your apps accessible?
So included in that we're
gonna take a look at
the UIAccessibility API.
We're gonna take a look at
several vision accommodations
that you should consider when
designing your applications,
and specifically I'm
going to call out dynamic
type as an important feature.
And at the end I'd like to
discuss some opportunities
available to you as a
developer in the accessibility
space.
So let's get started.
I'd like to begin with
a brief video that
Apple produced towards
the end of last year.
[MUSIC]
People think that having
a disability is a barrier.
[MUSIC].
But that's not
the way I see it.
It.
[MUSIC]
You can catch up with friends.
Ready?
You can capture a moment with
your family.
One face, small face.
Focus log.
[MUSIC]
And you can start the day
bright and early.
[MUSIC]
You can take a trip
to somewhere new.
[MUSIC]
3 miles to the summit.
You can concentrate on
every word of the story.
A bird begun to sing.
Jack opened his eyes.
[MUSIC]
You can take
the long way home.
[MUSIC]
Or edit a film.
Like this one.
[MUSIC].
When technology is
designed for everyone,
[MUSIC]
It lets anyone do what
they love, including me.
[MUSIC]
So the woman narrating and
whom you saw featured
throughout that video is named
Sady, and
she has cerebral palsy.
And she's the principal
editor on that video,
which I think is a powerful
example of the way in which
technology can empower
people with disabilities and
fundamentally change
their lives.
So that is really what
accessibility is all about.
It's making technology
work for everyone,
making it accessible for
everyone.
So let's take a look
at some statistics.
There are 285 million people
worldwide who have some sort
of low vision condition or
who are entirely blind.
There are 360 million who
are hard of hearing or deaf.
One in every 12 men is
colorblind in some way, and 1
in 68 children fall somewhere
on the autism spectrum.
And so what this means is
that worldwide there are over
a billion people that have
a disability of some sort.
Or in other words,
one in seven.
So by no means is
accessibility a small issue.
It affects a lot of people and
if your app has an audience of
any significant size you're
going to have users
that have disabilities.
And you should be doing the
best, your best to make sure
that whatever you're working
on works for everybody.
So at Apple we think of
accessibility in four distinct
groups.
which includes things like
autism, dyslexia, and
other forms of
learning disability.
Physical and motor skills, so
people that have tremors or
Parkinson's and maybe can't
make precise movements
or gestures, but
this also includes people who
are paralyzed or have
a limited set of digits that
they can use to interact
with the system.
For instance a single
finger or a single toe, or
in Sadie's case, her head.
Vision, which covers a
spectrum of vision impairment
from low vision to
completely blind, and
also includes different
forms of color blindness.
And finally we have hearing,
which also like vision exists
on a spectrum from the hard of
hearing to
the completely deaf.
So now our team has developed
a huge set of features on iOS
that assists in all of these
categories, and best of all
they all come baked into
the system from the beginning.
So they're all on all of your
iOS devices that you can turn
on, no add-ons required.
And as much as I'd like to
go feature by feature and
tell you why each of these is
cool, and why it's necessary
and solves the problem,
we don't have all night, so
I'm going to focus
on just a couple.
But I do encourage you to
go and check them out for
You can find accessibility
settings on your device by
yourself.
going to General and
tapping on Accessibility where
you'll find a long list of
all the features that you
can enable on your devices.
What I'd like to do now
though is demo for you,
one of our most popular pieces
of assistive technology which
is called VoiceOver.
It's a screen reader that
allows blind and low vision
users to use a touch screen by
audibly describing elements of
the screen as they pan or
swipe around it.
So without a technology like
this, blind users would be
unable to use the iPhone which
is why it's really important
for you to take advantage of
the API which I'm gonna get
into in a little bit so that
your apps play well with it.
So, I have my device here
on the home screen and
I'm gonna turn VoiceOver on.
And what you're gonna notice
is that it's going to focus on
the first element
of the screen,
which is the Mail app in
the upper left corner.
VoiceOver on.
Mail.
No unread emails.
And it described it to me, and
told me some extra information
about it, for instance,
that I have no unread emails.
So if I wanted to
navigate between items,
if I wanna go item by item,
I can swipe right or left.
Calendar, photos, camera.
And it's going to read to
me the description of each
But if we're on the home
screen which I'm here fairly
item as I go.
frequently, I know my way
around, I can also just feel
my way around the screen
with my finger.
You tapped on Music.
And once I found exactly
what I'm looking for,
a double tap acts like
a single tap would when you
don't have VoiceOver on.
So it's gonna open Music.
Music, this is now
playing screen, button.
Now because music is
a first party application,
Apple engineers have
gone through and
made sure that all of the UI
in that app is accessible.
So VoiceOver interacts
with this interface
exactly the same way that it
would on the home screen,
I could swipe, [SOUND]
Or
find exactly what
I'm looking for.
Now VoiceOver, because it
is intercepting gestures
that are normally used for
other things when
VoiceOver's turned off.
There are analogs for
each different kind of
interaction with the system
that you might need when
VoiceOver is turned on.
So, for instance, with the
track scrubber, if I only want
to scrub through the track,
if I don't have voice over on,
then I'm just gonna run
my finger along it,
like a slider.
But when VoiceOver's
on it's trying to
interpret that gesture as me
trying to find an element.
So instead we have this
adjustable gesture on
items that are adjustable,
I can swipe my finger up and
down to change the value.
8 seconds and 3 minutes.
30 seconds.
So those are just some very,
very basic examples of
how VoiceOver works.
It's much more advanced
than that when you get into
the nitty, nitty gritty of it.
And I highly encourage
you to turn it on and
play around with it and see
what the experience is really
like for a user who's blind.
So where does the information
that an assistive technology
like VoiceOver
uses coming from?
Well it runs in it's own
process on the system, and
it uses the UIAccessibility
protocol to communicate with
other processes, and
ask them information about the
current element on the screen.
So VoiceOver will
receive an input, for
instance a single tap, and
it will get the currently
focused element's description.
It will query the current
process for predefined pieces
of information
about that element.
And from those queries,
it's going to stitch together
a user friendly
description and speak it.
So let's take a look at
the different properties in
the protocol that an assistive
technology is going to
ask about.
The first, and
arguably most important,
is isAccessibilityElement
which tells VoiceOver whether
or not the current thing
should even be visible to it.
And if this is set to no then
obviously it's not going to be
an accessible element and
VoiceOver will not be
able to focus on it.
But in the case of say,
a volume slider,
which I'm going to
use as an example for
all these properties, we're
gonna set this value to true.
Next we have
the accessibilityLabel
which describes
what an element.
So in the case of the Volume
slider, it changes the volume,
so it's going to say Volume.
And then you may wonder
why we don't say something
like Volume Slider.
And this is because
of this next
property accessibilityTraits
which is used to define what
category an element fits into.
So in the case of a slider,
it's an adjustable element,
so we're going to give
it the adjustable trait.
This means that when
VoiceOver describes it,
it's going to say
volume adjustable,
which means that the word
slider is redundant.
And doesn't need to be there.
Accessibility traits
are important in
other ways as well.
So certain traits afford
elements certain behaviors.
For instance, in my demo
where I was showing the track
scrubber, that increment and
decrement gesture is added
because that view has the
adjustable trait set to it.
So, VoiceOver knows that that
view is going to respond
in some way to having its
value increased or decreased.
VoiceOver also has
a mechanism for
navigating a display,
where a user can say
I want to navigate based
on only this kind of item.
So, for instance, if I had
a table view that I wanted to
navigate just by its headers
then I could set this in
VoiceOver, and it's going to
go through and only focus on
elements in the hierarchy
that have the header trait.
So it's important that all
of your views have the right
traits so they behave as
expected to voice over users.
Next we have
accessibility value.
Which you can override if your
view has some sort of state.
So for example, the state for
the volume slider is what
is the current percent
that my volume is set to,
and we're gonna return 50%.
And finally,
we have accessibilityHint.
So this is another optional
property that's meant
to provide a more long-form
description of what something
is or what something does.
This is important often for
VoiceOver users who have never
used your interface before and
are trying to learn their way
around it and figure out
how things work together.
But you should never
put information that is
critical to the user
in this description
because Accessibility
can be turned off.
And therefore a user
may not ever hear them.
Which they might do to
keep VoiceOver from being
too verbose if they're
an experienced user.
So those are the fine five
main accessibility traits.
Without them the interface is
totally unusable to VoiceOver,
and that's the blind and low
vision users who rely on it.
UIKit views define these
properties by default, or
most of them do, which means
that most of the legwork is
already done for you.
But what you really
need to watch out for
is your own custom views,
so let's look at some code.
Let's say that I have
a view controller
that has a property image
view of subclass MyImageView,
which is a subclass
that I've created.
It's just a UIView,
it's not a UIImageView or
anything like that, so
it doesn't have
accessibility by default.
Well in my viewDidLoad method
I'm obviously gonna call
super and
then I could do this.
I could use dot notation to
set each of these different
properties.
I'm gonna say yes my
imageView.isAccessibilityElem-
ent.
I'm gonna give it some
reasonable label and I'm gonna
give it the trait, the image
trait, because I want it to
behave like any other
image would on the system.
Now, I probably want to do
this in a case where these
values depend on
an instance of a view.
But, there may be a case where
the value that is returned
from one of these properties
applies to all
view of that kind.
So, on the subclass
MyImageView,
I could have instead
overridden the getter for
isAccessibilityElement always
return true.
If I know that
MyImageView is never not
going to be an accessibility
element than this is
probably what I want to do.
Or if there's some internal
logic to that class that
determines whether or
not I should determine true or
false from here, this is
a much better way to do that.
And then I can override
the setter to just do nothing
this applies to all
of the properties.
I can override them,
their getters and
setters explicitly.
So, now I'd like to demo
what you've just seen
on a sample app that
I've been working on.
So I'm gonna go back over
here to my device and
I'm gonna turn
VoiceOver back on.
VoiceOver on.
So you see down here I have
this app called Notecards.
[INAUDIBLE] Note note cards.
It's just a basic app that has
stacks of notecards that I
can use to test myself.
And I need to do
an accessibility audit of this
app to see how well it
works with VoiceOver.
So, I'm gonna start by tapping
on the first thing I see,
which is that
collection header.
Collection.
So, as you saw it read
the label collection but
what it didn't say was header.
So I have no idea
that this thing
is actually a label that
is meant to be a header for
all of the content
underneath it.
So that's the first thing I
need to do is add that trait.
Add button.
That button has
a sensible label.
Physics five cards.
That seems right.
Image one button.
That doesn't seem right.
Image two button.
And neither does that so
both of these buttons
are missing accessibility
labels and so
I have actually no
idea what they do.
And it said image one and
two because VoiceOver
by default when it doesn't
have a label on something that
uses an image like a UIButton,
it's going to default to that
image's filename as a last
resort to try and see if it
can get something meaningful
out of what this element is.
So I need to instead add my
own labels to those buttons.
Trivia, nine trivia.
Now if I go in here,
I heard that that had
the header trait.
Add button.
That has a good label.
Close button.
And if I come in here.
The phrase "Let them
eat cake" is commonly
attributed to whom?
Queen Marie Antoinette.
I notice that
these two labels,
even though VoiceOver's
picking them up,
they are picked up as separate
elements and so, I don't
really have any context for
how they work together.
One is the question and
one is the answer.
And it would actually be much
better and give VoiceOver
users much context if I were
to group them together.
That's one element and
say this is the question,
this is the answer.
So they can actually
understand what's happening in
this interface.
So I'm gonna go over to
some code, to my app.
The first thing I wanna take
care of is that header trade
cuz it's pretty easy.
And I have this title
label right here, so
I'm going to say accessibility
traits or equals header.
Now I'm using or equals
instead of just explicitly
equals, because I don't know
what the superclass of title
label, what traits
it is added to
this accessibility element
that it wants to have there.
So I don't wanna override
whatever it set.
I just wanna add my own in.
So that's what
I'm doing there.
Next, let's look at this
cell and the shuffle, and
delete button.
So I need to add
accessibility labels for
these and come here and say
shuffleButton.accessibilityLa-
bel.
Shuffle seems like
a reasonable label to give it.
I'm gonna say delete
button equals delete.
This seems to convey to me
what exactly these buttons
are supposed to do.
And finally, I'm gonna come
to this collection view cell
to have this question and
answer.
What I'm gonna do here
is override these methods or
these properties.
So I'm gonna override this
accessibility element to
always return true on
the cell itself so
that the entire cell has
the accessibility element
instead of each
individual label.
I'm gonna set the label
to return Question,
then the question's text.
Answer, and
then the answer's text.
And I'm going to add
the button trait to it because
that cell is a button where I
can go in and edit the card.
And I need to convey
that to the user.
So let's build this.
Notecards.
[SOUND] Notecards,
collections heading.
So I've got the header trait.
Tab physics shuffle
button delete button.
Both buttons have
the right labels.
Trivia, link trivia, trivia
question: the phrase "Let them
eat cake" is commonly
attributed to whom?
Answer Queen Marie Antoinette.
So, I've got it behaving
exactly as I want it,
just a few simple
lines of code.
That's just a couple examples
of some of the issues that you
might find in your own apps.
So I'm gonna go back,
to my account.
I also would like to
touch on- VoiceOver off.
The idea of containers.
So aside from the attributes.
We also have the accessibility
container protocol.
So let's say that I am
the engineer who has been
tasked with coding this
view in the Calendar app,
it's the year view.
And I've decided that I am
going to design this view so
that each week is its
own custom UIView.
And within that UIView's
drawRect method,
I'm going to explicitly draw
all the days of the week.
Now because those views that
I've drawn aren't standard
UIKit views,
they don't inherit
accessibility by default.
And I don't really have
an easy way of setting
the accessibility
properties on each of them.
But what we'd like for
them to be is visible to
VoiceOver one day at a time.
And so that I can navigate
them day by day and
get a description for
each day at a time,
rather than each
week at a time.
So I need to do is create a
set of accessibility elements
from scratch that overlay
these day views and
return them as sub-elements
of my accessibility, or
of my week view container.
So what does that
look like in code?
Well, I have this
MyWeekView class.
Which I'm going to explicitly
say is not an accessibility
element, because I instead
want VoiceOver to go through
and find the sub-elements
of it that are accessible.
And I'm going to create
an array of elements that
are UIAccessibilityElement.
I'm going to iterate over
the days of the week that
are in that week.
And for each one I'm going
to create an accessibility
element, with the
accessibility container set
as myself, because I'm
the one that contains it.
I'm going to set its
label to be something
sensible for that day.
And now I'm going to
set this property
accessibilityFrameInContainer-
Space.
Now, this is crucial because
it indicates to VoiceOver
where the element is on
the screen, so that when I'm
panning around with my finger
VoiceOver knows where it is.
So if my finger is over it,
it can describe it to me and
see that I'm trying to
focus on that element.
It's also what VoiceOver uses
to draw the bounding box.
And in case you couldn't
tell this frame should be in
the coordinate space
of its container.
So once I do that, I'll pan
the element to my array of
accessibility elements, and
then, I will set the property
on MyWeekView accessibility
elements to be those elements.
And what this says is these
are all my accessible
sub-elements and
VoiceOver should navigate them
in the order that I returned
them in this array.
So, let's take a look at
adding that to my sample app.
Let me go back over here.
And turn the VoiceOver
back on.
VoiceOver on now.
So you may have wondered
what this shuffle
button actually does.
Well, it shuffles the cards in
the deck and puts them up so
I can test them.
Shuffle trivia heading.
And what I have down here,
this little circle view
is just a little UI to
indicate to me how far
I am through the deck.
So if I go to the next card
for instance- Next question.
It's increasing because
I'm filling out the circle
with how many cards I've done.
However if I stay
to swipe to it.
Next question,
from next question.
I hear a bonk and
try to run my finger I'm
also hearing a bonk.
So what that indicates is
that when I swiped and
did it it means there's
nothing left on the screen for
VoiceOver to swipe to you've
hit the last element.
And when I'm running my finger
over it means that there's
nothing below my finger that
is an accessible element.
But we'd really like that to
be accessible to VoiceOver
users, so they can track their
progress through this stack.
And so we're gonna use
accessibility elements
to accomplish this.
So I'm gonna come
back over to my code.
I'm gonna go to this
ShuffleStatusView,
which is where I've done
the drawing of this circle.
I'm gonna copy and paste.
So, what I've done
here is I've created
an AccessibilityElement with
myself as the container.
I set its label to be card,
whatever the current card
number is,
of the total amount of cards.
I've set its
accessibilityFrame
to be the frame of the circle.
And in my
AccessibilityElements because
the previous and
next button are also
part of the StatusView,
I don't want them to be
left out from VoiceOver.
So I'm gonna also
include those in my
AccessibilityElements along
with the new element that
I've just created.
So let's see if that worked.
NoteCards, NoteCards, collect,
shuffle button, shuffle,
trivia, previous question.
I've got my previous button.
Next question, problem,
part one of nine.
So now it's become accessible.
And pretty easy,
not too many lines of code.
We can go back.
So I'd like to change
gears for a minute, and
talk a little bit about some
visual accommodations that you
should be aware of when
you're designing your app.
So the first thing is color.
Color is a useful means of
differentiating information,
but if it's the sole
differentiator
then users who are colorblind
won't be able to fully
understand the user interface.
So, take for
example this view in Mail.
Our designers wanted
the unread and
flagged messages to be
differentiated apart from each
other with circle views that
are of a particular color.
But to a colorblind user, they
can't tell the difference.
So what we did, is we added
a setting in Mail so that you
can change flag messages
to use shape and color.
And what this does is it uses
both color and shape to convey
meaning so that no user
has to be left out.
So, if you're writing
an app that uses color to
convey meaning,
then you should consider
doing something similar.
Now color can also be too
bright, distracting, and
contrast and transparency and
blurring can all have negative
impacts on legibility for
people that have certain
vision conditions.
This is the default
control center on iOS and
as you can see color bleeds
through from behind and
is blurred by the control
center's background.
But if I turn on
the darken colors and
reduce transparency setting,
we no longer get those colors
bleeding through from behind.
And the contrast
between the colors and
the lighter background
is much more stark,
which means that it's a lot
more readable to those users
that have those
vision conditions.
So you can check whether
things like these are enabled
through these two
UIKit functions.
And this way, you can adapt
your interface to the needs
of your users rather than
having to try and create
some design that, from the get
go, applies to everybody.
Now for this next one, I'm
going to say that anybody in
the room who gets motion sick
from phone animation should
probably look away for
a second.
Device is gonna
show these standard
app opening animation.
So you can see that
when I tap on music,
the app expands from its
place on the dock, and
the screen swoops
in to center on it.
But if I turn on
the reduce motion setting,
I instead get this cross fade.
So there are certain people
with vestibular disorders
that can be triggered by
complex motion which most
often results in things
like nausea and dizziness.
So you should be mindful of
any animations in your app,
particularly if they cause
a lot of movement or
are unexpected in some way.
You should consider
enabling an alternative
animation when this setting is
enabled which you can check
through a similar
UIKit function.
Now the final visual
accommodation that I'd like
to talk about today
relates to typography, and
it's dynamic type which is
a feature in iOS that allows
a user to scale their font.
And I believe you touched
on it very briefly.
There are many users out there
who struggle to use devices
because the type is so small,
or so thin that it ends up
blurring together, and
they can't read it.
And this applies to people
with low vision conditions,
but it also applies to people
whose vision is simply
deteriorated from age, or
people who simply
need to wear glasses.
So, Dynamic Type is meant
to help adapt these
people's devices
to their needs.
Now on the left you see the
standard Mail inbox interface
with the default text.
And on the right I've scaled
it up several levels.
And as you can see,
the interface has adapted
itself and the layout as well
to accommodate
the larger text size.
The most common way that
you're gonna get this behavior
is by using this method
preferredFont(forTextStyle.
which is a class
method on UIFont.
When you set the font
of a UILabel or
UITextView, using this method,
the font will be scaled to
the user's preference
using the system font.
And what you do is you pass
through a TextStyle, which
indicates what the general
purpose of the text is.
So titles are large and
body is a more standard size.
There are these eight distinct
styles that you can pass this
method and each of them have
pre-defined point sizes and
weight sizes to them.
So, let's look at some
code where I used that.
So let's say I have
MyLabelView which is
a custom UIView, and
it has a sub label or
a sub view that is
of class UILabel.
Now in my init method,
I'm going to init that label.
Now, I'm gonna set its
number of lines to be 0.
And what this indicates to the
UILabel, is that it doesn't
need to be limited to any
specific number of lines.
It can actually grow to
an unbounded number of lines.
Which is important when I'm
growing the text size because
as I get bigger and bigger,
it's likelier, it's more and
more likely that I'm not
gonna be able to fit whatever
text I have on a single line.
Now I also need to set
adjustsFontForContentSizeCate-
gory to be true, and what this
does is it tells the label
that when the user has
changed their font size and
my app is opened in the
background, I need to update.
The label needs to update
itself to match whatever
the new font that I've
changed my size to is.
And then I am going to
use that preferredFont
forTextStyle.
Probably just gonna use body,
because it's standard in this
case and then add my subview.
Now, what do you do in
the case where you wanna use
a custom point size when
you're at the default
text size?
Or you even wanna use
a custom font but
you still wanna
support dynamic type.
I did this in my
own sample app,
it uses the
boldSystemFontOfSize method,
which is not going to
automatically be scaled to
the user's preference.
So, what I'm gonna do is I'm
going to take advantage of
this property on UIApplication
preferredContestSizeCategory.
And what this tells me,
is what the user has
currently set their font to.
Now there are seven distinct
size categories at default.
The large size is
the default size on iOS.
But there are also five more
accessibility sizes and
located in accessibility
settings that can make
the text really, really big.
So what would my code for
something like this look like?
Well, I'd probably create
some sort of NSObject like
MyFontManager, that will be
an object that will manage all
the fonts for my app so that I
can run everything through it.
And then I'd have some
method like this,
where I'd use a fontSize
variable and write a switch
statement that changes the
value of the fontSize based
on what my sizeCategory is set
to, to some sensible value.
I mean to do that for
every case.
And then I'm gonna use
whatever the method
I was going to use before,
like systemFont(ofSize: or
my custom font or
boldSystemFont(ofSize:
using whatever size I
determined was appropriate for
the current size class.
Now it's also important that I
register myself to listen for
the
UIContentSizeCategoryDidChange
notification.
Because I'm no longer using
that preferred font for
text style method so all my
views aren't gonna know that
they need to update themselves
when the font size changes.
So I'm gonna register myself
as an observer on this
notification and just write
a method that updates
my fonts in some sort
of sensible way.
So let's move for
the final time to my demo app,
and see what it's like
with dynamic type.
Now for this, I'm actually
gonna exit full screen.
And I'm going to bring up
this tool in Xcode called
the Accessibility Inspector.
Now this is a super useful
tool that I don't really have
time to go in to today
about how you can use it.
But, it's an app that's built
into Xcode that allows you to
audit your own application for
all of its
accessibility problems.
And there's a great video from
last year's WWDC that you can
find on the developer
website to go through exactly
how you used this app,
which I will have a link to at
the end of the presentation.
But for now, I'm going to
attach to my phone and
simply use it to change
the font size dynamically so
that you can see what happens
on the screen, what I do.
So I'm gonna come to
my stack of cards, and
I can see that the number of
lines is already set to zero
because this label is growing
based on how much text I
have there as I want it to.
But we're gonna see,
is as I change this value
here with the slider,
my text isn't updating at all,
the content size.
So something is wrong.
So I'm gonna come over
here to MyFontManager.
And I'm gonna go look at
my appFont method and
I see the problem immediately.
I'm not adapting myself to
what the preferred contentSize
is and I'm not using
the preferred font for
text style method.
So I'm gonna replace that,
With this,
which takes this size and,
based on some multiplier
that I decided looks good.
I'm going to modify
what the font size is,
based on the SizeCategory.
And I'm going to
return that using my
boldSystemFont(ofSize:.
Now, like I said,
I also need to register for
that notification, so
that my view actually
updates itself in real time.
So we're gonna
go to that cell.
And I'm going to add
myself as an observer,
not to put that there.
And in my
contentSizeCategoryChange
method, I'm just going to
update the fonts here.
And that should work,
hopefully, so let's rebuild.
So I'm gonna come
back over here.
I'm gonna open this and
I'm gonna bring up my
Accessibility Inspector again.
And now as I change the size
you see that it's growing
bigger, and bigger,
until it's real, real big.
And everything works exactly
as I was expecting it to.
And, not a huge change.
So, I've covered several
ways that you as a develop,
developer can make your app
more accessible to people.
This can actually be a great
way to get your app featured
on the store.
So we have sections that
are devoted specifically to
general purpose applications.
That we think we've done
a good job with
their accessibility.
For instance,
this collection of apps that
are good to use
with VoiceOver.
Beyond making your
own app accessible,
there's also a whole set
of apps that are aimed at
accessible users specifically.
So, I'd like to run through
a few of those examples with
you today.
We have knfbReader,
which is an app that scans
text in real time, and let's
users who are low vision or
blind interact with
things like paper or
a restaurant menu,
so they can read it.
We have an app like Ava, which
transcribes conversations in
real time, so that a user
who's hard of hearing or
even deaf, can follow
a conversation easier.
And this includes a feature
that actually breaks
conversation down,
differentiating the different
speakers by color so
I can tell who is speaking.
And finally we have this app,
Children with Autism,
which is a visual scheduler
built specifically for
children with autism.
And allows them to be
more independent and
understand what
they need to do,
during their day as they
are going along, task by task.
So these are just
a couple of examples.
And you may wonder, why am
I telling you about this?
Well, basically, if you're
looking for a possible idea
for a class of what you
might want to work on.
Or the next great thing that
you think you wanna work on,
I encourage you to check out
some of the work that's being
done in accessibility because
there are a lot of problems
that still aren't solved, and
that are worthwhile to tackle.
Now, I've covered
a lot today and
there's more that you
can find on the web.
These are a couple of links to
some resources that you might
find useful, including some of
the things that I spoke about
during the presentation today.
I would encourage you to check
out some of these WWDC videos,
In particular,
including the one on
inclusive app design,
which is a whole session
on design, focused on
both accessibility as well
as internationalization.
And that auditing your
apps for accessibility,
which goes through how to take
advantage of the accessibility
inspector to make your
own apps accessible.
So, in closing,
I'd like to circle back
to the why of it all.
Why should you take the time
to do something like this?
Let me read you this quote
from Sady, the woman who,
from the video that I
showed at the beginning.
My love for technology is
more than just a passion.
It gives me access
to my world.
I need help in some areas,
but assistive technology
enables me to communicate
with my loved ones, and
pursue my career.
What everybody else can
do with a keyboard and
a mouse,
I can do with my two switches.
The common person's life
is enhanced by technology.
But for somebody like Sady,
technology is transformative.
It can make them independent
in ways that really couldn't
have been imagined
ten years ago.
It can allow them to do jobs
that they couldn't have done,
have hobbies that they
couldn't have had, or
experience the world in ways
that they couldn't have.
So by taking the time and
putting in the effort to make
sure that the work you do
works for everyone, you can
have a lasting, meaningful
impact on people's lives.
I promise you that you'll
never find a more loyal
customer than the one whose
life you made better.
Now I know that some of you
may be thinking that that's
great and all, but
there are some things that
really just don't work
with accessibility.
And I challenge you
to think different.
If you'd asked somebody 15
years ago how a blind person
could use a touch screen,
they probably would have
told you that they couldn't.
And that's not true today.
Anything is really possible
when you put your mind to it.
So this is a video of my
colleague Ryan DJing at last
year's WWDC.
Where we awarded
the app djay Pro for
their work on accessibility.
He DJed live on stage using
the app with VoiceOver and
I'd like to play this
brief clip for you now.
I have an iPad Pro
running djay Pro and
this external mixer.
I'm gonna go ahead and
throw on my headphones now.
So, here's the things that's
interesting, the external DJ
controller acts as an
extension of the onscreen UI.
And so I can use it to really
create kind of a pretty
cool performance.
Also you're probably wondering
what of this can I see.
Not much.
I pretty can see the light
coming from the screen and
some of the colorful lights
coming from the DJ controller,
but that's about it.
So knowing that,
we're gonna use VoiceOver
to control this interface.
Let's go ahead and
get the music started.
Play Okay, so the first thing
I'd like to point out is that
I have access to information
I've never had before.
For example, the time.
How much time is
left on this track?
Let's find out.
Time deck one, 2:56.
That's perfect.
Okay, so I'm the DJ.
I'm supposed to keep
the music going, and
now I have that kind
of information.
I also can use these
tempo sliders.
For example if I touch it
right now, hold on a second.
tempo deck one 0% adjustable.
So we hear it's at its
standard playback speed, but
if I slow it down using
the DJ controller and
I touch it again.
Tempo deck one,
-7.1%, adjustable.
We can hear exactly how far
I've slown that track down,
that's really cool.
I also can use these
multi-dimensional effect pads
for example if I touch it
the first time Effects pad,
deck one.
But the second time.
Really cool stuff, right.
So between these effects pads,
this external controller, and
all this accessible UI.
I can do a pretty
cool performance.
So I'd like to go ahead and
ask the stage crew to please
take VoiceOver off
of the PA systems.
So that it's only available
to me in my headphones.
Play deck one.
Cool, thank you very much.
And I'm gonna mix for you now.
Here we go.
[MUSIC]
[APPLAUSE]
So because of the effort
that their team put in, people
with vision impairments,
like Ryan, can DJ just
as well as anybody else.
It's something that he loves
to do, and it's only possible
because somebody at that
company decided that it was
worth it.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
For more,
please visit us
at standford.edu