[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
Developing Applications for
iOS, winter of 2017.
This is Lecture number 7, and
today we're going to talk
a little bit more about Swift.
And once we do that,
we can introduce some
technology that we need
to do more sophisticated
UIKit objects like,
scroll views can be our first
examples of that today's web
demo at the end where we show
you how to use scroll view.
First thing I wanna talk about
in Swift is error handling. So
far, we have not called
any methods that
can generate an error, or what
we call throwing an error. And
we can always tell these
methods though really clearly
in any API.
Because when they're declared,
they'll have the word
throws after it. And
throws means that somewhere in
the processing of this method,
it's possible, but not
guaranteed, that it will throw
an error. So when it
throws that error at us,
we have to catch the error.
And the way we catch it is,
well, first of all,
every time we call a method
that can throw an error, we
have to use the word try. So
we have to try that method
because it might fail.
So that's why we use
the word try. But
if we wanna catch
the error that comes back,
we actually have to do that
little try inside what's
called a do construct.
So we have to say do{, and
then some code that has some
tries in it. And then} catch,
then let error is going to
allow us to grab the thrown
error into a variable,
in this case called error.
We could say,
let any variable name we want.
That's gonna be the variable
that has the error in it.
And then in that curly brace,
we handle the error. And
then after we've handled it,
our code continues. So
we caught the error, we deal
with it, we keep going.
It did, if we want to, and
if our function throws,
we could re-throw the error by
using the keyword throw there,
in our second, little curly
brace space. Now this error
that gets thrown to you, it
does have to be of a certain
type. The type is called
error. It's a protocol,
which I'm gonna talk about
later in this lecture, but
it's a pretty
simple little type.
And in UIKit, when UIKit
methods throw an error,
they throw an error of
this type NSError. So
you can go take a look in the
documentation for NSError and
see what an NSError is. It has
an error code, it has an error
domain, like where
the error occurred. And it,
even has some things like a
description of what happened,
why it failed,
things like that.
Now, sometimes we call
a function that throws,
and we know for sure it's
not going to fail. This is
rare that we know this, but
if we're certain about it,
we can use another version of
try, which is try! And just
like exclamation point means
to force it in an optional,
exclamation point here means
to force it essentially.
And if we call
context.save() right here,
whatever that function is,
if we call it and it throws,
our app will crash, okay.
That's what the try!
means. It means try, I know
this is not going to throw.
If it does, crash my app.
There's yet
another try though,
which is try?. Try?
means try to call this
method that throws, and
if it does throw,
just give me back nil.
Well, for
that to work of course,
the variable that we're
assigning the result of this
method, I called this one,
errorProneFunctionThatReturns-
AnInt. Whatever that returns,
it's now gonna return
an optional version of that.
So error prone function
that returns an int,
returns an int obviously.
But x,
this let x =, that x is
gonna be an optional int for
obvious reasons because if
error prone function return
an int throws, it has to throw
nil back at us, okay? So
that's what try? is. Try?
is give it a try, if it fails,
just give me back nil. If I
do this try, I don't get to
look at the error.
I don't know what it is.
I'm ignoring the error here.
I know there was an error, but
that's all I know in the try?
case. So it's a very simple
error mechanism that
works quite well.
In Swift they really learned
the lessons of some other
languages that have more
overwrought, over complicated
throwing of errors that are
throwing up call stacks and
all these things, Swift
is very straight forward,
sees the entirety of the error
processing, all right?
Now, another completely
different topic, extensions.
So, an extension allows you
to add a method or a var,
even, to another class or
structure enum, that you may
not even have the code to,
okay, it's called extension
because it extends that class.
So, here's a concrete example,
I hope you understand why
we might use an extension.
Remember when we did
our app last time and
we went to our Storyboard and
we wrapped the detail of
the split view in
a navigation controller and
it broke our code.
Right, it broke our code and
prepare for segue because
that code was looking for
a Face View controller and it
found a navigation controller
instead. And the way we fix
that is we just look to see if
it was navigation controller
first. And if it was, we look
at the visible view controller
of the navigation controller,
now we have our Face View
controller back again. Now,
we could put that code into an
extension of UIViewController
by creating a new var,
you can see it right here
called contentViewController,
we can call the new var
anything we want, I like
contentViewController cuz
if it's a navigation
controller, it's the content.
If it's not a navigation
controller, it's just self.
It's the view
controller itself.
It's its own content.
And so I can add this, so
I'm adding this var actually
to UIViewController. So now
UIViewController understands
this var, it has this new var.
Now I didn't subclass
UIViewController to do it,
I just extended
UIViewController. So
you UIViewController and all
subclasses of UIViewController
will now have this var. And it
makes that code that we had in
prepare, which looks
something like this,
the green part is
the same in both places.
It changes that code
with all that to
just this simple line of code.
The segue's destination,
contentViewController as my
MVC. I think that slide says
destinationViewController-
that should be
segue.destination.contentView-
Controller there. So,
it just cleans up our code and
prepare for segue. But
the extension that we
have UIViewControllers,
purely a UIViewController
thing.
It has nothing to do with our
emotions view controller,
anything like that. We purely
extended UIViewController to
have new functionality. Now,
extensions inside their code,
they can refer to self.
And when they refer to self,
they mean the class they're
in. And so in this case,
the self means
the UIViewController that
is executing this var
which makes sense,
right? There's some
restrictions though with these
extensions. So extensions
are not a substitute for
everything object oriented
like subclassing and
things like that. One thing is
that you can't re-implement
something that already is in
there. So, you can't override
or subclass with extensions.
You can only add new things
that aren't there. And in
fact, if UIViewController were
to have implemented this
var contentViewController,
its version would win-
the extension with not win.
In fact, it might even get
an error when you try to add
an extension to
something already there.
So its not our replacing or
overriding or
anything like that, it's for
adding new things. And a huge
restriction to extensions is
they cannot have any storage.
The only vars an extension can
have have to be computed vars.
They can't have any
stored vars, okay,
extensions have no storage.
They are purely for
adding code, all right. Now,
this feature of extensions is
easily abused especially
by beginners to Swift.
They start saying, cool,
I'll just add this code and
extension here,
I'll add new code and
an extension there and
I'll add it over there.
And you start getting this
kind of messy situation where
the extensions don't
really make sense for
the class you added them to.
So I'm gonna suggest that you
be kind of go slow and
steady with the extensions.
Don't use them too much. Now
having said that, extensions
can be super powerful for
architecting your code well.
Okay, especially when I start
talking about protocols.
They can be a fundamental
aspect of building
like a functional programming
approach to building your app.
But I don't have time to
teach all that to you. So
you're only gonna know enough
about extensions
to get yourself in
a little bit of trouble. So be
careful with extensions, okay?
Use them lightly. But
in the future when you start
a becoming serious iOS
developer someday you're gonna
wanna learn how and
you can use extensions to your
advantage without abusing
them, all right? Next topic,
protocols, super,
duper important topic here.
How many people have
encountered protocols in
other languages? Nobody, see?
Well, one or two people.
So it surprises me a little
bit, but, protocols,
while very simple, are also
incredibly powerful. So,
a protocol is a way
to declare a type
that really just means these
methods and vars with no
implementation generally.
That's what a protocol is.
A protocol, as you'll see, is
a type. But you're essentially
just defining a few methods.
Or even some vars,
that are part of this
protocol. Then we're gonna use
the protocol, as you'll see,
to define our APIs better.
It allows you to create an API
that lets the callers pass
anything they want- any class,
or struct, or enum even,
they want to this API that you
create. But it allows you,
who's receiving it,
to ensure that that class, or
enum, or struct,
implements certain methods or
vars that you need. So
that's what this is all about.
It's about API design.
We want to build API so
we can express in our API
exactly what we want and
no more. Okay, just the
methods and vars we need to do
whatever this function is
going to do or whatever, and
not extra stuff. So, a
protocol is just a collection
of method and
property declarations.
That's what a protocol is.
But a protocol is a type. It's
a full fledged type. It serves
any place you can use a type,
like a float. You can use
a type that's a protocol.
Protocols are first-class
types. Absolutely first-class
types. The implementation of
the methods and vars under
protocol, since a protocol is
just the declaration of them,
where does the implementation
happen? Well, mostly
it happens in classes and
structs and enum that claim to
implement that protocol, or
conform to that protocol,
we say. So if I'm a struct,
and I wanna say yes,
I wanna conform to protocol x,
then I have to implement
all the methods in vars that
are in protocol x, right?
Cuz protocol x is just
a declaration of them,
it's not an implementation.
Now,
you can also do implementation
on a protocol in an extension,
but I'm going to put that
on the shelf for second and
talk about that in
a few more slides. But
primarily protocols,
implementation happens in
conforming or
implementing classes,
structs and enums. Now,
the three parts to a protocol.
One is the declaration
of the protocol.
That's really simple. It looks
just like declaring a class,
a struct or an enum.
But there's no implementation,
okay. The second part is
the class or structure or
enum that claims to
conform to that protocol.
That claims that it
implements that protocol. And
then of course there's the
actual code that that class,
struct, or enum, that claims
to implement the protocol,
actually does implement
the protocol. So that's it,
those are the three part
of using a protocol.
Both the declaration and
then the implementation. Now,
I'm gonna talk about
a feature with protocols,
called optional methods.
This is not optional,
like the optional type.
This is different optional.
It means that the methods in
the protocol, are optional,
you don't have to
implement them, and
you can still say that you
implement this protocol.
Now this is an Objective-C
thing. This is not a really
a Swift thing. In swift when
you have a protocol and
it has a bunch of methods
in it, if you're struct or
class and you wanna say you
implemented that protocol,
you have to implement
all of them,
all right. In Objective-C
though that's not true,
in Objective-C some of the
methods might be optional and
in which case you can claim
to implement the protocol and
not implement those. So, if we
have a protocol that has these
optional things in it,
it has to be marked objc.
So you put this little @objc
before the word protocol, and
that says this is
an Objective-C protocol. And
then inside the declaration
you can put the word
"optional" in front of any
funcs or var that you want to
make optional. So this is
going to be used for something
called delegation which I'm
gonna talk about in a few
slides which is an Objective-C
thing that is brought forward.
Because it's in UIKit so
extensively it's brought
forward into Swift using
this @objc protocol, okay?
But back to protocols in
general. So let's take a look
at what a protocol
looks like to declare.
So here's the declaration of a
protocol called SomeProtocol.
And you can see it looks
just like declaring a class,
a struct, or an enum, right.
You got the keyword which is
protocol instead of class,
struct, or enum.
Then you got the name.
Now after that though there's
a colon, and other protocols.
These protocols are called
inherited protocols.
Some protocol inherits
these two protocols. And
what it means is that anyone
who wants to say yeah,
I implement some protocol,
they have to
implement those too.
Okay, they're doing all
three of these protocols.
Some protocol, and
its two inherited protocols.
So protocols essentially have
multiple inheritance. How many
people know what multiple
inheritance is in object
oriented? So only a few of
you. So multiple inheritance
just means like you could
have two super classes, or
three super classes.
Some languages support that.
Swift does not. But
Swift does support multiple
protocols that you can
inherit from, okay?
Now, the protocol inside,
you can have properties and
you can have funcs. And
if you have a var, a property,
you have to say whether
it's a get set property or
there's just get only and you
do that in a curly brace get
set. Curly brace get.
So you have to put that curly
brace something in there that
says whether you're gonna be
a get set var or whether
you're just a get-only var.
Any function that the protocol
expects would mutate the thing
implementing it, like if
a struct were implementing it,
you have to mark it mutating.
Now if a class were to
implement this protocol,
it wouldn't matter,
classes don't have to
mark themselves mutating.
And in fact it's even
possible to say,
I want this protocol only to
be implemented by classes.
And you do that by putting
the word class right after
the colon. See the yellow
class right there SomeProtocol
: class- that means this
SomeProtocol can only be
implemented by
reference types. And
in that case you don't have to
put any mutatin's in there.
But if you are gonna
allow your protocol to
be implemented by an enum,
or especially by a struct,
obviously you're gonna have
to put mutating in there.
You can also specify in
a protocol initializers.
You're basically saying,
anyone who wants to implement
this SomeProtocol has to be be
able to be initialized with
these arguments, all right?
If you do that, by the way,
and you're a class,
okay, then you have to mark
the initializer required. I'll
show you that in a second. All
right, so how does a class or
a struct or an enum say yes,
I implement SomeProtocol?
It does it this way. A class,
right after its superclass,
just puts a comma and
the protocols'll do this.
And you can implement any
number of protocols there.
So this class called
SomeClass has a SuperClass,
it's called SuperClass of some
class, and it also implements
two protocols, SomeProtocol
and AnotherProtocol.
Now inside of SomeClass'
implementations it must
implement all the methods and
vars in those two protocols
unless it's an Objective-C
protocol and they're marked
optional. Okay, the methods
in there are marked optional.
That's the only exception to
that. All right. Structs or
enums. Exactly the same, it's
just they have no superclass.
So here's an enum saying,
that it implements those two
protocols, okay? And here
is a struct saying that it
implements those
two protocols. Now,
you can have any number of
protocols implemented. And
as I said, inits have to be
required. The reason that
these inits have to be
required here is that,
what if a subclass, subclass
is SomeClass right there, and
it does all the initial
exation games such as,
this is no longer
a good intializer.
Because maybe this
was required.
You need an initializer,
you need an override, so
now you have your own new
designated initializer,
et cetera. Well, that would be
bad, because that would mean
the subclass of SomeClass
would no longer conform to
that protocol, and
that is not allowed.
If a class conforms to
a protocol, like SomeProtocol,
all of its subclasses have
to continue to do that. And
they'll inherit that from the
superclass except for init,
are the one thing that can be
uninherited by the rules of
init. Okay? One thing that's
very interesting is that you
are allowed to add protocol
conformance to a struct,
a class, or an enum using an
extension. As long as you can
do it without any storage. You
can do it in the extension.
You just say, extension
Something, where Something is
the class, struct or enum,
colon, SomeProtocol.
And that saying, I'm creating
extension to that class,
struct or enum that
implements this protocol.
And then inside
that extension,
you have to implement all the
methods of the protocol. Okay,
understand what I'm
saying there? Let's
talk about protocols being
types. What do I mean when I
say a protocol is a type?
So, I got an example here.
I've got a protocol
called Moveable and
it just has one function in
it, a mutating function called
move to point. Now, I have
two data structures here.
One is a class called Car,
and it's Moveable.
Okay, the Car is Moveable, but
the Car also has other methods
like changeOil. You change
the oil of the car. And
similarly I have this
struct called Shape.
It also implements Moveabl.
Look, see, mutating func
move to point. It actually
implements that. But it also
has a function called draw.
Because it is a shape and
it can be drawn on screen.
All right, so all
two of these classes implement
this protocol move to.
Do you see that? So do you see
that they're all moveable?
Okay, a car is moveable.
A shape is moveable.
That's how we would describe
those. So I created two little
vars down here. A Prius,
which is of car of course,
it equals a new car.
And then I created a square,
which is a shape, of course.
So I've got a Prius and
a square here. Let's see what
we can do with the Prius and
the square. First, I can
create a var whose type is
Moveable called thingToMove
and I can assign it to Prius.
Because a Prius is moveable.
So if I have a var that
is of type moveable, of course
a Prius can be put in there.
Everyone understand that? And
I can even say, thingToMove,
move to this point, because
thingToMove is a Moveable.
So, if it's a Moveable, it has
to implement move to point. So
I can say that. However,
I cannot say, thingToMove,
change oil. This is the
critical thing to understand,
okay? Even though I put
a Prius in thingToMove,
that var is not a Car,
it's a Moveable.
And moveables don't know how
to change the oil. Cars do.
But moveables don't. So what
matters is the type when it
comes to sending the messages,
not what's actually in there.
Everyone understand that? Now,
of course, I could also say
thingToMove = square. That's
perfectly legal as well. Okay,
square is not even a class,
it's a struct. Okay,
it's not a car, it's a shape.
But they're both moveable so
that var thingToMove which
is of type Moveable can hold
either of those things.
In fact, I can even create
an array, thingsToMove, which
is an array of Moveable and
then I can put a Prius and
a square both in there,
even though they're
completely different classes,
types of things.
They can both go in there
cuz they're both moveables.
So, the type of thing in
that array is Moveable.
What it actually is,
doesn't matter. Okay,
everyone cool with that?
All right, I could also have
a function that takes
a Moveable as an argument,
like slide that takes a slider
which is a Moveable, and
I can say, slider move to that
position because the argument,
slider, is a Moveable so
we can say move too. And
I could say slide a Prius,
slide a square.
It works perfectly fine. By
the way you can have arguments
to functions that require
multiple protocols.
For example I could have
a function, slip and
slide which has a parameter
x which is both Moveable,
and another protocol,
which I haven't showed here,
called Slippery. And that's
what the ampersand means.
It means both of
these protocols. So
that inside slipAndSlide, I
could send x Moveable things,
like move to, and I could
also send it Slippery things,
whatever those are. Note that
I can't say slipAndSlide
Prius, because Prius does not
implement slippery, okay?
Prius does not conform to the
Slippery protocol so cannot
pass in there, Swift would
not even let me call that.
Okay, everyone understand what
I mean now by a protocol as
a type? It's just a type, and
anything that conforms to that
type can be stored in
something, or passed through
in something of that type. Now
I'm gonna take a couple slides
here and talk about the
advanced use of protocols. I'm
not gonna ask you to do that
in the nine or ten weeks we
have here because it is kinda
advanced use. But I think it's
important that you understand
that this exists because all
of Swift's standard library,
arrays and dictionaries,
all that stuff, is all
implemented using protocols.
So, one thing that a protocol
can do that I'm not gonna ask
you to do, is that it
can restrict the type
of a generic. Everyone knows
what a generic is, right?
An array of angle bracket t.
It means the array can hold
any type in there. But that t,
that array of t could be
restricted to things that
implement a certain protocol.
So here's an example,
which is range. When I showed
you range, a few lectures ago.
I said it was sort
of Range. Okay,
the reason it was only sort
of Range was because
actually range bound or T
bound is just a variable name
basically for that type,
colon comparable.
Okay, so a range can only be a
range of things that implement
the protocol Comparable.
Luckily ints implement
Comparable. Floats implement
Comparable. Characters and
strings implement Comparable,
etc. So these things all
implement Comparable so
you can have a range of ints,
a range of floats,
whatever. Now,
why does range want the thing
in its range to be comparable?
Well it's because it wants to
make sure that its lower bound
is always less than
its upper bound.
I think on the other slide,
I said it was start index and
end index. Which is actually
not range, the range struct,
that's countable range, and
those kind of things have
that. You rarely use
just a straight range.
You're almost always using
the countable range,
or closed countable range, or
one of those. But anyway, so
that's why it wants the type
that it can be generic for
to be Comparable. So
being able to restrict this
generic types by some protocol
is really super powerful.
Okay, because it allows you to
build much a more wide variety
of generic data structures.
Because you can make it so
that they have to implement
certain things to work.
All right. Now,
also, you can use
generics to declare protocols.
So you can have protocols,
where the methods in vars
might be a generic type. So,
now you can have these
protocols kind of meta.
But you can have these
protocols that can be
describing behavior that
can work on generic types.
Or maybe work on generic
types that implement certain
protocols. Now, this is
probably hard for you to
imagine where this could go,
but it really can go.
Okay, so you're really opening
up a lot of power here
by adding generics. And
constraining these generics
using protocols.
Again remember that you kind
of get multiple inheritance
with protocols. And I'm
going to show you an example
here with CountableRange.
So CountableRange is the type
of struct you get if you use
3..<5. Remember I showed you
that. Like if you're doing a 4
in and you want to come
forward to 5 non inclusive,
use three dot dot five you
get this countable range.
Well, le's think what
CountableRange is.
CountableRange is a struct
that implements a ton
of protocols.
Here's some of the interesting
ones it implements.
IndexableBase which gives it
start start index and end
index which I showed you on
that slide kind of erroneously
as Range, it also implements
this method index
after. So, a range can move
forward cuz you can always
find the next index.
And it also does subscripting,
so you can take a range and
get subscript sub three, and
it will get you the fourth
one in there. Right,
so that protocol's called
IndexableBase. Then there's
another protocol called
Indexable. Which actually
inherits from IndexableBase
which has index offsetBy.
So now you can move through
the range more than just to
the next one,
you can move farther ahead.
There's also
BidirectionalIndexable.
Now you can go backwards,
index before, okay. So
these things like startIndex,
index after, index offset,
index before, these are just
methods in these protocols.
It also implements this very
important protocol called
Sequence. And the main method
in Sequence is makeIterator.
Which gives back an object
that can do the for in thing.
So a Range, that's why
Range works with for in,
because it implements
the Sequence protocol. And
it also implements
the Collection protocol.
But Collection is primarily
just an indexable sequence.
So it implements both those
protocols- things that
are collections implement
both those protocols.
So why does Apple go
to all the trouble
to take something simple
like a CountableRange and
make it implement all of
these ridiculous protocols?
Well, here's why. Because
Array also implements all
those protocols and so
there's Dictionary and Set and
String.UTF16View. The thing
that will let you see Unicode
characters in the string. All
of these things do. So they're
all sharing the same basic API
description of their behavior.
Even though they're
quite different.
An array is quite different
from a range. A set
is different than an array.
And certainly a, character,
UTF16View, is different
than any of those things.
They're dictionaries. So these
are all different things.
But they share the behavior
of being indexable,
being a sequence of things,
being collections of things,
they share all that behavior.
And so that's described with
these protocols and wait,
there's more. Because of
this thing I told you that
extensions can be used to
add code to a protocol,
okay. Now there's restriction
there, of course, because both
protocols and extensions
can have no storage.
So if you extend
a protocol and
give it some actual
implementation,
by implementing some of
the methods in the protocol.
You can only use other
methods in the protocol. Or
methods you inherit
from other protocols,
right?
You can't use any storage.
All you can do is call
other methods and vars. But
you'd be surprised how much
you can do when you do that.
And what that
allows you to do,
in this case, if you consider
Sequence. I told you that
Sequence mostly just makes
you that makeIterator thing.
So, you can for in through
the string characters or
through the array or through
the range or whatever. Well,
if you just implement that one
method, Apple has provided
an extension to the Sequence
protocol. That implements two
dozen other methods that are
based on being able to iterate
through. Like contains, is
this thing contained in this
Sequence? Or joined by
separator, which will take
each thing in the sequence,
turn it into a string, and
join it by whatever separator
you say, like a comma, and
give you back a string.
Okay? Or min and max.
What's the minimum thing,
or the maximum thing?
Of course in that case,
the sequence would have
to have what, comparable
items? You have to be able to
compare them. If you're gonna
do min or max. Even those
cool functions I told you,
filter and map, remember
those? That took a closure and
you were able to map an array
from one thing to another.
You can do the same
thing with a range. And
that code is not in Array.
It's in this extension of
Sequence. Okay, so
now you're actually inheriting
true implementation,
true functionality. And
you're multiply inheriting it,
okay? And
you're doing it in
a generic way so
that the code works on arrays,
string characters, etc.,
equally. Okay, so hopefully,
that's given you some feel for
like whoa, what you could do
if you had these protocols?
If you've designed your
API using protocols.
And then, you could add code
like this using extensions.
You can hopefully see, and use
generics especially, you could
see how you could reuse a lot
of code. Now this approach, I
actually mentioned it before.
This approach of focusing on
the behavior of things
rather than on the storage.
Is leading to a methodology
called functional programming.
And again, I can't teach
you that unfortunately, but
I want you to know it exists.
And maybe you can take
a course here where you
can learn about it.
If you go out to the outside
world, self-teach
yourself if you have to. It's
very powerful mechanism for
programming.
And the protocols and
generics play right into this.
Because protocols and generics
are all about the behavior
of things, not about their
storage. Okay, all right.
That's all I can unfortunately
have time to say about
the functional programming and
protocols. And
now let's back way up off of
advanced protocols and
start talking about a couple
of simple uses of protocols.
Here's a simple protocol that
you could use right now in
your calculator. It's called
CustomStringConvertible.
And it only has one thing in
the protocol which is a var.
It's a get-only var called
description. Looks familiar?
Which is a string. And if
you implement this protocol,
then when you print,
if you do the backslash,
parenthesis thing and put your
thing inside. It will call
this description to get the
description of it. So right
now, if you said, print quote
\ ( your CalculatorBrain,
in your view controller, ), it
would probably print out some
hexadecimal number and the
word CalculatorBrain, which is
useless. But if you put colon
CustomStringConvertible after
your struct CalculatorBrain,
now, when you print it out,
it'll print out the
description. In other words,
the equation, right, because
you implement description
already. I intentionally chose
the name description there
so that you would implement
CustomStringConvertible
automatically. But you have to
also say that you implement
it. You can't just
implement description and
expect it to work. You have
to say, yes, and I implement
CustomStringConvertible by
putting that on there.
So give that a try.
Go get your calculator and
put this colon
CustomStringConvertible. And
then, in your view controller
somewhere, print out your
CalculatorBrain with\().
See what you get, all right?
Another really simple use of
protocols is delegation, okay?
And it's really where we've
all been leading up to here,
in terms of a use case of
protocols. This is not gonna
use any of the other stuff I
was talking about, generics or
extensions, none of that,
okay?
This is just the simplest
possible use of protocols,
although it does use
Objective-C protocols
because a lot of optional
methods in these protocols.
But this is how we're
gonna implement this MVC
thing we talked about,
which is blind, structured
communication. The delegate
and the data source, remember
that from lecture 2? This is
how we're gonna implement it,
we're gonna implement this
with protocols. So here's how
it plays out, to use protocols
to do that delegation. First,
UIView thing, okay, like
a ScrollView, for example,
or a TableView, which we'll
talk about next week.
It declares a protocol,
which has all the will and
should and did methods
I was talking about.
So I will scroll to here, or
should I allow scrolling in
this direction? Those kind
of methods, it implements
a protocol that just has
those methods listed in it.
It's gonna be
an Objective-C protocol,
they're almost all gonna be
optional, all right? So it
just declares that protocol.
Then the view adds public API
to itself, which is a weak
property called delegate or
sometimes data source. And
that type is that protocol,
okay? So anything can be
assigned to that var,
as long as it implements that
protocol. The view uses this
delegate property in
itself to get the answer,
should I scroll here, and to
tell people, I just did scroll
here, okay? It sends those
messages to the delegate,
because the delegate
implements, optionally,
the methods in that protocol
so we can send it to them.
If it has no delegate,
if the delegate is nil,
because this weak delegate
property, since it's weak,
it has to be an optional. All
weak properties are optional.
So it could be nil.
And if it's nil,
then the ScrollView's just
not gonna talk to a delegate.
It's just not gonna ask it any
questions or tell it anything.
Now, the controller declares
that it implements that
protocol.
That's what it has to say.
It has to say at the top, you
know, if view, class UI view,
class calculator view
controller, whatever,
UIViewController comma
UIScrollViewDelegate. So
it says, I implement that.
Then the controller sets
itself as the delegate of the
view, which will be legal now
because the controller claims
to implement that protocol.
So it can now be put
in a var of type
that protocol. And finally,
the controller implements
whatever methods it wants.
Since they're probably mostly
optional, it can just pick and
choose which ones it wants to.
And those did and should
methods will now start being
sent to it by the ScrollView
or whatever, okay?
So now the view's hooked
up to the controller.
The view has no idea who he's
talking to. All it knows about
this delegate is that it
implements those should and
did things.
That's all it knows,
so it's a completely generic
and reusable view still.
But it can communicate with
the controller. This mechanism
of delegation, you find
it all throughout iOS.
Any complicated iOS object is
gonna use delegation when it
needs to talk back
to its controller
in a complicated way.
This was all designed, though,
pre-Swift and pre-closures,
things like that.
A lot of times, a closure
might be a better solution
than delegation. So,
delegation- a little bit of,
what do you call it,
backwards compatibility thing.
But you still gotta know it
well if you're gonna do iOS,
because it's just everywhere
in iOS. By the way,
do not use delegation in your
homework assignment three.
I think I might even have
made it a required task.
You can't do it,
do not use delegation. I never
teach you anything after
the assignment's already,
you know, started.
Delegation's not for
assignment three. All right,
so let's take a quick look at
what this looks like code-wise
for ScrollView. First,
ScrollView's going to have
a var called delegate.
It's gonna be of type
UIScrollViewDelegate optional
because it's weak. The
protocol UIScrollViewDelegate
looks like this. It's got
these optional functions,
like scrollViewDidScroll and
give me the viewForZooming
in the ScrollView,
etc. Then the controller is
gonna say, yeah, I implement
UIScrollViewDelegate by doing
the little or purple or
blue or whatever code that is.
And in viewDidLoad, the view
controller's gonna say,
ScrollView's delegate is me.
So ScrollView, please send
me all those messages. And
then it would just implement
whichever methods it wants.
And we'll see this in the demo
I'm gonna do today as well.
All right, so
that's it for delegation.
Let's move on now to the first
class that uses delegation,
it's ScrollView. Before I
talk about ScrollView,
I wanna show you a little
bit how ScrollView works,
this ancient video I have.
This is like, I don't know,
iPhone 1 or something. But
if you look at the way
it's scrolling,
it actually is very
sophisticated.
It can have a horizontally
scrolling thing,
like the stock charts, and
inside of it, have vertically
scrolling ScrollView.
So that's ScrollViews
inside ScrollViews, okay?
And ScrollView's smart enough
to know whether you're swiping
sideways or vertically to make
it scroll. Now let's talk
about how you put something in
a ScrollView so you can scroll
around in it. But you do it
by adding subviews to it. So
let's review how we add
subviews to a normal view. So
I create a view, like a logo
view. And I set its frame,
which is where it's gonna
be in its superview.
And then I just add it to its
superview. So here, I'm saying
view.addSubview(logo) view is
probably the top-level view
in my view controller. Or we
know that there's a var called
view for that. So
a ScrollView is similar. But
before you're doing all that,
you're doing a very important
step, which is to set the
contentSize of the scrollView.
So this is a var contentSize.
It's a CGSize.
And it's gonna be how big
a space you're going to be
scrolling over. So you've
gotta set that first. It's
very important to set that
first. But then, after that,
you just addSubview,
just like you did before.
So here, I added the, this
logo view at 2700 across and
50 down. And that's it,
so now the ScrollView is
going to scroll around.
Here, I added another one.
Let's add two views, okay,
we got two views in there. And
now the ScrollView is just
going to scroll around
on this content area. You see,
it's just scrolling around.
In fact, you'll even see
the white of the content area
while you're scrolling around
to do that. Now, of course,
you can reposition the views.
Let's put this big
aerial view up in the corner.
And
then let's put the Stanford
logo so that it overlaps it.
And then we can always change
our contentSize any time
we want to not have any
extra space, right,
and contain the whole thing.
So if we do that, then,
when we're scrolling around,
we're not seeing
the white background there. So
that's how ScrollView works,
couldn't be simpler. It's
all about that content size.
If you forget to set
the content size,
scroll view will not work. If
you remember nothing else from
this lecture, remember that.
Once it's scrolling around,
you can find out information
about where it is.
You can find out
the upper left corner for
example of where the scroll
view is. Using scrollView's
contentOffset point,
it'll tell you the x and
y of the upper left corner of
where the thing is. You could
also just say, where is the
rectangle that is currently
showing the scrollView, where
is that showing in the view
behind that like aerial view
of Stanford? But to do that,
don't forget that those are
different coordinate systems.
They're different views so
they have different
coordinate systems.
So you have to convert,
all right.
You're gonna convert the
scrollView's bounds, right,
the scrollView's bounds,
that's in the scrollView's
coordinate system. You're
gonna convert that to the
coordinate system of the view
like aerial. See, I'm doing
aerial.convert up there,
converting that rectangle.
Now why are those rectangles
not the same?
Well, a lot of reasons.
One, you're panning around so
it's always changing.
Two, you might be zoomed, so
it might be quite different.
If you're zoomed in on that
scrollView than that little
rectangle might represent
a huge piece of aerial or it
might represent a tiny, little
piece of aerial. Who knows.
So you're gonna use this
method we already saw.
We saw it when we were
doing the drawing example.
I converted center from my
super view down to my view
here. I'm just converting the
bound to the scrollView. From
the scrollView to whatever
view there that I'm interested
in. All right. Now,
how do we create one of these
things? Very straightforward.
We drag it out of the
utilities area in storyboard.
It's just a view so you can
do UIView, scrollView frame
if you want, but 99% of
the time we're pulling it out.
You can also pick a view
that's already in your
storyboard and go up to Embed
and say Embed In -> Scroll
View. And it'll put it inside
the scrollView. Okay, so
that's another way to do that.
Then you just add whatever
your too big view is. The view
you wanna scroll around in.
You just add it as a sub
view of the scrollView. But
of course, you're not gonna
forget to set the contentSize.
Okay? And that's it, it's
really quite simple to use.
And you can scroll around
in there programmatically,
obviously, the user's
gonna have their touch.
And they can just pan around,
but you can do it too by
saying scrollRectToVisible,
and it'll take a rectangle and
make it
hopefully entirely fit on
screen. It'll do the minimum
amount of scrolling necessary
to get that rectangle,
on screen. You can do a lot of
other things in scrollView,
I don't have time to talk
about like controlling
that behavior where it
only scrolls vertically or
horizontally and it'll kind of
on first motion it'll figure
out which one you mean and
do that. You can flash
the scroll indicators when
the thing appears on screen.
You can also offset the actual
content that you're scrolling
over by a little bit.
This happens a lot in
navigation controllers.
Sometimes the bar at the top,
which is semi-opaque, or
semi-transparent, is not
transparent enough for
the application of the,
whatever you're looking at in
your scroll view. So
you'll offset it a little bit,
the content you'll offset by
that height of the, navigation
draw. So there's a whole bunch
of stuff in there I can't
really talk about. Another
big piece of this is zooming.
So, we've talked about panning
around in the scroll view but
you can also use your
pinching to zoom in and
out. So zooming in and
out, the way that works,
all UIViews have a property
called their transform.
It's an affine transform which
means it has translate, scale,
and rotate. And
when you pinch on a view,
all it's doing is affecting
the scale of its transform,
does nothing else.
Now that for most views, for
all views, that's going
to scale the bits up. So
if you zoomed in really big,
you'd have really big pixels.
It would look really grainy.
But if the view wants to,
it can make it look really
good after the zooming is
done, for example, UIImageView
does that. If you're zooming
in on a UI image and its got
more bits of resolution, it'll
show them to you as you zoom
in, and you could do that, for
example, with your calculator.
If you had your calculator in
a scroll view,
which you're not going to.
But if you did, if you had the
graph part of it, you could,
when it pinched in, when it
was done pinching, you could
re-draw the graph to give it
nice smooth curves, right, so
it wouldn't be all pixelated.
All right,
I'll show you how to do
that in the next slide. So,
two things about zooming in
a scroll view though that you
have to know. One is you
have to set the minimum and
maximum zoom scale. So that's
how far you'll zoom in, and
how far you're allowed
to zoom out. And
by default these are 1.0 and
1.0, meaning no zooming in and
no zooming out. So you have
to set these to something. So
if you set the minimum
zoom scale to 0.5,
means you'll zoom down
to half its normal size.
And if you set the maximum
zoom scale to 2.0 it means
you're gonna zoom out to twice
its normal size. All right, so
you can decide how much you
want to let your users zoom in
and out. The other piece is
you need a delegate method.
Zooming does not work
without delegation. And so
you have to implement this
delegate method called
viewForZooming(in scrollView)
and all you have to do is
return the view that's
in the scroll view,
one of the subviews, the one
that you're going to zoom on.
And this is the one whose
transform transformed.
Of course you can zoom
programmatically as well.
It's not just
pinching to zoom.
You can set the zoom scale.
Here's some examples on how to
do that. So here I set my zoom
scale to 1.2, now I'm gonna
set it to 1.0. See it
goes back to normal size.
1.2 I'm zoomed in 20% okay or
same thing with rect. If I put
a little rectangle right there
and I say zoom to that rect
it's gonna zoom that rect
out as big as it can be.
Or if I had a rectangle
that was bigger and
I said zoom to rect it
will zoom it down so
the rectangle fits. Okay
it's going to do the minimum
zooming to get that
rectangle on screen.
There's lot of of other
delegate methods,
at least a dozen more besides
that view for zooming and
scrollView. For example,
if you wanted to do the thing
where you zoomed in and
then you wanted to re-draw
to get rid of the pixelation,
you would implement
scrollViewDidEndZooming with
view atScale. And
this will tell you when
the pinching has stopped and
now you can re-draw.
Of course if you re-draw by
the way at the new scale,
you're gonna reset
your transform,
the view's transform,
back to the identity
transform. Otherwise, you'll
both drawing it scaled and it
will be scaled because you're
affine transform is well
pixelated too. So, you don't
want both of those things
going on at the same time.
So you reset, you would
reset your transform here.
Okay, so the rest of this
is going to be demo, so
let me just talk about
what's coming up here.
The demo I'm gonna do is
a Scroll View Demo, obviously.
I'm gonna show you
how to do that,
I'll show you some other
things too, like extensions,
things like that.
On Friday we have
Instruments. Okay, performance
testing. Really important if
you want to do the extra
credit in Assignment 3,
which is a good one,
you have to figure out
why your calculator,
graphing thing doesn't perform
as well as you'd like.
On Monday, Assignment 3,
what you're working on now,
your graphing calculator
is due, before lecture. And
then the topic on Monday is
going to be multi-threading.
We're gonna take the demo
we're doing today,
which is going to
be very sluggish,
and we're going to make it
perform a lot better using
multi-threading. On Wednesday,
we're going to go into
TableView, really important
part of the UIKit.
There will be an assignment, a
TableView assignment that goes
out on Wednesday. It'll be
due the next Wednesday. And
there's no more reading
assignments. I can tell from
talking to some of you that
you didn't read any of
them very closely. And you
know, I don't quiz you on it,
I don't test you on it because
it's kind of up to you how
much you wanna learn
in this class.
It's just one of those things
where whatever you put into
it is what you get out of it.
But
I really encourage you to at
least go through the parts
in there that you
don't understand, and
be cognizant of the fact, I
don't really understand this.
Okay, because then when you
graduate from this class,
which is, you know, you're
getting started with iOS in
this class. When you graduate
from it you'll know,
okay that's something
I gotta go back and
really understand better.
All right, okay so
this demo is going to be,
again, fresh start.
So I'm gonna create a new
Xcode project in single view
application.
I'm gonna call it Cassini,
cuz we're gonna do some stuff
with the images that came out
back from Cassini probe
that went off to Saturn.
And I'm gonna put it in the
same place I put all my maps,
home directory Developer.
And here it is I'm gonna move
xcassets and the AppDelegate
and the LaunchScreen out
of the way again. I'm actually
not going to move info.plist
out though. We are going to
be looking at that today. So
we're gonna put these
in Supporting Files.
Now, I showed you last
time how we can rename
a ViewController, if it's got
like a generic name like this.
You know, another thing
we could do to this
ViewController, is just delete
it. So I'm just gonna go here,
right click on it, and delete
it. And remove all references
to it and I'm gonna go to my
storyboard right here, which
still has this ViewController.
And by the way, if I go look
at the identity inspector
here for that ViewController.
It's still trying to be
class ViewController,
even though I deleted that
from my app, all right.
But I'm gonna fix that by
just deleting that from my
storyboard. All right, so now
no ViewController anywhere.
Now, I do need a view
controller for my app and
it's gonna be called
ImageViewController.
It's going to be a generic,
reusable MVC for showing
an image. Whenever I build an
MVC, I always wanna see if I
can build a nice generic
reusable one because then
maybe I can use it in some
other app that I'm building.
And also it gives me
the discipline as an API
designer to think about my
public and private API even.
So, let's go ahead and do
that, let's create a new file.
Coco Touch Class of course,
and we'll call it
ImageViewController, it's a
subclass of UIViewController.
Okay, very carefully here,
I do not wanna put this at the
top level. I wanna put it down
in here where the rest of
my files are. All right so
I got my ImageViewController
here. I don't need for
now anyway, any of the
ViewController lifecycle. I'm
also not going to segue from
this MVC. So I don't need any
of that. I actually I'm going
to be segueing to it however,
because it's a nice reusable
image showing things.
So as you can imagine I might
want to be segueing to it any
time I want to show an image.
When I have a new class like
this one the first things I
like to do is think about what
is my model? Because the model
is what this MVC does?
So if I can determine what
the model is, it'll help me
think clearly about what
this MVC is all about.
And so this shows an image, so
I'm gonna have my model,
I'm gonna have it be public so
other people can set my model,
and I'm going to have it be
a URL of an image.
Because what does my MVC does?
It shows an image. That's what
it is, an image shower. So,
it seems like having a URL of
an image would be a good model
for it. Now, let's go back
to our storyboard here and
create an MVC for this thing.
So I'm just gonna grab
a View Controller. Drag it
out here. Gonna go up to
the identity inspector, again,
and I'm gonna set it to be
an ImageViewController,
right? Now,
I could start building my UI
here by dragging more things
in, but I thought it might be
valuable a little bit, to show
you how to build some UI in
code. It's gonna be simple,
but we'll build some UI in
code. And what my UI here is
gonna be at the beginning is
just an ImageViewController or
a UIImageView, right? I'm just
going to show an image using
UIImageView, this class
UIImageView. By the way,
one thing that's missing here,
you can tell by this warning.
Let's click on this warning
and see what it says.
It says ImageViewController
is unreachable.
Remember that? There's no way
to get to this. That's because
there is no arrow that
goes into this anywhere.
If I were to run this app,
it would crash and
say, there's no initial
View Controller. So,
how do you set the initial
View Controller? Well,
you pick the View Controller
you want to be the initial one
and you go over here to the
Attributes Inspector because
it's an attribute of that
View Controller. And down here
under View Controller right
after its title is, is Initial
View Controller. So, I click
that and look what happened.
You got the little
entry arrow there. So
now when this thing run, it's
gonna jump right into this
View Controller. Which is
where we wanted to start.
Eventually we're gonna
have other MVCs, but
we'll start with this one.
All right,
back to my ImageViewController
here. I said I wanted to
build its UI in code.
I know I need ImageView so
I'm just gonna start right off
with private var imageView:
is a UIImageView.
And in fact, I'm gonna
create it right here. There's
no reason not just to say,
this, it's going to create it
with basically CGRect zero.
This is just like saying
frame: CGRect.zero,
it's exactly the same as doing
that, but you know we don't
need that extra code there.
So now I've created this image
view, it's in the upper left
hand corner of whatever its
super view is, it's not in
any super view yet, and
it's of zero zero size.
So it's not that useful, but
of course, as soon as I set an
image in it, I will resize it
to fit that image. And
speaking of setting an image
in it, I imagine that when I
set an image in my imageView,
I'm gonna need to do things
like change the the frame,
of my imageView, and
things like that.
So I'm gonna create
a little private var here,
called image, which is
gonna be a UIImage and
it's gonna be computed and
it's gonna have a get and
a set so that every time
I get or set the image,
I can do other stuff.
Okay, this is a really kind of
simple clean way to keep, you
know to do ancillary things
when you're settings and
getting some piece of data.
So, for example, when I
set this image right here,
I'm going to set the
imageView's image to be equal
to that new value of course.
That's the primary thing if I
wanna set my image, I need
to set it in my imageView.
So this var right here is just
the image that this imageView
is showing. But
then also like I said,
I want to set my imageView's
size to fit this new image.
In fact, there happens to be
a method called sizeToFit in
imageView that will cause
it to size its frame to
fit whatever image
is inside of it.
So it's nice that it had
that this nice method for
me right here. If I control
click on it, you can read it.
See that's what it says.
And then how about getting it?
Well, I'm just gonna return
the imageView's image in
this case. Okay, so this
is a var and it's computed,
so there's no storage. And
actually I'm doing the storage
here in the imageView. Now,
this is giving me an error
right here. And the error it's
giving me is that I need
to unwrap this. Well,
that's because this image
right here is an optional.
Cuz imageViews don't
have to have an image,
they could be
empty at the time.
Now I could unwrap this here,
but I'm thinking,
you know what? I want my UI to
be able to be showing no image
at some point. That's
perfectly reasonable. So
instead, I'm gonna change
this to be optional. So this
image var is optional, it can
be nil. And when I do that I
wanna make sure that I can say
imageView.image = newValue,
is that gonna work if newValue
is nil? Yes, it is because
we know that this imageView's
image is itself an optional.
The imageView might have
no image at this time.
It's perfectly fine. Okay,
everybody cool, understand
what I did there? It's just
a code organization thing,
it just keeps me from
having to, you know,
be resizing this fit somewhere
else. Or to be putting
in some other part of my code
that makes no sense. Here it
makes sense because here's
where I'm setting my image.
All right, let's now
put this imageView into
our view hierarchy in code.
I told you we were gonna do
our UI with code. Let's do it.
We're gonna say viewDidLoad is
a good place to do this
because we know that by
the time viewDidLoad happens,
we're fully initialized.
All our outlets are set.
We've been prepared if
someone's segueing to us.
We're in a really good state
right now to add more things
to our UI. And I'm gonna do
that just by saying view,
remember that the special bar
in View Controller which is
the top level view.
AddSubview my imageView,
okay? So
I'm just putting it on there.
It'll either be zero zero size
or if someone set my imageURL,
then it might be sized
to fit or whatever.
Okay, now what happens if
someone sets my imageURL?
I better set this image, okay?
And we know a good way to do
that, right? So our property
observer here on our model,
any time someone sets our
model. First I'm gonna
actually clear out whatever
image I have. And then I'm
gonna put the fetching of
an image in another method.
Remember that this imageURL
might be an Internet URL and
this might be a slow Internet,
this might take a long time.
So I'm gonna put it all off
into this other function here,
private function, fetchImage.
And it's gonna do
the image fetching. So
how do we fetch an image
from a URL, all right?
It's actually remarkably easy.
First, I'm gonna make sure
that I have a URL to fetch.
I'm gonna say, if I can let
a url equal our imageURL,
that's our model, okay? If I
can get my imageURL there,
then I'm going to let the
contents of that URL, so I'm
gonna go out in the Internet
and get the contents of it.
I'm gonna let that equal
Data(contentsOf: url).
So data is that bag of bits,
thing I told you about
a few lectures ago. And it
has a really cool initializer
which is load up your bag of
bits with whatever's at this
URL on the Internet. Now, this
has an error right here. And
the error is that this throws,
because that URL might not
point to something, or
it might be a malformed URL,
or it might be a URL to some,
you know, bad data or
something like that.
So, if I look at this error
here, it's complaining about
the immutable. But it's also
saying this call can throw,
but is not marked
with a try and
the error is not handled. Now
here, someone's asking me to
show this imageURL. I suppose
I could catch that error and
like put up an alert saying,
here was the reason I couldn't
show your, display your image.
But I'm just going to instead
use try, with a question mark,
and if I can't get it, then I
just won't show it. Which is
probably not that great but
it's good enough for a demo.
So now as soon as I put try
question mark here, this is no
longer going to be of type
data. It's gonna be what type?
Yeah, it's optional. See, it's
an optional data because if it
throws, it can come back nil.
All right, since this is
optional, I'm gonna say if I
can let the imageData equal to
the contents of that URL.
Then, now I can create
the UIImage with that and sure
enough my image which is this
var right here is gonna be
equal to UIImage. And image,
we all know about Image named,
but there's also Image,
with the imageData. So if you
have the actual JPEG data or
whatever, you can make
an image out of that.
And of course, when I do
image = UIImage here,
it's gonna go down
here to this setter.
It's gonna set that image
in the UIImageView.
Which we added as a subView
and then it's gonna size to
fit that imageView and
show it to us, all right?
Okay, now, there's only
one problem with this,
one thing I don't like about
this. Which is well, let's do
one other thing too. I'm gonna
go to viewDidLoad here and
have it do a demo URL,
so we can see.
I'm gonna set my own
imageURL equal to and
I have these demo URLs here.
Okay, it's this little thing
right here. Copy that in.
These demo URLs have a for
example, a little
Stanford URL right here and
also some NASA ones which
we'll be doing next time.
But I'm just gonna use this
Stanford URL right here. So
our imageURL is
DemoURL.stanford.
What I don't like about the
way we've written this code
though is here in viewDidLoad,
I'm setting my imageURL to
stanford.
That's gonna go up here and
cause this fetchImage
to immediately happen.
Which is gonna go out in the
Internet and grab this image.
So as soon
viewDidLoad happens,
man, I'm not on the Internet
getting that thing. And
that's probably not something
you wanna do, why wouldn't
you. Imagine this MVC which is
supposed to be reusable was in
a tab bar, okay. All of the
MVCs that are in the tab bar,
they're all created in
viewDidLoaded even before
any of them are shown. So, if
I had a tab bar that had five
image view controllers right
here, they'd all be off on
the Internet loading things.
I might not click on any of
them. And
I wasted the cellular data
plan of my user, all right.
So I really only wanna go
fetch this URL when this
view controller is going to
appear on screen for sure. So
can anyone think of where I
would put that instead of in
viewDidLoad there? Different
view controller lifecycle
method.
How about viewWillAppear?
Super.viewWillAppear. So
I'm going to do the actual
fetching in viewWillAppear.
Now, I wanna do this, no?
Okay, there's another problem
though. What if I'm
already onscreen and
someone sets my image? Then I
can't do it in viewWillAppear.
I've gotta do it right away.
So I can kind of
really just want to delay
doing it to viewWillAppear
if I'm not on screen already.
So what I'm gonna do up here
with my imageURL up here
is I'm just gonna check and
see if I'm currently on
screen and if I am, so
I'm gonna say if my
view.window is not nil,
then I'm gonna go fetch this
image right away, okay. So
view, remember that's the var
that's the top level thing.
Window is a var that is in
all UI views which tells
you the window it's in. And
if you don't have a window,
it means you're not on screen.
If you do have a window,
you are on screen. So
if my view.window is not nil,
then I'm on screen.
I'm gonna go ahead and fetch.
Otherwise I'm not gonna fetch.
And instead down here in
viewWillAppear, I'm gonna
say if my image is nil. So
if I don't have an image yet
so far, then go fetch it. So
you see how the combination of
these two things is going to
wait to fetch it until view
will appear. Unless I'm
already on screen, then it'll
fetch it right away. So
that's at least delaying it.
So now if I were in tab bars,
when I clicked on the tab,
viewWillAppear would happen
and I would load up. And
if I did something that caused
the image to change, it would
change right away, cuz I'd be
visible. If I went offscreen,
then clicked on another tab,
my image was changed,
it wouldn't change.
When I click on it,
then it would go get
it from the Internet.
So, I'm minimizing the amount
of data plan usage
if the person's going,
doing it over cell.
Okay, so, I think we got
everything we need here to
make this work. Let's try
running, let's go on an iPhone
7. Hopefully our network works
on this laptop here. Okay, so,
it comes up here, and it's not
showing. Where is our image?
We don't have any image. Well,
I think I see something in
the console down here. Let's
see what that says. It says,
App Transport Security has
blocked a cleartext HTTP,
hm. It's insecure, of course,
we know HTTP is insecure,
HTTPS is secure. It says,
temporary exceptions can be
configured via your app's
Info.plist file. Luckily,
I didn't move my Info.plist
into Supporting Files,
cuz I knew this was gonna
happen, obviously. So
what's going on here?
Well, if you look at the URL
that we're trying to load,
this Stanford URL,
see it's an insecure HTTP URL.
And by default, iOS does
not let you load those up.
You have to say that you're
willing to load those up
untrusted URLs and you do
that with this Info.plist.
So what is an Info.plist? It's
really just a list of some
settings, some configurations.
For example, it shows, will
you run in portrait mode? Will
you run in landscape left?
In landscape right?
Those kinds of things.
It's really kind of runtime
configuration, how your app
will run. So we can add
this App Transport Security
that we need right here
by right-clicking, okay,
we right-click. Pay attention
here, cuz you're gonna need to
do this probably, in a, maybe
in a future homework. But
we're gonna right-click and
pick Add Row.
So that's gonna add a row.
Oops, we don't wanna add
a row there, sorry. That added
a row to our support interface
configuration.
>> So
we wanna be not selecting
that, and do Add Row. And
if you go look in Add Row,
right near the top is App
transport security settings.
You see it right there? So
I'm gonna click on that then
I'm gonna open the security
settings. Don't forget to
open those settings and
then hit plus which will
add a security setting and
here you can see the options.
And
we want the one which is
allow arbitrary loads.
We'll allow any HTTP URL to be
loaded and we're gonna go over
here and say that that is yes.
So allows arbitrary loads,
yes, okay? So we just add
this to our Info.plist,
now when we run our app, we've
given permission, essentially,
for the app to load
these http non-S URLs.
Okay, there we go,
look at that, woo hoo!
We got Stanford, and
we can even rotate.
Good, now of course we can't
see the whole image here and
we can't zoom in. It would be
nice to be able to zoom in.
For that we obviously
need a scroll view. So
how are we going to put
a scroll view in here? Well,
this is a good opportunity
to show you mixing code for
doing your views in code, with
doing it in the storyboard.
So I'm gonna put my Scroll
View in the storyboard, and
we'll leave the image view in
code. Okay, so you see them
both working together. So
to put a Scroll View here in
my storyboard,
I'm going to just search for
Scroll View down here in the
utilities window, there it is.
I'm gonna drag out
a scroll view, here it is.
I'm gonna use the blue lines
to put it in the whole,
filling my whole, MVC here,
without even any borders.
Then I'm gonna use this
little reset to suggested
constraints, you
remember that?
To have it do the auto
layout for me.
Then I'm actually gonna go
up to the size inspector,
right here, and click on it
to double-check what it did,
in terms of constraints.
And sure enough,
it's done exactly the
constraints I want, all right?
So we have this. We wanna
talk to the scroll view,
of course we need an outlet
to it. So, let's get our
controller on screen at
the same time here and let's
control drag. I'm gonna put it
to scroll view down here by
the image view. So let's
control drag right into our
code right there. It's
an outlet, get to scroll view,
notice it's weak.
We talked about why our
outlets are weak. I'm gonna
call this outlet scrollView.
Cuz that's what it is. Var
scrollView right there. Now,
I want to integrate the image
view into the scroll view,
so I'm just going to,
when the scroll view gets set,
I'm just gonna add that
image view as a sub view.
Okay, and now I don't need
to do that in viewDidLoad.
Where is viewDidLoad?
Okay, don't need to do adding
the image view as
a sub view of our top
level view because now I'm
adding it as a sub view of
the scroll view, all right?
Make sense? So,
let's see if that just works.
That should just work.
Yeah, it's good. You should
all be thinking about,
hm, why wouldn't that work?
I'm gonna ask you why it's not
working in a second. All
right, here it is! It looks
like it works. Let's scroll,
we can't scroll around. Why?
I know I put a scroll view in
there. How come the scroll
view's not scrolling? Anyone
have an idea? Okay, the,
he's saying
the the two variables,
the zooming things.
Well, that's true.
That's why it won't zoom,
but it won't even pan.
Why won't it even pan around,
let alone zoom?
>> Content size.
>> Content size, exactly.
We haven't set
the content size.
So, this scroll view actually
is panning around the content
size, it's just that the
content size is zero-zero. So,
when you are trying
to pan around,
it's like you're not even over
that zero, zero spot, and
it's impossible to be over it.
So, we want the content size
to be encompassing this
whole image here so
we can pan around with it,
so let's do that.
Now, where do we want to
set our content size?
There's actually two times
that we wanna do it.
For sure when our scroll view
is first hooked up here,
we're gonna wanna set
our content size.
So I'm gonna say the
contentSize here equals and
what is our contentSize
gonna be equal too? Well,
it's our image view's
frame size, okay?
We want to enclose our
entire image view.
So, whatever the size
of our imageView is,
that's what we the content
size of our scrollView to be.
But there's another time we're
gonna wanna sent the content
size, which is if our
image changes, right?
If you put a new image in
there, then we're gonna have
to adjust our content
size to make a change.
And luckily, woo hoo, we have
this nice var down here,
so that every time we set
our image, we can do things.
And sure enough, right here,
I'm just gonna say,
scrollView.contentsize equals
the imageView.frame.size.
Now, this might seem good.
But actually this is very bad.
And the reason for that is
that. If we're in image
view controller, and
we're getting prepared.
Someone's going to
set our image url.
That's how they're gonna
prepare us right? So
let's follow what that's gonna
do. So imageURL is going to
set the image to nil,
down here. Set this image,
to nil, and it's gonna try to
execute this line of code,
and that is gonna crash.
Because when we're preparing,
our outlets are not set so
this is nil. So the way around
that? Question mark. This
optional chain. If it's nil,
I won't be setting the
contentSize of the scrollView,
but that's okay cuz later,
I'll come along and
do it here when the outlet
does get hooked up. So,
this is just to remind you
that any time you're accessing
outlets and methods that might
be called during prepare, you
need to optionally chain them,
okay? So it doesn't crash
your app during prepare. All
right, so let's go ahead and
see if that fixed everything,
set our content size here.
Should be good to go.
All right,
here's our image, and look at
that, scrolls nicely, rotate,
okay, scroll. Okay, and notice
it has a kinda this little
thing where you scroll too
far and it bounces back.
You can control that, by the
way, and scrollView's one of
its settings, all right? Oops,
wrong rotation there, okay,
we got it? Now, of course, now
we'd like to zoom in. We wanna
look and see if we can find
any of ourselves down here.
Maybe that's one of us right
there. We're gonna zoom in and
see. But for zooming,
as he was saying up above,
we need to make sure we set
the minimum and maximum
zoom scale. Cuz actually
zoom scale are set right now,
they're set to 1.0. So
that's minimum and max, it
means no scrolling. All right,
so let's set that. A good
place to set that is probably
when our scroll view is first
hooked up as an outlet.
So we'll just do this here,
we'll say,
scrollView.minimumZoomScale.
Let's go really small,
how bout 0.03, okay,
3% of the size will go,
make allow our image
to be really small.
And maximum, just to show you
the difference, we'll make it
only, so we can only be twice
as big. Or, or we can even
make it so it can't be bigger,
right? 1.0 would be,
it can never be any
bigger than it is.
It could be smaller, but not
bigger. Which we might want,
because if it's allowed to be
bigger than its natural size,
it's gonna start
getting pixellated and
we don't want that. But just
so you can see it happening.
And what's the other thing we
need to make zooming work? No
one remember?
We need delegation. Yes,
the scroll view needs to
know which of its subviews
you want to have
the transform change. And
it does that by asking you to
delegate. So now we're gonna
get to see delegates
in action right here.
So to make a delegate work,
you need to set the delegates
to be yourself.
So I need to say,
scrollView.delegate = self.
Now, this is not legal,
and this is going to generate
an error. And hopefully you
can kinda see why, we'll look
at the error, and it says,
you cannot assign the value
of type ImageViewController,
which is what self is, to
the type UIScrollViewDelegate
optional. So I told you that
the ScrollViewDelegate is
an optional
UIScrollViewDelegate protocol,
and that's what it is.
And of course,
self isn't that even though it
doesn't employ any methods and
that protocol has only
optional methods.
Because it needs to go
up here and say yes,
I'm a UIScrollViewDelegate.
Okay, so this is this class,
UIViewController, saying I
conform to this protocol, and
as soon as I do that,
the error goes away, and
there's no errors. Even
though I didn't do anything,
I didn't actually implement
the UIScrollView delegate
protocol, that's because all
the methods in UIScrollView
delegate are optional. So
I don't implement any,
but they're all optional.
So I've conformed to
the protocol. But of course,
that's not gonna help us with
our zooming because we in
fact do need to implement
a method. Now I'm gonna show
you a cool way to do this with
extensions. I'm going to add
protocol conformance to my
ImageViewController with
an extension. And
I'm gonna do that like this.
So I'm gonna make it so that
it does not conform, okay,
ImageViewController does
not conform.
But I'm gonna add an extension
down here, at the bottom of my
file, which is an extension
to the ImageViewController,
which causes
ImageViewController to conform
to the UIScrollViewDelegate
protocol. Okay, so by just
putting this here, this error
down here is gonna go away.
Because I've added an
extension, which causes this,
this class right here to
conform to this protocol.
Again, all the methods
are optional so
normally we would have to put
a bunch of methods in here.
But I am gonna put the one
method we do want down here,
which is viewForZooming
in scrollView.
Now what's interesting, notice
as I start to type this,
it actually knows that I'm
a UIScrollViewDelegate, so
it offers me that
method as a choice, so
I'll double click on it.
Here's my viewForZooming in
scrollView. I just need to
return which view I wanna
zoom in for us. Of course,
it's that image view.
So I wanna just say
return imageView, but
that doesn't work. Why do
you think that doesn't work?
This imageView is private.
Now, I could unmake
it private, but
now everyone can see
that image view, and
that's a little too unprivate.
So there's another kind of
private called fileprivate,
and what fileprivate means is,
it's private to everyone
in this file. So
that allows this extension
to see this image view. And
it's still private
to everyone else.
So everyone using my MVC
who sees this, other files,
it's still private, they don't
see it. But this guy can use
it, okay? So that's
a different kind of private,
fileprivate. All right, so
we got the view for zooming.
This is, in fact,
the view we wanna zoom.
So let's go ahead and
take a look here.
All right, here it is. We
can still scroll around, and
if we hold down the option key
and get our two fingers here,
we can also zoom. Okay, and
we can zoom in really small,
and we can zoom out.
But notice, it won't let
me zoom any larger than
1.0 because I set that as
my maximum zoom scale.
All right, so, the last thing
I'm gonna do, well, I'll leave
this as is cuz I'm gonna post
this code like this, and
you can play around with it.
Next time, what I'm gonna
do is add another MVC that
lets us pick some NASA images,
you can see any NASA images.
And one thing we're gonna find
about this images, they're
huge, and even on our Stanford
network, they take a long time
to download. And that's gonna
be annoying, and so we are
going to use multithreading
to keep our UI responsive,
even though it's doing
this very expensive thing,
which is downloading this
huge file, all right? So,
I'll see you then.
>> For
more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.