>> Stanford University.
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193,
winter quarter of 2017.
Today I'm going to continue
that demo that we started last
I'm really just going to
enhance it to be multiple MVC
time.
again, it gives you a chance
to see it all happen again.
And I'm gonna be going
very quickly for
doing that because we already
did that in the last demo, so
and you did it on
your homework,
so hopefully it's really,
really comfortable.
Now we're going to dive
back into the slides and
solve a problem that we're
going to have with our app,
which is that
it's really slow.
And not only really slow, but
it blocks our user interface
so that the user thinks
the app is probably dead and
needs to be killed or
something.
And we're gonna fix that
with multithreading, so
I'm gonna talk a little about
how we do multithreading.
I'll go back to the demo,
we'll fix it with
multithreading.
I'm gonna show you a couple
other cool things to do.
And then we're gonna come
back to the slides and
I'm gonna talk about text
field, which is a little bit
of a random topic, but
I have to fit it in somewhere.
And if I have a little time at
the end, which I doubt I will,
but if I have time at the end,
I'll actually get started on
table view, which is gonna be
our big topic for Wednesday.
A very important topic, and
it's what your next
assignment is gonna be about.
Sorry, your next assignment
has multi-threading as well,
of course, but it's mostly
a table view assignment, so
that's what we're
gonna do today.
So let's jump right back into
our demo from last time.
You remember that it
looked like this, so
here it is running.
And this was a nice little
image viewing application so
far, and we can zoom in and
out, and pan around, and
all that.
And in fact,
in building this application,
I've built this nice generic
ImageViewController.
It's a reusable MVC,
just like in your assignment,
you built a reusable graphing
view controller, well,
I've built a generic MVC
that will show an image and
let you zoom in on it and pan
around, so, that's kinda cool.
Hopefully you're gaining
an appreciation for
good API design, and how
important good API design and
reusable componentry is to
building good architecture in
general, so hopefully,
you're seeing that.
I mean, these are very simple
applications that we're
writing, so it's hard to see.
But when you start building
a huge app and have these
reuseable components and
really strong public APIs that
you're willing to support, and
things like that, then you'll
find that your application
is gonna have less bugs,
and it's gonna be able
to grow over time.
And you're gonna be able
to work in teams better, so
it's just good all around.
In my viewDidLoad, I put
that little imageURL equals
DemoURL.stanford that
was just for testing.
Now that we know
that it works,
I'm just gonna delete that so
that my ImageViewController
again can be reusable.
This is its public API,
which happens to be its model.
It's not that unusual,
by the way, for the public
API of a view controller
to be to set the model,
that's quite actually common.
So that's our model,
it's the URL for
the image you wanna show,
and it's public.
So we're gonna be using that
when we build the rest of
So our storyboard so far
just has this one image view
our app.
controller right here, and I'm
just gonna rapidly go through
and build a multiple MVC app.
What we're gonna do is
just use our generic image
controller MVC here to
view images related to
the Cassini project,
which is a space probe that
was sent out to Saturn.
To do that, it's gonna be
all the things you know.
I'm going to get it
build another MVC, so
here let's drag
out another MVC.
Let's create a class for it.
It's a Cocoa Touch Class,
of course,
I'm gonna call it Cassini,
my CassiniViewController.
I'm gonna put it in the same
place that I put all my other
files here, and here's my
CassiniViewController.
I'm gonna remove my
ViewController lifecycle but
I'm gonna leave my prepare for
segue, without the comments,
because I am going to
be segueing from this
CassiniViewController to
my ImageViewController.
So the way this UI is gonna
work is I'm just gonna have
three buttons here in Cassini,
similar to how we had with
the emotions application.
And these three buttons are
going to pick these three URLs
right here that are from
NASA here, jpl.nasa.gov.
One's of Cassini itself,
one's of the Earth and
one is of Saturn, so we're
just gonna have three buttons
that let you pick
those three images.
So let's build that UI.
First of all, let's make
sure we set our identity.
We just dragged out
a generic ViewController,
we obviously want its identity
to be a specific subclass,
in this case,
the CassiniViewController,
just like this one is
an ImageViewController.
So let's drag this out to make
the button a little bigger,
to get a bigger font.
Try a maybe 40 point,
something like that.
The three buttons that I had,
one was Earth, I'll just do
copy and paste, make a couple
more buttons here, another one
was Cassini itself,
another one was Saturn.
And we'll just select these
and we'll put them in a stack
view, and we'll put some
spacing between, and
we'll fill, and fill equally.
We'll take it and
drag it to the middle here.
We'll use our blue lines
to put it in the middle, so
that we can go down here, and
say Reset to
Suggested Constraints.
We can go to our Size
Inspector here just to verify
that the constraints it added
seem like the ones we want,
which definitely
does seem like that.
Let's go ahead and,
one thing I wanna show you
a little different this
time is before we started with
a SplitViewController and
then I added the navigation
controller in.
In other words,
I started with an iPad UI,
building an iPad UI, and then
I made it also work on iPhone.
We can do the other
way around as well.
So we could take this view
controller, which is the one,
the base one that we
want to show, and
we can say embed it in
a Navigation Controller.
And then, obviously,
we want to make this
navigation controller be
the entry point of our app.
I don't want to forget that,
so I'm just gonna throw that
little arrow over
here onto the left.
And then when we do
our segues here,
like from Earth over to here,
and from Cassini.
And I'm going to Show Detail
because I know eventually I'm
also going to support
the iPad, instead of Show,
which would only really
support the iPhone.
Because Show, remember,
if you do a Show and
you're in the master of
an iPad, it'll actually,
if you're in Navigation
Controller in the master of
the iPad and you do Show, it's
going to replace the mster,
whereas Show Detail
replaces the detail.
So here I have
these three segues.
I'm gonna kinda cheat
a little bit and
have my segue identifiers
just be the names of these
URLs right here, so
Cassini, Earth, and Saturn,
that's gonna be my
segue identifiers.
I say it's cheating because
normally your identifier would
just identify the segue, and
then you would get the
information somewhere else,
but just to make our code
really, really simple.
Oops, that's not Earth,
that one's Saturn.
And then let's go to this one,
wait, where's our Earth?
And we go to this one,
oops, this one rather,
that is Cassini.
Okay, so we built our UI here.
Now, this would be really only
an iPhone appropriate UI.
If we run this on iPhone,
it actually would look fine,
you'll see.
Now why doesn't
this work as is?
You see I had this right here,
and I get this modal view,
it kinda came up.
Obviously, we have no
image selected yet,
we haven't written
any prepare code.
But there's no back here.
Why is there no back?
That's because of this
things being show detail.
Because show detail only works
in the iPad configuration.
So like, if I change
this to being a show.
Well, actually,
I'm not sure, someone was
saying that to we have to
remake that one to be a show.
Let's see if that works.
And this is where
it goes Saturn.
Cuz we're not being prepared.
All right, see?
So now it pushes, we're inside
the navigation controller.
We can go back.
But this is an iPhone only and
we don't want that.
We want to work on
both platforms.
So I am gonna take
that out again,
and put this back to
be showed detail.
Anyway, so I have this nice
iPhone API, or UI rather.
And I wanna turn into
split view if, so
I am going the other way and
terms of preparing it.
So lets go down here and
grab a split view.
I drag it out here,
remember it brings all
this other junk with it.
We close our document outline,
you can delete these
things that came with it.
Now we have our Split View
Controller right here, and
we can just use Ctrl+Drag
to make this be our master.
And we can put this down here,
let's say,
in control drag to make
this be our detail.
And let's make our entry
point the display view and
just like that now,
we turn this into something
that can work on iPad.
But having these segues we
show versus show detail is
kind of an annoying little
difference between the two
platforms.
So you kinda have to know
whether you're gonna put
it into split view or
not unfortunately,
when you build your app.
Now, this will still
work on iPhone.
Just begins on
the detail to start and
we can navigate here into
these various things.
And it will also work on iPad,
lets see iPad.
Here is the thing we can
slide out our master,
I click on these things or
we can go to landscape.
And again, it's not showing
anything cuz I haven't yet.
on iPad maybe we want to
put this in a navigation
Now, again,
controller right here so,
we get a nice title over here.
So I can do that as well,
just go down here and
select this new
controller down here and
do embed in
navigation control.
Now if we do that,
we're gonna be want to be
careful in our prepare.
That when we prepare for
this segue, we account for
this navigation controller
perhaps being there.
And I'm gonna show you
how to do that as well.
Let's do our prepare.
We've got our UI,
same kinda UI as we did in
emotions, exactly the same.
But obviously nothing works
in these segues unless we
So, let's go to our prepare
for segue here and type it in.
prepare.
It's gonna be a really
simple prepare for segue,
cuz I made the segue
identifier be the thing I'm
gonna look up in the table.
So I'm just gonna say
if I can let the URL,
that I want the NASA URL,
equal DemoURL.NASA.
And I'm gonna look it up, by
taking the segue identifier,
but if that segue identified
with nil, this won't work.
In other words,
you can't look up something
that's an optional,
like the identifier is,
in a dictionary.
This dictionary is looking for
a string here.
So, I'm just gonna say
defaulting to nothing.
And of course, looking this
up in this dictionary,
it's gonna return nil.
But I'm doing if let right
here, so that's okay.
Now I'm getting the URL if
possible, so that segue,
if it's possible to
get that URL out of
the NASA dictionary,
then I will do that.
Now, of course,
I need the view controller
that I'm segueing to.
So I'm gonna say,
if I can let imageVC =
(segue.destination as?
ImageViewController.
That's that view controller
that we're segueing to.
If I can do that,
then I can prepare.
But of course, here we've
got the problem where this
destination on an iPad
might be, what?
A navigation controller.
So normally, we would
put a little if in here,
we say if the thing is
a navigation controller,
then we would get
the visible view controller.
Remember that code
that we put in there?
You probably put that
in your homework,
if you used navigation
control for your detail.
Instead, I'm gonna put
that in an extension,
remember we learned about
extensions last time?
So I'm going to extend
UI view controller, and
just add a var to
UIViewController.
Now this var I'm gonna add,
I'm gonna call it contents,
and it's going to be of
type UIViewController.
And since it's in
the extension,
it can't be a var
that has any storage.
Extensions have no storage.
So it can only be a computed
var so I'm gonna compute it.
And what is contents gonna be,
what is this var?
Well, I'm defining contents
to be the contents of this
view controller, what this
view controller holds?
Well, if this view controller
is a navigation controller,
then tha's the visible
view controller.
If it's not,
then it's just itself,
a view controller's
contents are itself.
Unless, it happens to be
a navigation controller and
then it returns to
visible view controller.
I could also,
And if I am,
show the visible tab, too.
But for interest of
time I won't do that,
you can do that if you want.
I'm just gonna say here if
I can let navcon = self as?
a UINavigationController.
In other words, if I'm a
navigation controller then I'm
just going to return
the navcon's visible.
Navcon is myself,
it's just that it's myself
as a navigation controller.
So I can send this var,
I can get this var from it.
Of course, this visible
view controller is optional
because the navigation
controller might not have any
view controller in
it at the moment.
So, I better have a default
there which I'll just
return self.
And then if I'm not in
navigation controller,
then I'm just
gonna return self.
So you see how content, it's
showing the contents of our
navigation folder, otherwise,
it's returning myself.
Which is kind of cool for
this situation.
And it allows me to go up
here, instead of saying segue
destination, I can just say
sequedestination.content.
And then I don't need
this little if up there.
Now, is this a reasonable
thing to do in extension?
Absolutely it is, because
this var has complete and
utter understandable semantics
that only have to do
with the UI view
controller and
nothing to do with Casini view
controller or anything else.
Because when you
do an extension,
you want that to be the case.
You don't wanna generally put
extensions on other classes
that have to do with
other classes, generally.
Unless they're kind of
like standard types, or
something like that.
Maybe converting from
a string to a date,
or something like that.
In some way might
make some sense, but
you wouldn't want to put
extensions on other classes
that are specific to things
that other classes need.
In that case, just put
a function in your own class
that does that thing.
So does everyone see what
I'm saying about this?
This makes perfect sense,
this would be usable
in any environment,
it's a sensible var to
have on a view controller.
Now that I have my
image view controller,
either by getting it or
going through the navigation
controller, I can prepare it.
And so
preparing it is really easy,
I just wanna set the URL
equal to that URL, okay,
the URL that I got
out of the demo URL.
This is just public API, okay,
this happens to be its model,
let's also set its title.
We can set the title equal to,
we could do the same
thing we did before.
Take the sender interpret
it as a UI button and
if we're able to do that then
we'll get the current title.
Which might be nil, but
that's okay because this
is also an optional.
This is optional so can take
a nil even though this is nil.
And of course it might be nil
because this turns out to not
be true, and that's fine, too.
See how these optionals play
out nicely because you have
vars that are optional and
things are optional?
So you can set things
equal to each other and
it kind of just all plays out
kind of beautifully there.
So that's it, let's run here.
Let's see
what we got.
Here we go.
So
let's take a look at Cassini,
for
example, look, it's broken.
Whoa, what's going on?
I clicked there to get Cassini
which, look, there's Cassini.
Let's zoom in on Cassini.
There it is.
So this is the Cassini space
probe right here by Saturn.
But when I clicked on it,
it seemed like my UI froze.
And if I click on these
other ones, look,
I'm clicking Saturn, Saturn,
Saturn, nothing's happening.
Because it,
now something came up.
So this UI seems broken.
Now we're on ultra
fast network here.
This is Stanford's network.
We have like gigabyte
connections to everywhere and
it still took a while cuz
it's a very large file.
Imagine I was on cellular.
That image might take
a minute to download.
And meanwhile my app
is completely stuck,
I can't click on
any other button.
If I'm on iPhone,
lets see what he looks like
on iPhone, it's even worse.
If I'm on iPhone,
I'm gonna click that.
I'm gonna think,
" my app is broken".
So I'm in
a NavigationController,
no problem,
I'll just hit back.
But even the back button's
not gonna work, as you'll see.
All right, so here we are.
Got the detailed view there.
Now I'm gonna hit Earth,
it's stuck.
And again,
I can't do anything.
Finally comes back.
So this kinda UI is horrible
because, especially on
cellular or something
where it's really slow,
users are like,
this app is broken.
They're literally going
to double-click the Home
button and flip your app off,
to use an analogy there.
They're gonna flip your app
and kill it because their,
they think it's broken.
So we're gonna fix
that with multitasking.
So first, let me show
you how that works.
All right, so, multithreading.
There's two reasons generally,
that you wanna do
multithreading.
One reason is, you have
a mathematical problem, or
some image processing problem,
that is best solved
using some kind of parallel
processing algorithm where you
wanna go off and do 1000
things or 100 things at once.
And then and when they're all
done together you're gonna
combine the result, or
something like that.
So that's an obvious need
to do multithreading.
That's not the multithreading
I'm gonna be
talking to you about.
That, that's a perfectly
valid use of multithreading,
iOS has some great API for
doing that kind of design.
But that's not what
I'm talking about.
The second reason that you
might wanna do multithreading
is because you
have one thread.
By the way, does everyone
know what a thread is?
Raise your hand if you
know what a thread is.
Okay, I see some people
saying, yeah, remind me.
A thread just means, thread is
short for thread of execution.
And it just is kind of a,
the process,
through which code
is executing.
That could conceivably be
separated where you have
multiple of them.
in the iOS, you've got a very
important kind of main thread
For example,
That's the thread of execution
that is listening to gestures
of execution.
and doing drawing,
things like that.
Then you can have other
threads of execution that
might be doing background
things, like going out onto
the network and getting data,
or something like that.
Most of our devices aren't
multiprocessor, per se, so
these threads, although they
have multiple cores, so
they can actually do
two things at once.
They literally can.
But in this case where I'm
talking about multithreading
to solve this problem of
keeping the UI responsive,
we don't even care about that.
And so here's the thing with
multithreading and the UI.
We want the thread of
execution which is listening
to the user to be super
responsive, always working,
never blocked.
And we don't really care
about other threads too much,
but we really want that one
to be unblocked at all time.
So if we're ever going to do
anything that would block,
like either block because it's
doing so much computation
that it's not getting back
to the rest of the code.
Or in this case, with our
Cassini, it's gonna block
because it's waiting on some
resource like the network.
Okay, I make a request for
a URL.
It doesn't respond
immediately, I have to wait.
Any time I have to wait, I
can't be waiting in the middle
of that UI cuz now no
one can do a gesture or
click on the back button or
do anything else.
So that's the kind of
multithreading that I'm
talking about here that
we're gonna try and
solve, is keep the UI thread
responsive and active
by pushing everything else
that could be slow or blocked,
waiting on a resource,
off to a different thread.
Now in iOS,
we don't actually even really
talk about threads much.
I've been using
this word thread,
because that's what's going
on underneath the covers.
We're talking about
threads of execution here.
But really,
what we talk about is queues.
So multithreading is
really about queues.
Now what's a queue?
Queue is an English word,
actually.
We don't use it in
the United States much, but
a queue just means a line.
Like if you go to the movies,
you might say, I'm queueing up
to see this movie, especially
if you were in London,
you would say let's go
queue for the movie.
So that's all a queue is,
it's a line.
And what are we gonna
put in this line?
Instead of people waiting for
the movie, we're gonna
put blocks of code.
And we know a great way to
make a block of code that we
can put in a line
which is a closure.
So we're almost always
doing this with closure.
So putting these closures,
it could be any blocking code,
but we're putting these
closures basically,
usually into a queue.
And so what's happening
then is the system
is creating threads as
necessary to grab those
blocks off that queue, off the
front of the line, who's ever
in the front of the queue and
executing on a thread.
That's how multitasking or
multithreading really
works in iOS.
We don't really care how
the system assigns threads to
these lines, these queues.
All we care about
is the queues.
And when we wanna express
to the system where we want
things to run, you know,
where the UI runs or
in background process or
whatever,
we specify it by what
queue we put code on.
Does that make sense?
Let's talk about the queues
that we can have.
One important queue,
of course, is the main queue.
So this is the queue
on which all the UI
activity is happening.
It's not only the queue that
all UI activity is happening
But it's the only queue that
UI activity can happen on.
in general.
And that's because
it's a serial queue.
A serial queue is
a queue where everyone,
the blocks in code
are waiting in line to run,
and there's only one
thread to run them.
So when the system comes along
to grab the next guy in line,
he runs him to completion and
then goes back for
the next one.
So you see how they're serial.
They happen in order.
The entire line of closures
waiting to run, or code
waiting to run, is processed
in order, one at a time.
What's really great about
the UI side of that is it
makes it very predictable.
You really don't have to get
into a lot of the mind games
of multithreading, where it's
like, is this thing waiting on
this, do I have to have a lock
on this data resource bug?
Because all the UI stuff
is all happening in
the main queue.
This is all
happening serially,
you never have to worry about
two UI things accessing
the same data structure
at the same time,
cuz they're all just marching
in line, down this main queue.
So, all UI activity and only
UI activity, no other stuff,
generally, runs in the UI,
the main queue.
And the reason we don't want
other stuff running in the
main queue, is we never want
the main queue to be blocked.
We never want it to be off
doing some computation or,
certainly, never
blocked waiting for
the network or something.
So that's the main queue,
that's the most important
queue, and then,
there are these other queues.
I'm gonna talk first
about the global queues.
The global queues
are different kind of queues.
These global queues, people
wait in line to go onto those,
and at the other end of the
line the system has multiple
threads ready to go.
And it can pull a closure off
the line, give it a thread,
it starts running,
pulls another one off,
it starts running before
the first one's even done.
So those are called
concurrent queues.
The queues where you could be
pulling people off the line
cuz you got multiple threads
to assign to the task.
So, things we do
outside the UI,
like network things and things
that block, we're generally
gonna do those in these
global concurrent queues.
You can also create your
own serial queues and
your own concurrent queues.
We'll talk about that
in a couple slides.
You're not going to need
to do that in this class.
90% of the time you're either
using the main queue, or
you're using one of these
global concurrent queues.
So let's talk about the code,
how do you get a queue?
I need a queue because I wanna
put a block of code on this
queue, I want it to
get in line to go run.
Well, the main queue,
you just use this bar
DispatchQueue.main.
It's a static bar,
a class bar,
on the class dispatch queue,
and that's it,
you have your main queue,
it couldn't be easier.
Now, getting one of these
global concurrent queues,
a little bit more work.
You're going to use
DispatchQueue.global instead
of DispatchQueue.main, and it
takes an argument there, QoS.
QoS stands for
Quality of Service.
So this is talking about how,
what
the quality of the service
that the line is getting.
So, high quality service means
things are being pulled off
the line really fast and the
threads that are being used to
execute them are high priority
threads that get to run a lot.
Cuz remember there's
only one processor, so
they often kinda
share the processor.
So, high quality service
means you get a lot.
Low quality services, well,
the system will pull your
thing off when it feels like
it, like maybe the phone is,
is well, got woken up for
some other reason,
it's not gonna wake
your phone up to do it.
And it's certainly not going
to block any high priority
thing, that kind of thing.
So, but the quality of service
is not like a number, 0,
low quality, 10,
high quality, instead,
it's kind of
a flavor of usage.
These are the four
qualities of services here.
So user interactive is, means
the user is interacting with
the UI right now,
usually with a gesture.
They are panning around, or
pinching, and your forking off
something into a thread
to go do something.
Now, this is usually not a
case of the thing you're gonna
be doing is so intensive
that it would block the main
thread, because the person
is panning right now.
But it might be something
that can't quite keep up
with the finger, and you're
going to deal with that by,
in this other thread, trying
to keep up as best you can and
just updating the main
thread as fast as you can,
which might be a little slower
than the fingers going.
So, you know,
the finger dragging around,
maybe it's jumping a little
bit because it can't calculate
its new position fast enough.
But the point is, this
queue really needs to run,
almost as bad, it's almost
as high priority as the main
queue because you're doing
something interactive.
Okay, the next one
is user initiated.
What this means is this, the
user currently did something
to initiate this activity,
this can be done in
this queue, so
it's pretty high priority.
Okay, the user did something
and they're waiting for
a response presumably.
So that would be the category
for our Cassini project.
We clicked Earth, or Saturn,
we want that image now, and
we're waiting for it.
So we are gonna use,
user initiated.
Cuz the user initiated
a request for it.
But it's gonna take a while,
and the user's not
interacting, we're not
making it doing something
different every time it moves.
We were just, it's, but
it was user initiated, so
user initiated is
pretty high priority.
Then there's background and
utility.
These are somewhat similar.
Utility is truly the deepest
of background processes.
This might be something you
run once a week in your app.
Maybe it cleans up
the database by removing old
crufty stuff,
something the user doesn't
even know is going on.
It's so low priority,
it just kind of happens
in the background.
Background might be
something that you, you,
like maybe you're thinking
ahead a little bit about
the way the user might
want to use your app.
And so you fork something
off in the background to go
fetch some stuff or whatever.
The user didn't ask you to do
it, but you kind of do it.
And you kind of
want it nowish but
it's okay if it takes
a little while.
So you see what that one is.
So these are the four
qualities of service and
you just need to pick which
quality of service you want
for your global queue.
And then remember that
the things you put on there
are going to be run
concurrently, so
they can really
depend on each other.
I'll talk about things
depending on each other in
But this, you wanna think
about the things you put on
a second.
these global queues
as being these
independent little things,
like go fetch this file,
it's all self contained,
just give me this file.
Not blocks that are gonna
be somehow depending on
each other's results because
this is all concurrent,
these things can be happening
at exactly the same time, so
they can't really, it's not
serial like the main queue.
Now, like I said,
you've got this queue,
and all we're gonna do
is put blocks on it and
we do that with these two
functions, async and sync.
These two functions take one
argument, which is a closure,
a function but usually it's
a closure, that closure
function takes no arguments
and returns no arguments.
And you can put anything
you want in that closure.
So, async means put this
closure on the queue,
put it in the line to execute,
and return immediately.
So async does
nothing except for
put that block into the queue,
whatever queue you send it to.
Sync, same thing,
puts it in the queue and
then it says block this thread
until that closure finishes
executing on whatever
queue it's on.
Which could be a totally
different queue.
So basically, the sync is
block me until this closure
finishes executing
wherever you put it.
So, you would never do
sync on the main queue,
cuz we never want to
block the main queue.
So, you would never say
main queue.sync anything.
But you might have
other queues and say,
you know, sorry, you would say
main queue, you could say main
queue.sync, but you would
say it on another thread.
You fire off some
of the thread,
it's running along
in the background.
It could say main queue.sync,
this code.
Now that code would be
put on the main queue.
Sometime later,
we don't know when,
it would run on
the main queue.
Once it's done,
then your thread,
your queue that issued this,
would continue.
So sync, we would only do the
sync from code that is not on
the main queue, cuz we never
wanna block the main queue.
Question.
Yeah, so the question is,
when I say sync, am I saying,
let this block, this closure
go first or something?
No, okay, this has nothing
to do with priority.
The priority is
the quality of service.
I'm just saying
put this queue,
this closure onto
the end of that queue.
Now, whatever queue it is,
we'll have some
quality of service and
it will eventually
get to this thing.
In the meantime,
while all that's happening,
this queue that this code is
in is waiting, it's blocked.
It's just blocked, waiting for
that closure to finish.
How that closure finishes
depends totally on what queue
you put it on, and how much
other stuff is in that queue,
and whether it's a concurrent
queue, all those things.
But this sync just means block
me until that thing's done.
Question.
So the question is,
does running multiple threads,
having multiple things
going in multiple threads,
does it slow down
the main queue thread,
the thread that is
running the main queue?
And the answer is no.
It does not usually, because
the main queue is getting
a lot of high priority.
So it's pretty much
interrupting anything those
other guys are doing whenever
it wants to run, okay?
So if it wants to run,
it pretty much gets
the processor.
The main queue is the highest
priority thread that exist on
the device.
So it's rarely gonna
be slowed down.
Now, I'm not gonna talk
about this, but yes,
threads have overhead.
If you created
thousands of threads,
that would start slowing
down your computer.
But again, that's why we don't
really talk about threads.
We talk about queues and
we let the iOS manage the
threads cuz it knows how to
efficiently manage thread
pools and things like that.
You can create your
own queues just using
a normal initializer
of DispatchQueue.
Instead of saying
DispatchQueue.main or
DispatchQueue.global, you
say DispatchQueue
with the initializer that
takes a label that makes
a serial queue.
And that label,
it shows up in the debugger.
So in the debugger
if you pause and
that queue is
running a thread,
you'll see that thread in
the little debugger window on
the left in the navigator
with this name, this label,
so it's just purely for
seeing it in the debugger.
And if you wanna make your
own concurrent queue.
A queue that has multiple
threads that can be working
on things.
Then same thing, except you
put attributes.concurrent,
in the initializer there.
You won't need to do
that in this class and
rarely do we do this.
It's usually main queue and
the global queues
90% of the time.
All right, I'm only showing
you the absolute tip
of the iceberg for
multithreading.
I'm showing you the basic
stuff you need to get stuff
off of the main thread but
there is a lot more.
You're gonna wanna familiarize
yourself eventually with
DispatchQueue and
all the things that it can do.
This stuff is all
based on something
called Grand Central Dispatch.
Because when we put
a closure onto a queue,
we call that dispatching
the closure onto that queue.
For those of you who do
know about multithreading,
you can do all the things
you can expect,
protecting critical sections,
readers and writers, you know,
single writer
multiple readers.
You can do synchronous
dispatch, you can do locking,
all the things you
need to do you can do.
I'm not gonna talk about any
of that, but it's all there.
There is another API for
doing multithreading,
OperationQueue and Operation,
these are classes.
Classes or structs,
I guess they're classes.
And you'll see those
occasionally in iOS API,
kinda older iOS API.
But for the program
you're gonna do, again,
unless you got the kind of
multithreading problem, which
is doing a parallel processing
thing, not the kind of problem
where you're getting
something off the main queue.
Operation and OperationQueue
are nice because it makes easy
to make dependencies.
Where you say this
block of code
depends on this
one running first,
I need the result from this
one before I can do this one.
So you can set up
those relationships,
then you can say,
now I just start running them.
And the system
will make sure this one gets
run before this one, etc.
All those dependencies.
So that's Operation and
OperationQueue.
you'll see certain methods
that are multithreaded.
In iOS,
And you'll see that
in the documentation,
you'll read in
the documentation.
And the way it works is you're
gonna see a method that takes
a closure as an argument, and
it'll say in the documentation
this closure is run on another
thread off the main queue.
And when you see that,
you have to go, uh-oh, because
any code I put in that closure
that I'm passing to this
function can't be doing any
UI stuff because that only
can happen on the main queue.
And this happens quite a lot,
that we have a closure that
we're putting on some
background queue, or
passing to some iOS function,
that says it's not gonna
put it on the main queue.
But we still wanna do UI
stuff, so how do we do that?
We just dispatch it
back to the main queue.
And this is what
that looks like.
Here is an iOS API that takes
a closure as an argument and
it runs that closure
off the main queue.
I's called NSURLSession,
i's used for
getting the contents of URLs.
Now, you saw in our image
view controller demo, so far,
that we already know how to
get the contents of URLs,
we just use data contents of.
Remember, we said try
data contents of.
And it blocked, blocked the
main queue while it went and
got that URL.
So that's one way to do it.
But it kind of
non-configurable.
What's cool about
NSURLSession is,
you see that argument there
configuration.default?
Well, you can change
that configuration.
For example, you could say,
I'm gonna fetch this URL,
but don't fetch
it over cellular.
Only fetch it if I
happen to be on a Wi-Fi
network, for example.
So you can configure how you
want this fetching to happen.
So it's kind of a more
powerful way of fetching than
just saying data contents of.
And the way it works is you
create an NSURLSession with a,
(this is an old slide, so it's
just called URLSession and URL
not NSURL), but you create it
with a certain configuration,
then you get the URL you
want and then you call this
method dataTask(with: url) and
closure.
And what this does is it
creates a dataTask object.
With that URL that you
want to get, and when, and
it goes off to fetch it,
or it will in a minute.
And when you send
it off to fetch it,
when it comes back it will
call this closure and
this closure has
three arguments.
The data it got from the URL,
the NSURL or
the URL response,
and then some error,
if some error happened
trying to get it.
So the, that closure, so this
closure is interesting cuz it,
the documentation
will tell you,
this closure does not
run on the main queue.
So, that's a problem because
if, (by the way, that resume,
task.resume at the bottom,
that's what actually causes
it to go do the fetch),
so the dataTask really
doesn't do anything but
create the task, and then when
you say task.resume it goes
off to fetch it on some
other thread, doesn't block.
task.resume does not
block obviously.
So when the closure,
when the data is gotten and
that closure is finally called
on some other queue
besides the main queue.
You wanna do some UI in there
like you wanna show the image
that you just fetched or
whatever.
And you can't do it because
you're not on the main queue.
So, how do you fix that?
You just put inside of this
closure that you put right
here, another dispatch.
Back to the main queue.
DispatchQueue.main.async with
a closure.
And you put your
UI stuff in there,
now it's gonna happen back on
the other, on the main queue.
So let's go through,
I wanna show you the timing
of each of the steps of
this code right here.
So you can see what's
happening, when.
Because multithreading is
really a lot about when, and
it's the when that can
confuse people when
they're doing multithreading.
So obviously, the first line
of code is that let url,
get the url, so
now I have the url.
Next, we're gonna
create this dataTask.
This line of code, line B
there, returns immediately.
Because all it does is
create the dataTask,
it doesn't actually
do anything.
You pass the closure to it,
but it's a non-escaping
Closure, hold onto it, this
data task thing holds onto it.
Then you do task resume,
that also returns immediately.
But on a different queue,
it starts doing the fetch.
It starts trying to get
the contents of that URL.
But on some other queue, so
that's why on this queue, this
is the main queue presumably.
It is returning immediately,
task.resume returns
immediately.
So that means that line H
happens immediately right
after task resume,
boom the print firing,
done firing off the request.
But that's all
we've done is fired
off the request at this point.
The next line of code that's
gonna happen after this one
is this one.
So after the URL
contents come back,
now this closure
is gonna execute.
And so we're gonna have
line c be executed.
So a, b, g, and h, they
executed boom, boom, boom,
boom, run right after
each other, no delay.
Then there was a delay
while we went and
got the URL content.
That could be a long delay.
That could be minute or
more if it was a big file over
cellular or
something like that.
So this line of code, c,
you have to be careful.
It could happen much later,
and by the time it happens,
you might not even
care anymore.
If you had a really slow
network and a big file,
by the time it came back,
the user, they're like,
I don't even care about it.
So you, when you come back
to line c right there,
you better check and make sure
that you still even care.
Make sense?
All right, next thing that
happens is we wanna do some UI
stuff with the data
we got back.
But of course to do that,
we have to dispatch
to the main queue.
This line of code, line d,
also returns immediately
because it's async dispatch.
All it's doing is putting that
closure onto the main queue.
So this is the next line
of code that executes.
Notice line e has
not executed yet.
Line f executes and it just
says I did some stuff with
the data, but the UI
part hasn't happened yet.
I put it on the queue, but
it hasn't been executed yet
by the main queue.
And then finally the UI
stuff gets pulled off
the main queue and executed.
Did everyone understand
that process?
So to summarize, its a,
b, g, h, c, d, f, e.
Now this thing about this,
there's actually not
necessarily exactly this way.
Because when you dispatch
things to the main queue from
the main queue,
they could run right away.
So it is possible that e
could happen before f.
But if this was on some other
queue besides the main queue,
it's very unlikely that
e could happen before f.
But it even could then
because the main queue has so
much priority that when you
dispatch something onto it,
the system might immediately
go and try and process it.
That's how high priority
the main queue is.
So it's possible that e
could happen before f.
But I just want you to think
conceptually that when you put
something on the queue, you
kind of put it on the queue,
There might be other things on
the main queue ahead of you.
could happen later.
So definitely wouldn't
run right away then.
So that's the timing
of multithreaded.
So let's go back to our
Cassini code and make it so
that it uses these queues to
stop blocking the main thread
and stop being all
stuck like that.
To do this is actually
remarkably simple.
We're just gonna go back
to our imageViewController,
this is the deadly
line of code.
I even put a comment in for
this line of code when I
posted this last time so
that you realize this is
a terrible line of code.
This line of code,
if this is in, from now on,
if you turn in homework with
a line of code like this,
you're gonna get major dings.
Because one of the evaluation
criteria now is gonna be no
more blocking the main queue.
You cannot block
the main queue.
That's, that's an evaluation
criteria of all the homework
going forward and
of your final project.
All right, so we have this
terrible thing, and we can't
do this line of code like this
cuz it blocks the main queue,
so what are we gonna do?
We're just simply gonna put
this call on some other queue.
And I'm gonna do that by just
saying DispatchQueue.global,
I'm gonna get a global,
one of these global
concurrent queues.
And it's asking me for
the quality of service.
And the user initiated
this request, but
it's not interactive, so
I'm gonna say userInitiated,
the choices there.
Now I've got the queue I want,
and I'm just gonna
asynchronously post this
code that I wanna do,
this code that blocks,
onto that global queue.
And at some point, that global
queue is going to allocate
a thread and grab this closure
off it and start running.
Now that's gonna happen
pretty darn quick, but
not necessarily instantly.
So now I've solved
the problem,
woo hoo,
it's off the main queue.
No longer blocking the main
queue because this,
which is executed
on the main queue,
because all of this code
is on the main queue.
We're executing all of
our codes generally on
the main queue.
This returns immediately.
It's async, so it immediately
returns, it just puts that
closure on the queue and
returns immediately.
So no blocking the main queue,
excellent.
But you notice I got
this little error here.
Let's take a look at it,
what's that thing?
Yeah, reference to
self inside a closure.
You have to
explicitly put self so
that you think about
memory cycles.
And indeed, there is
a bad memory cycle here.
Because this closure, if you
remember, this is happening
because I clicked on Saturn or
Cassini or Earth.
And it went off, created
an ImageViewController for me,
and that ImageView Controller
is being put on screen and
it's going off to
fetch this thing.
Now what if the user is like,
I'm tired of waiting for
that Earth image, and they hit
back, and go click on Saturn.
When they hit back,
what's supposed to happen to
that ImageViewController?
Anyone?
>> It's supposed to
leave the heap, okay.
Because it was under
navigation controllers on
the top and I hit back.
Whoo, toss it out,
but can it leave?
No, because this closure
is keeping it in
the heap even though I
don't want this any more.
I went back because I'm
now I'm going over to see
Saturn instead of Earth, so
I don't even want this
Earth thing any more.
So this is a bad kind of
memory cycle cuz this is gonna
keep that ImageViewController
in memory, so that's bad.
So this doesn't
want to do this, so
we're gonna fix this
one using weak self.
By the way, you know,
I showed that you can do,
weak weak self equals self.
But I'm a personally a fan
of when you're using weak on
self to just say weak self.
And all that does is inside
of this closure, it make
self be an optional version
of itself, cuz it's weak now.
So that means I have to do
this because if I do finally
come back from this closure
and the person has hit back,
then the ImageViewController
is gonna have left the heap.
And so self with be nil,
perfect, exactly what I want.
And if self is nil and I do
this little optional chaining,
then this whole line of
code is not gonna happen,
exactly what I want.
I do not want to create
an image out of that
information that came back.
Because that
ImageViewController has
left the heap.
So here I've broken this
memory cycle beautifully here.
Now, this does
beg the question,
surprised no one has
raised their hand.
How do I interrupt
this closure?
When I hit back, and that
ImageViewController goes away,
and I'm not interested
in Earth any more,
I'm still finishing the fetch,
of Earth.
And the answer is,
you can't stop a closure
that's been put on a queue,
you cannot stop it.
The only way it can stop
is if it quits itself.
So it could be looking at some
global state to see if it's
still relevant.
And if it sees,
I'm not relevant anymore,
it could return.
So if it was doing some
long running thing.
Could do that.
Or you can use something
like NSUrlSession
which is really smart about
going and getting URLs.
And it knows how to
be interrupted and
all the things like that.
So you could do something a
little smarter than just this
one line of code.
But once this goes on
the queue, it, it's gonna run.
So it's up to it to
decide not to run.
So we fix that problem of it,
but
there's still more
problems in here.
What happens if this
takes a minute,
or ten minutes because
slow network or whatever.
And we get back and
in the meantime,
someone called this on
my ImageViewController.
Now, our Cassini
can't do that, but
you could imagine an app that
would be showing something
in the ImageViewController.
And then you click
on something in
the ImageViewController itself
and it shows a different URL.
So someone calls this.
If I call this again,
it's gonna go down here and
fetchImage again, which is
here, and it's gonna dispatch
another closure off to
go get the new image.
So now there's two closures
out there fetching.
Now what happen when
the first one comes back?
What do I wanna do
with that image?
Ignore it.
Because the person said
they want a new one.
So I better put something in
here after this comes back to
see if I even care about
that anymore, which is easy.
I could just say for example
image == self?.imageURL.
So I'm sorry url
== self?.imageURL.
So I'm just gonna look at this
url, which is right here,
got captured by this closure.
This closure has
captured this url.
I'm just gonna check if
that url equals whatever
our current url is.
And if, if I'm not there,
then it's okay.
It's gonna be nil.
So if I can equal nil, and
there we go.
So here I just put a little
test in there to make
sure that I'm still
interested in that URL.
Can everyone understand
what's going on here,
where url = imageURL,
this is a constant, a constant
that got captured here.
So i's always gonna be
the URL that we went and
got the contents of.
Ther's yet
another problem here.
Can anyone tell me another
problem with this code,
obvious problem?
I just showed you
in the slides.
This right here,
self?.image is gonna
call this code down here.
That's gonna do all
kinds of UI stuff.
It's gonna set
the scrollView's content size,
size of the imageView,
size of the imageView's image.
This is all UI stuff.
Where does that
need to happen?
On the main queue.
And is this on the main
queue right here?
No, this is on this queue
over here, this global queue,
userInitiated global queue.
That's where this is
all happening, so
that's not the main queue.
So that is illegal.
That's gonna cause all kinds
of weird behavior in your app
if you do that.
But easily fitched, fixed,
we'll just ditch
DispatchQueue.main.async and
put this back on
the main queue.
Now what's really cool
about this syntax,
I guess you would say,
of doing these things is
it looks very much
logically like normal code.
Right, it's almost just
like if thens or whatever.
However, you do have to
understand that when you do
a dispatch like this, that's
gonna happen asynchronously.
It's gonna happen
in a different time
than the rest of this code.
Same thing with this one.
This is gonna happen
a little different time.
Now of course, things
that you put on the main queue
tend to run pretty quick.
But even so, you just have to
be cognizant of the fact that
even though it looks like this
line of code is gonna happen,
then this line, then this
line, then this line,
then this line,
it's not gonna happen.
It's gonna happen more
like the slides, right,
where things happen a little
bit out of order there
because things are happening
asynchronously.
Async means asynchronously,
out of time,
right, different,
not lined up in time.
Everybody got that?
Let's see if that fixes
all our problems.
So remember,
here we have no image.
By the way, this is a terrible
problem right here where this
comes up blank.
And I actually mentioned
last week that I was gonna
make it extra credit for
you to figure out how to not
make this blank in your
calculator, have it
come up with the calculator
instead of an empty graph.
But I decided instead I'm
gonna show you how to
do it today.
That's why I didn't
make it extra credit
in the assignment.
But anyway, so
here's the detail.
We haven't picked an image so
it's blank.
Now I'm gonna go back.
Here's our Cassini
viewController.
Now I'm gonna pick Earth,
and it's loading up, but
I changed my mind.
Saturn, changed my mind.
I can change my
mind now because
those things are being
fetched in some other thread.
Now if I wait long enough,
they get it and return it.
So here I am.
I have Cassini here.
If I go back and hit Earth,
again, I give up.
Saturn, I'll wait, and
we'll see if we get Saturn.
By the way, Saturn, this is
kind of a weird, I don't think
Cassini took this photo here,
this picture of the people.
But wait a minute,
look at that, there's Saturn.
One thing about this app,
though, that's kind of bad
is I click on this and
I get this white screen.
Especially on a big image like
this one we get this white
screen, it's white screen,
it's white screen.
It's like what's
happening in this app?
I don't even understand
what's going on.
It would be really cool if
I could give the user some
feedback about
what's happening.
Now this feedback might be
something that says loading
dot dot dot dot or something.
But a really cool feedback
when you're waiting for
something is a spinning,
a little spinner.
Have you seen those spinners?
A lot of apps have this where
there's a little spinner.
So let's add a spinner
to our app so
that when we click here,
it's a little thing spinning
until an image appears,
and then it goes away.
That turns out to be
incredible easy to do,
because that's a common thing
to want to do is to give
the user feedback.
Yes, I heard you and
I'm working on it, but
I don't have it yet.
How do we do that?
Let's go back to
our storyboard.
And this is where we're gonna
wanna do that is on this
viewController right here.
This is where our scrollView
is with our little
imageView in there.
And what we can do is just
go over over here and
get an object.
It's called
an Activity Indicator View.
Here it is right here, view
And I'm just gonna
drag this into my UI,
right in the middle.
Now what I just did there
was a very bad thing.
It looked fine,
but it's very bad.
And it's a little subtle
as to why it's bad, so
let's investigate this one in
depth why this was bad that
I dragged that in there.
And the way we gonna see
that it's bad is by bringing
out for the first time
this document outline.
This little thing in the lower
left which I told you we were
gonna talk about and
here we are talking about it.
This is everything that's
in our storyboard in
outline form,
in kind of text form.
And when we do this,
we look down here at this
Activity Indicator View.
By the way,
if you select something here,
it'll select it here and
vice versa.
So this is selected, so
it's showing it here.
And you see how these things,
this is all the views, this is
the top level view, that's the
view var in the controller.
Then here is that scrollView
that we made, and
then here is
the indicator view.
We see how these are indented,
that means they
are subviews of each other.
So we made the gray
activity indicator
a subview of our Scroll View,
we do not want that here.
We want our Scroll View
scrolling around our image,
we don't want it scrolling
our indicator around.
We want the indicator
to stay in the middle.
We don't want it to be
a subview of Scroll View,
we want it to be a sibling.
We want them both to
be at the same level,
one in front of the other.
And we can do that just by
picking this up right here,
and moving it to the same
level as Scroll View.
Now that's very hard to do in
here because any time you try
to pick this up and move it,
it's always gonna wanna try
and drop into a subview or
a superview of something, so
it's always gonna
grab on to it.
But in this document
outline it's very easy.
You can just pick it up and
move it there.
So when you do these activity
indicator views in your future
apps and
in your final project,
make sure you don't
accidentally make it a sub
view of something that
you drag it onto.
If it what you intend.
Notice also the order
matters here.
This is the sub views
in their, in order, and
remember that sub view sub
zero is in the back, and
all the other ones
are in the front.
So we obviously want this
activity indicator to
be in the front,
in front of everything.
All right, so that was that.
Now what we wanna do is we
want to wire this activity
indicator right here
up to our code.
Why?
Because we have to tell it to
start running.
Or actually even
before we do that,
let's configure
it a little bit.
We've got it right here,
we can inspect it.
Here's the inspector of it,
see Activity Indicator View.
It looks kind of small
to me for this big view.
So I'm gonna switch
to a different kind
which is the Large White.
But I don't actually
want it to be white
because the background
is white.
So I'm gonna change its
color to be, Iet's say blue.
So this can be large and blue.
Also, every time I stop
animating it, I want it to
hide itself, because I
don't want it to be stopped
spinning, sitting
there showing.
Any time it stops I
want it to disappear.
Then if I start it again,
it'll reappear.
So that's what this button is.
This here animating would
mean that it would come up
animating, but
I'm gonna turn it on any time
I go do a background fetch.
So I don't want it to come
up with this view animating
already.
That's what those all mean.
To turn it on I need
to talk to it, so
I need an outlet to it.
So I'm just gonna control drag
from it, just like any other
outlet we would make to
a button or whatever.
Here it is.
I'm gonna call it a spinner,
that's what I like to call
my UI activity indicators,
spinner.
There's my spinner
outlet right there.
All I need to do here is turn
this thing on whenever I
go off to another
thread to do something.
So here's where I go off
to another thread to do
something, so I'm just gonna
say spinner.startAnimating.
And that's gonna
start it spinning.
It's gonna unhide it,
if it was hidden, and
start it spinning.
Question?
>> Animated just make
thatlittle blue thing go round
It just makes it spin
just like all spinners.
and round.
>> Yeah, well,
when I inspected it over here.
And I did, and I didn't
click this button Animating,
that just means it doesn't
start out animating.
I have to start it in code,
that's what this means.
If I turn this on,
then as soon as my app came
up it would be animating,
which I don't want that.
I don't want it to start
animating until I do this
dispatch onto
some other queue,
that's when I want it
to start animating.
Now, you might imagine that
the place to stop animating it
might be right here.
spinner.stopAnimating, but and
this would kinda make sense.
Because you know, I went off
to go get this image and
it came back, and
I set the image.
Now I can stop animating.
But actually I don't
wanna do that here.
And that is because I
wanna stop animating
anytime the image is set.
If an image is set in my
image view controller,
I wanna stop animating.
I don't care how it got set.
If it got set from my thing
coming back, that's good.
If someone set it by saying,
image URL equals like a local
URL, I wanna stop then too.
So I'm gonna put it
down here an image.
Here's where we set our image.
This is the set part of it.
And I'm just gonna say
down here, stopAnimating.
So, any time my image is set
I'm gonna stop animating cuz
it would make no sense if
the image was there and
the thing was animating.
That would never
make sense for
an image to be showing, and it
to animate at the same time.
Because animating
this thing means I'm
waiting for an image.
Got it?
Touch it, that's all you have
to do to do the spinners,
they're super, super simple.
They only makes sense when
you're doing things in other
threads with the spinner.
Cuz if you're me, if you're
not doing something in another
thread then why would you?
See, now look.
This came up, it's blank but
it's not spinning
because I haven't asked for
anything yet.
So I'll go back here and
I'll ask for Earth.
It says nil while
doing Optional value.
That's not bad.
What happened here?
Ahh, yeah, good one.
All right, so this crashed.
Why did this crash?
Why did we have
a problem here?
And the answer here
is that when I set
this image I was in prepare.
And when I'm in prepare,
my outlets are not set.
So I need to optional
chain that right there.
So this crash,
you'll get it yourself a lot,
where you prepare
something and crash.
It crashes during prepare
because you try to set
your outlets.
Now, this is fine for
the spinner not to be set, and
I'm setting the image because
I never would have started it
in this condition anyway.
So all is well just to ignore
setting the image when I'm
preparing.
Everybody got that one?
You all have that, hundreds
of times in your iOS careers
where you have some code
that you'll prepare,
execute that uses an outlet.
All right, so let's go
back now, we hit Earth.
See it's spinning.
As soon as the image gets put
in here, it stops spinning,
all right, it's gone.
Okay, back here, spinning.
Yeah, we don't want it.
Let's go here, skip it here.
Now, the last thing I wanna
do is this thing where,
when the thing starts
up it starts up blank.
All right, it starts blank
because it's on the detail.
And I don't want
it on the detail
when there's no
image URL there.
I want it to start up here if,
when I first start.
All right, so
how do I do that?
I'm gonna do that using
the split view controllers.
If we go look at our
storyboard here.
I'm gonna use the delegate
of this split
view controller right here.
Because this split view
controller asks the delegate,
would you like to do the job
of collapsing the primary
view, the secondary
view controller rather,
you know the detail,
on top of the master?
Okay, so it's gonna give me
the opportunity to do that.
And what I'm gonna do is, if
there's no image URL in there,
I'm gonna say I did it but
I'm not gonna do anything.
And that's gonna cause it
not to collapse the detail
on top of the master.
Now, I need to have one of my
view controllers be the split
view controller's delegate.
And I can't really have
it be this one right here
because this one comes and
goes.
This is the Image View
Controller. It gets created
when it's segued to and
when you go away, it stops.
You go throw it
out of the heap.
So I can't have my split view
controller's delegate thrown
out of the heap all the time,
so
instead I'm going to have this
view controller be my split
view controller's delegate.
So here we go.
Here's my
CassiniViewController.
Now where is a good place to
set yourself as your own split
view controller's delegate?
You could probably
do it in view and
load and that would work.
But I think a better,
safer place to do
it is awakeFromNib.
Cuz awakeFromNib if
you remember from from
the ViewController life
cycle is called really early
in the game.
So if I wanna set my own
splitViewController's
delegate to myself, delegate.
This is really early
time to do it.
Now notice here
that I'm taking my
own splitViewController
which might be nil,
because I might not be in
a splitViewController.
And I'm setting its
delegate to myself.
Remember, every
ViewController has this bar
splitViewController which
is the splitViewController,
it's in if it is in one.
And so
I'm getting an error here,
anyone know what
this error is?
Nobody?
It says that you can not
assign a CassiniViewController
to be a
UISplitViewControllerDelegate.
You can't make this equal
this, that's because this is
CassiniViewController is
not a UISplitViewDelegate.
UISplitViewControllerDelegate.
We have to say that it's a
Okay, once we say that,
that resolves this error.
All the methods in that
protocol are optional.
So, we've satisfied
the protocol,
which is kinda weird.
But now we can implement
any of the ones we want.
Here's a trick for you.
If you want,
if you're a delegate and
you wanna find out
what methods are,
just start typing
the name of the class.
So here's splitView and
here's all the
splitViewControllerDelegates.
You have to have done
this part first.
You have to say you're
a delegate first.
Once you do that, it's gonna
show all these, right,
these are all the things
splitViewDelegate can do.
And we want this one
right here at the top.
CollapseSecondary onto
primary.
So I'm gonna
double-click that.
I'll show you these arguments
a little easier to see if I do
this.
That and then this one.
So this
splitViewControllerDelegate
method has three arguments,
one is the sender,
that's the splitViewController
asking you.
Here, it's asking
me please collapse
this secondaryViewController,
that's a detail onto
this primaryViewController
that's the master.
So this what happens when we
first start up, a blank detail
gets put on top of the master,
and we don't want that.
But we only don't want that
if that detail is blank.
So I'm gonna go here and say
if the PrimaryViewController
is myself, because if the
PrimaryViewController is not
myself, then the things
are gone weird here,
but it should be.
So I'm gonna say if the
PrimaryViewController.conte-
nts, because I might be in
navigation controller equals
myself, remember contents
is this thing down here.
So, I'm doing that there.
Then I say if I can let
the ImageViewController equal
the secondaryViewController,
that's the detail.
It's this argument right here.
It can pass to me,
it's the thing that is asking
me to collapse on top of it.
SecondaryViewController as
an ImageViewController.
And again here,
I wanna do contents.
So that's inside
the NavigationController.
But that's not all.
It's not just if I have
an ImageViewController being
asked to collapse
on top of me.
But I wanna make sure
that that IVC's imageURL.
Equals nil.
So if splitViewController's
asking me to collapse
an ImageViewController
that has a blank image,
I'm going to return true
to say, yep, I did it.
But I'm not actually
going to do anything.
Because I don't want
that to happen.
So I'm kinda faking out this
splitViewController there.
Otherwise I'm gonna return
false, which means, no,
I couldn't do this collapse,
so you do it.
Now the splitViewController
will do it itself.
So it's kinda funky, but I
just wanted to show you this,
to show you that there are a
little more complicated ways
to do things then
I sometimes show.
But look what happened.
I ran and I did not get
that blank VieController.
Because I told
splitViewController
that I collapsed it on there,
but I didn't really so
it did nothing.
But if I click on one now the
image url is not nil and so
it did do the collapse for me.
All right, so that's it.
Let's get back to our slides
and do our last topic here.
Which is our text field.
So I'm just gonna throw
in text field in here,
cuz you're, it's going to be
included in our next demo and
in your next assignment, it's
a pretty easy little class,
UITextField.
It's very similar to UILabel.
The difference is
it's editable.
UILabel, if you touch on it,
nothing happens.
But you do UITextField,
if you touch on it,
a little blinking cursor
happens and the keyboard will
come up from the bottom, and
you can use your thumbs and
type, or, if you have an iPad
with a physical keyboard,
you could type or whatever.
That's all the UITextField is.
Now because it's editable,
it's got some little
intricacies that are quite
a bit different than UILabel.
It still has things
like attributed text,
and you can set the font,
and all these things,
because it's very much like
a UILabel in that way.
But there's this keyboard,
okay, when you are in
UITextField and you touch on
it, it brings up a keyboard.
So how does that keyboard
show and not show?
Well, the keyboard shows
any time, any view,
in the view hierarchy,
becomes the first responder or
what's called
the first responder.
And the first responder means
it wants to be the thing that
gets key events
from the keyboard,
it's the first responder for
key events.
You can make your UITextField
start it cursor blinking and
make the keyboard come up by
sending it the message become
first responder.
If you tell your UITextField
to become the first responder,
the keyboard will appear, so
that's how you make
the keyboard up here.
And similarly if you want
the keyboard to go away and
the blinking caret to go away,
say resignFirstResponder
to the TextField that is the
current first responder and
it will go away.
So that's how you
control the keyboard.
UITextField has a delegate.
It has about actually
ten delegate methods.
Can do quite a lot of
interesting things.
For example, when the keyboard
comes up, most keyboards,
have a Return key in
the lower right hand corner.
And when you hit
that Return key,
you get this delegate method.
Text field show return,
it returns a bool.
It's basically saying,
should I do what I normally
do when you press Return?
Because text fields
are also controls,
they can do target action.
So it's kind of
asking you here,
should I do target
action today?
You know, some control
dragged to an IBaction,
should I send that?
It's what it's asking here
what should I return.
But one thing you can do and
should return you might return
yes, but you might also
resignFirstResponder.
Because when it hits Return,
you want the keyboard
to go away.
Because otherwise
the keyboard will not go away
when it hits Return.
Even if you have
target action,
it's not gonna make
that keyboard go away.
It's very common that you
wanna implement a text
field delegate,
just to make the keyboard go
away when you hit Return.
What other delegate methods
does a TextField have?
You can find out every time
it resigns first responder.
It will send its delegate
the method didEndEditing.
So this is a good way to find
out, I'd better get the text
out of there and
go do something with it.
Because someone hit Return, or
did something that caused
resignFirstResponder to happen
so this method
gets sent to you.
In fact, this is probably
a more common way to
get the text out
of a text field
then target/action is to
implement its delegate.
And in end editing you get
the text out of there.
Or you could even grab it
out of there in should
return if you want.
So text field is a control.
You can do target action,
just Ctrl drag.
It has certain events that can
cause target action to happen
just like a button actually.
And you can right click on a
text field in a storyboard to
see what it can do there.
The keyboard, you can change
the kind of keyboard.
The keyboard, for example,
there's a keyboard for
entering URLs, and it's got
a button on there, .com.
I think it even has a button,
HTTP so
that you can quickly
enter a URL.
There's another URL which
is like a phone dialer,
which is the keypad, or
another, a keypad rather.
It's like a phone dialer, so
it just has the numbers or
whatever.
So you can specify that.
And the way you specify
those things is you
don't send any messages
to any keyboard object.
You send it to any object that
is using the keyboard that
implements the protocol
UITextInputTraits.
UITextInputTraits is
a protocol that has
all these things
shown here in it and
when you send it to
something like a text field
it configures its
keyboard to match that.
If you want auto correction
in your text field,
where you're typing and
you're mistyping, and
it's autocorrecting as you go,
you can get that.
Just set your auto correction
type there to .yes in your
text field.
So you're sending these,
these vars are on text field.
But they're on text field
because text field implements
the UITextInputTraits
protocol.
And you can do secure text for
passwords and
all that kind of stuff.
In other words, if you're
looking to control your
keyboard, don't look
in text field per se,
go look at this
UITextInputTrait protocol, and
you'll see what you can do for
your keyboard.
You can also set an accessory
view in your keyboard,
a little view along the top of
your keyboard that is just for
your app.
That's kind of fun.
You just, again,
just TextInputTraits
protocol thing.
One thing about the keyboard,
I'm actually not gonna talk
about this because of time.
We'll talk about this
in a later lecture.
But the keyboard when it comes
up it actually covers up
your views.
So you better make sure that
text field is not underneath
the keyboard.
Otherwise keyboard
will come up and
people will not be able
to type in your text.
And I see a lot of final
projects that do this,
where you have
your nice UI and
you've got a lot of
text fields on there.
And you've got some text
fields towards the bottom of
the screen and when I try to
run your app and do it and
I click it, I am running
it on a real device,
there's no keyboard I can't
type in the simulator.
One thing about when you're
doing text field, be careful
because in the simulator you
can just type on the keyboard.
But in the real world
the keyboard's gonna slide out
from the bottom.
So students often will do
their final projects do
the whole thing
in the simulator.
They only barely do it on
the device even though that's
absolutely required for
your final project by the way.
And they turn it in and bam
they get dinged pretty hard
because I can't use their app.
Because this keyboard comes up
and covers up the text fields
that they're wanting
me to enter text into.
The way you find out
about the keyboard and
where it came over is
using these observers.
And you're basically gonna
observe the window, and
the window is gonna send you
this little notification that
says, hey, keyboard just came
up, and in the notification
that's sent to you,
there's gonna be information
about the rectangle that the
keyboard used to cover you,
and you have to move
your UI out of the way.
Hopefully you're in a
scrollable thing like a table
view or just a scroll view.
But if not then you just gotta
move, set the frame of your
super view or something
to move that thing up.
Because it's your
responsibility to make sure
that the keyboard is not
covering something that's
necessarily to user UI.
So when you're doing
your final projects
do it on a device.
Otherwise you are very likely
to run into this problem.
So we'll talk about
these observers,
these notification sender and
stuff in a future lecture.
There's other text
field properties not
related to the keyboard, like
it does the auto shrinking and
all that stuff that we
saw with UI labels so
you can control that
stuff with text field.
I'll let you look at the doc
to figure all that stuff out.
Text fields also have a little
right and left accessory view.
These little overviews for
like a search button.
Or little, you can put little
exclamation points in there,
things like that.
So you can look for
that as well.
That's it.
On Wednesday I'm
gonna do TableView.
Big old lecture with
a big old demo.
And that's what your
homework's gonna be about.
Friday, we have a section
it's going to be on
CollectionView which I'd love
to teach in main lecture
because it's really
an important class.
It's very much like
TableView but more flexible,
a little more powerful
than TableView.
You kind of need to
know TableView first,
that's why we do TableView
on Wednesday and
then the CollectionView
on Friday.
Then next week I'll be doing
the object oriented database,
called Core Data, and you'll
be integrating that into your
assignment 4 to make
your assignment 5.
That's it, see you then.
>> For more please visit
us at stanford.edu.